When I was a child, I was fearless and I want to go
back there. You know, I keep trying to figure out
how I. How I go back to the six year old
me that completely didn't get what people mean when something
was difficult. Before quantum computing, before titles and
credentials, there was a fearless 6 year old. Welcome
to Women in Quantum.
Welcome to Women in Quantum, a podcast about curiosity,
courage, and the many paths that lead women into
one of the most exciting frontiers of science
and technology. This isn't just about equations
or labs, it's about people, the moments that
sparked curiosity, the obstacles along the way,
and decision to stay when things got hard.
You don't need a technical background to listen.
If you've ever wondered whether there's a space for you in deep
tech, this podcast is for you. I'm
your host, Candice Gilhooly, and this is Women
in Quantum. Today we are speaking
with Anna Beita Kalish
Hedegaard. She is the CEO and at
Quantum Security Defense and Quantum Prime.
Welcome. Ana. How are you today? Thank you, I'm
good. Thank you for having me, Candice. I'm looking forward to the
conversation. Excellent. I'm really, really excited. You
know, in the green room, we had this little
discussion about names and I just thought what you said about your
name is fantastic. Would you like to repeat it?
I guess you mean that my name exists in so many countries and
it's pronounced in so many different ways? It is.
I think it's very international and over years,
because I lived in six countries and also met people
from around the world. And I always found it very
fantastic that people can connect over a name, you know, and
it brings a bond. And they were like, oh, in my country, your
name is this and this. And I was like, oh, that's lovely.
It always made me feel welcomed. I think that's great.
I think that really kind of immediately eliminates barriers
and it actually brings people to a single point of
commonality. And if you can find that single point from the very
beginning, I think you've already won most of the battle.
So I think that's wonderful. I think that's really, really great. I love it. My
maiden name, I just want to mention is Rechtschaffen, which
is German, which when you break it down means right
thinking. And it's not really even
like a real name if you think about it. It was a name that was
created, you know, in the 1700s,
you know, for, for, you know, people who like the Germanic
lifestyle and mentality. So they chose Rectschafen
which was German for right thinking. Right. But it's like not like really,
really like a name like Smith or Baker or things like that. Right.
So I always find names, etymology. Really, really exciting.
So let's start at the very beginning. Okay. So when you look
back at the very beginning, not your credentials,
just you. What kind of person were you before
Quantum entered your life? I
was very little. I
was very wild, extremely
energetic, curious.
Um, and I. I just loved doing things
and being creative. I've always loved words.
I. I just loved running around. I was also
very doing sports and, and just exploring. I thought
it was. I always wanted to do everything and. And it just was
a such a hunger to understand things
around me and it didn't matter. I loved learning about diseases.
I loved learning math and I loved playing
tennis. You know, like it just. And I always been
fascinated with people, you know, and like how
they are, how they different, how they think and
stories and I loved stories so much
and being very sensitive person and
always lived through. If I read a book, you could talk to me and I
couldn't hear you. If I watched a movie I was in, I was very
fully immersed when I was doing things.
So was there. So you obviously were drawn to math and science
very early on, right? Yes. And then you
continued that curiosity. Was there ever a moment
a teacher, a certain experience when you might have learned a
certain concept that really it made science
feel truly possible for you?
That's a good question. Well, I was at home. Like my mom
is mathematician, so I guess this way
of thinking. I would say that I was more inspired by a
logical way of thinking about stuff and like problem solving
than rather something very specific. At my
science lessons I thought they were just cool because they were describing the world,
you know, but there was this critical way of
faking analyzing things. That was something that was
at home, that was something that was also
precious and it was very respected. Oh,
you, you can analyze things, you can think about it that way. And was
always encouraged. And I think that inspired me
to maybe not only the sciences, but be
curious about problems to be solved. And science is just
one of the places you can apply the things. Like an obvious
place. Okay, so you were. I mean that's
it. You were encouraged from so early to pursue
this kind this sector. You know, it doesn't
sound like you really had the typical experience that like
that young girls face where maybe they're not having their
questions answered or they're not giving answers in the classes that the
teachers aren't picking them and they're kind of found
a way to kind of push girls, you know, away from the
sciences and math. You had such a strong, you know, inspiration
from your family that you didn't really have to think of it any other way.
You didn't necessarily have the obstacles, did you? Did you notice
that there were not a lot of girls around you that were pursuing the same
things as you? Yes, and I think
I've been. I would say that it was not so pink as
you painted it for me. I did very
quickly got lots of signals that
my interest, my energy, the way I was
approaching things was very non girlish. So almost
everywhere where I engage, it was
I wanted too much or like, you don't have to.
And people always had some level of opinion why I should not
be interested in math or why I should not be good in math. Even I
was really good in math. There was always like, oh,
but that's for sure because you're still young and it has nothing to
do with your future potential. So I was picking it up from
every side. And I think even
weirdly enough, at home there was
this perception that, oh, maybe the world will not get me.
So they were trying to somehow, you know, you also have to do
this because the world will not understand you like that, you know,
like, so there was these signals that the way I am and
my interests do not fit. That's not normal.
And as a child it's very confusing. Right? Because
what else should I like, if not the things I like? You know, like you
don't. And I. I think what saved me a
lot was that I always thought that that
was bizarre. I never thought they right and
I am wrong. I always thought they wrong. This is so
weird. Like I was. I always had this voice
in my head that is not okay. Like there is
nothing what I want that. It's absurd. Like, and
it kept me sane and it kept me
truthful to what I wanted as much as
possible. It's not like I didn't suffer, but. But
still, this voice is like something that protected my
little dreams and my ambitions.
How do you think we could make that better for
the young women who, you know, young girls.
Let's go back to girls. Girls that are, you know, in. In
middle school, in high school. What can we
do for them to show them that it
shouldn't be like, well, you don't have to do that, dear. You know,
like, oh, okay, so you're, you're good at that now,
dear. But like, let's see what happens, you know, there'll be something else, that you're
more suited. I mean, do you. What do you think that we
could do? Well, there has
to be girls that appear in books. You know, there have to be. I
was, I think a lot about it. I have kids myself, and I
have a little girl in this age. And I'm
always thinking, what can I do more? So
what I did, I just bought every single book where the girl
is a main character. And
to the extent that my son was like, but he
thinks sometimes that some of the female characters are cooler.
And on the beginning, he was like, are boys always
sidekicks? You know, like, he, he, he. He got
this schedulity. Of course. Then when he went to the
kindergarten, it got all explained to him that, no, you know,
the men are the. The leaders.
It's very quick. So it actually happens very quickly. And I
think we need as much as possible
representation and cool girl characters.
And something that really hit me
also with my kids was when you ask my son
who he would like to be when he watched
Frozen, he wanted to be Elsa.
And you know what it like, hit me. This is what we need
as women, as girls. We need such
cool female characters that boys
would be like, well, if I was to dress up in this
universe, I would be a girl. Because often when
you watch a movie, right, when you watch a Superman, do you really want
to be Lois Lane? Or you really would like to be a Superman, right?
Like you want to be a sport? There's no way. And I want that
for little girls, and we can get there because stories
is. They so powerful. They. They carry
us, they care. They. They explain us the world when we kids. And
actually they explain us the complex world when we are adults.
The stories, the movies. I think that that is
the key to really get to the heart of it. Because everything
later is kind of too late. We are correcting
for a culture that already is showing.
Well, you kind of the second one, right? Because the coolest
character is a boy. You know,
that's, you know, Harry Potter is Harry Potter.
Right, right. No, no, that's absolutely true. And that's it. If,
if girls see themselves in what they're
interested in, then again,
they'll feel more comfortable pursuing it. And it
won't feel like it's something strange to pursue. It would feel like
it's something natural. But I think you made a great point. Like your son
wanted to be Elsa. Like, she was the coolest character
there was. You know, he felt. And
justifiably so. I think it's a Whole
reframing of the situation, right? Like, you know, yes,
Harry Potter had Hermione, right? But why wasn't Hermione
the main character. She could so much be. The book was written by
a woman, right? It could be her.
And, and, and the impact of that,
that type of stories that we could bring to the world that girls
would also have those powerful characters. I love it. I love,
like, I love the movie when they made Ghostbusters and it was all starred women.
Did you see it? It was wonderful. I loved it.
I loved it. Or when they did the, they did like the Ocean's Eleven
movie but then they had all women in it instead of it all
being an all male cast. And it was, it was a, it was brilliant.
It was. I don't know if you saw I. That I love it
so much, right. I want, and I want to see women
doing weird jokes. I want us to do
bad things. I want us to, you know, I want, I want women
to take all those different roles. I want them be silly. I want
them be, you know, awkward. I, I want that they take
that spaces where we were completely erased from.
We were put into pretty clothes, doing pretty
face. But I want to see women filling all those different
other characters and owning them,
you know, like, and I appreciate, I appreciate when
they being even vulgar because I think that we need,
that we need those women characters, you
know, in the movies when they do all different sorts
of things and, and, and there's
so much space to fill it so that
we all can be like, oh, I'm also sometimes so
angry. You know, I'm also sometimes that
lazy. I want, I want that. I want to not only have this
perfect image of women, I want to have this whole
complexity, complexity that men have. And we
crave, I think we crave it. I think
so. I think you're totally right. I think you're totally right.
So let me, so let me understand. You know, I'm understanding a
bit about the beginning. And you were very well nurtured for
it. So when did you turn directly to
physics itself? You see, for
me, physics was a random choice. I thought I was rebellious
when I chose physics because I didn't choose math like my mom.
So I somehow in my head I
didn't knew what I wanted to do. I was good in science, I liked
sciences. And then physics was just this, you know,
okay, I'm not gonna do a math like my mom, you know, I'm gonna do
physics. And then I did
physics, I did electronics, telecommunication,
and there were things I Liked always.
And there were things I did not. And then I used
that as a guidance since I didn't have a fixed plan. I
had this voice about teleportation as a kid,
but I could not use it for a job. I was
always very confused why it's there. I was exploring it.
I even thought that maybe I should do special effects in the
movies because that was the closest. But then the
exam was from the humanistic knowledge and I was like,
I have no idea what that means. So it was much easier to
pass math exams and physics to go to the
university. That something that was very open
ended for me what it means humanistic knowledge.
So I've just chosen that because it seemed right.
It seemed like I. I've also thought when I was young that I have
plenty of time to figure it out. And I think
this childish aspect of my approach, I'm not saying
it's good approach, it's just, you know, sharing with you how I did it. I
just always naturally first
engaged with the world and then tried
to fit how that feels for me
and not take it for granted what my path has to be,
but more like exploring. And that's how
I approach also my education. I was just exploring it.
Always learning, always being ambitious,
but taking it as, oh, I'm exploring. This is not my
end point. It, it's just I still don't know.
And, and then I was. Then it took me to Denmark. It took me
to study inflation theory on the beginning of the universe.
It took me to the labs to work on nanoparticles.
It then took me to US to work on radars and antennas.
It just kept taking me places and
work on so many different technology
projects. I went to Malaysia, also worked on antennas with
carbon nanotubes. Went back, studied cosmology and the
field theory on the beginning of the universe. Then took
a job in a, as a, as a patch in the patent office and
worked on a. Airflows in the,
you know, inhalators for asthma
and studying that there. And then I worked on air pollution
and went into AI because of the amount of data and it was
all just curiosity learning.
And then when I had to make my decision, you know, I was, I was
ready. Like, it's like, oh, what I really
could do is entrepreneurship
and I love it. But I, I think I needed all that
complex path before, you know, so I could get to know what I like.
Okay. It's interesting, right? Because that's it. Like so you
were trying all these different ideas to see, oh, I like this, but I don't
like that. And then you're constantly pivoting and adjusting or
at the same time being given these amazing opportunities to go all
around the world and try out different things
all around the world to see kind of what you were really excited about.
So how did it feel to be recognized among the
top 10 women in engineering in Poland?
It meant so much.
It was. It was like coming back home
when you. After all the traveling, I don't live anymore in Poland, you
know, and then going back and then
being put on a stage and being able to share, you know,
my childhood fascination with teleportation and that it took me on
this amazing journey and then entrepreneurship
and then having people coming, I think it was just like,
oh, I. I come from this place, you know,
that's my. That's my home place. You know, that's my comfort food place.
You know, if I'm. If I'm having tough time, I always crave Polish
food. There is just no way around it. And then going
back and getting a prize saying, hey, we see
you, you know, you are abroad, but we proud of what you do. I
felt it like, like a hug, you know, it was nice,
meant a lot. It's nice like a hug. I like that.
So what's challenged you more along the way? Has it been
technical difficulty, self doubt,
or how others have perceived you?
I guess all of three.
Somehow it's a mix. I mean, technology is tough. I mean, doing
quantum and engineering and
theory, I mean, it's. It's hard.
But I also realize, I remember when I was
studying theoretical physics in Denmark, I realized that
and had those conversations actually with my colleagues. So that
the way they were approaching that, it's difficult. It was very different
than me. And they were like, oh, this is difficult.
I just have to keep reading it many times and then it's gonna be
okay. I was like, oh, my God, this is so difficult. There is something
wrong with me. Maybe I don't get it. And.
But even this, the fact that I had colleagues with
whom I could talk about it and they would share like, oh, they. And
I remember it made me think like, I didn't understand it. You know, it
didn't change my way of thinking, but it really made me. Made me think,
like, okay, it's not me. It is just
difficult. And. But the way I'm approaching it
holds me back and slows me down. And
so the same in entrepreneurship, I feel like,
keep reflecting. I reflect a lot. I spend a lot of
time on the. Developing my emotional Intelligence.
And then I'm really uncovering a lot of things that were given to me that
I should be afraid of. Difficult things that. Exactly.
Going back to this, what we discussed, you know, in a childhood, that
the response to my energy is like oh, this is
too much, you know. And then when you put that energy
out you'll be like, okay, am I stepping over the boundaries?
And that is difficult because it comes in so
many different phases. It comes on the feedback that
sometimes like oh, maybe that means if someone is tough. To
me the first thought would be maybe I don't belong
here. Like it's a, it's this subtle thing
that immediately tells me oh, but the truth is
they just tough and I, I have to
learn. Oh, this is difficult word to say relearn it,
you know, and correct it in my head. No,
you're doing difficult thing. This person is
tough. That's how they are. You belong here. But you maybe
don't want to hang out on everyday basis, you know. But like
reframing things for, for myself because the
signals are very strong in a childhood and they
set up so much.
So yes, self doubt is, is big all the
time. So that kind of leads
me to, you know, how is your
relationship with confidence changed over time?
Wow, that's a very complex question.
I see it way more
subtle I think. And so I, when I was
a child I was fearless and I'm keep come I want to go back there.
You know, I'm keep trying to figure out how I,
how I go back to the six year old me that
completely didn't get what people mean when something was
difficult. You know, when I was, when I wanted to be on the stage,
I did not care that I was not that good in music.
I did not care. I knew I don't have a talent, mind
you. I knew. But I knew that if I spend
day in and day out practicing, I'm gonna nail
it and I'm going to be so good that I can be on the stage
and perform and I'm going to be afraid. But it didn't matter. I
wanted to be there. I want to be back that person. Because over
years I got self doubt and self
doubt actually and the lack of confidence
came from the fact that it was bizarre that I was
not afraid. It was bizarre, it was weird. So it was constantly
repeated to me, well why do you want
it? Like why? It's like well I don't know, like
I don't have, I just want it and then, then I just do what I
want you know, like you won't go and play football. I don't
want it. But I want to play on a stage. That's what I want at
the moment. And, and I would like to go back to that confidence and
I'm still not there. I'm still carrying this
social heritage, you know, of,
of what was given to me. But now over the
last, I said four or five years,
I learned to catch up myself on that.
I catch where the voices are not mine. You
know, they are like, whoa, I don't
think that matters. You know, like, like I just, I just start to talk with,
with myself inside and with those doubts and then.
Right. Rebuild my. As an
adult woman that already have the experience in between, you
know, when I was holding myself back and it did not make
me happy. And when, every time when I
doubt, I see that, you know,
they were wrong. And each time I take a challenge,
you know, okay. I mean sometimes I'm not that good. You know, it's not like
every time I'm on the stage I'm like a star. But you know what,
it's okay. I then go again and then I'm a little bit better
and that's okay. It is failing. So I
started to redefine it that I simply
can do it. And my goal is to get to this like a 6 year
old that totally didn't get. It was oblivion to what
people were telling her. I
really, I appreciate that. I think as women professionally
in all fields, self doubt is
our biggest enemy. And you
know, the whole imposter syndrome and do we know what we're talking about
and why do we even doubt it right when
we've been doing it, why we doubt that, why we doubt ourselves the way
we do. And it's definitely outside force
coming in making you constantly question what
do you really know and are you sure? So
what's so interesting to me also is that you
are a physicist by trade, but now
you've gone over across the bridge to
industry as a CEO and founder
and there's a lot of people out there in
our audience who are on the academic
side and they want to go over across the bridge to the
other side. It's that journey that
they don't necessarily know how to do.
What do you find were some of the biggest
personal and professional challenges that you faced when you were transitioning?
Transitioning, that's a hard one. Transitioning
from academic science into entrepreneurship and
leadership. It's
a, it's a different world where you
sell different things and you
in academia you sell your expertise,
your knowledge on the big, especially on the beginning in
a career right later on also when you go to the leadership,
you start to be more a person that has to bring funds.
And I think that starts to be much closer to entrepreneurship.
But typically the people that want to transition, they just finished, let's say
their PhD, they very. So their experience with
research and academia is very
heavy based in
knowing things. And when you go to
business world, it's not about what you know,
unless that's the only thing you want to sell. Okay, like some
but. And you can do business based on that.
But the scalable businesses, okay, are typically the
businesses where it's really little about you,
about what you know, and it's very much about what other
people need and how you can deliver the value for
them. So. And
that shift when you're in academia
and you're specializing in something typically very
niche, but the value and
prestige put on it is so big, you've been
pursuing it so much, it's really hard to let go.
And you want to know. You want to know everything. But when you
do business, it's very often not about what you know,
but how much you listen to other people, what they need.
So it's. It shifts the conversation a bit
from you to other people. And then you have to figure
out what a lot of people need if you want to
scale your business and how you can really deliver the value
to them. And I think that
that's very hard because when you're studying, your
whole identity is built about you being
smart. And suddenly it really
doesn't matter. Like it, like, I'm not saying it's like
completely, but, you know, it just doesn't matter. Like, it's
great that big owners of the companies,
they smart. But the truth is we are not buying the
products because they smart. We buying the products or the things
because those are good products and they fulfill our needs.
And that means that. But they somewhere along the way
stopped looking only what they think it's cool. But
started to really listen what people would need.
That's a big shift. And also the fact that
it's exactly. You need to suddenly care less about.
Again, knowledge. I think that's encapsulating everything because
it doesn't matter. You're producing papers, it doesn't mean how many papers you
read. It really matters if your business is running and it's very
pragmatic in the end and you
need to engage way more with people. And
yeah, and that can be hard because it's A very different lifestyle suddenly.
That's totally fair. That's completely fair. So as
the leader of Quantum Security Defense and Quantum
prime, how do you define your
mission? What's the problem
in Quantum that you're so passionate about solving?
So it, I would separate it. So something that I already
mentioned that really brought me to this field is teleportation
and I am so fascinated with that.
And I, and that's where Quantum prime got
built. That's how I've built my professional network.
And I'm still so fascinated
and, and when I meet people that you know, they add that
little brick to my understanding of that picture. I
have some, I, I dream in pictures, right?
What, what, what this dream of teleportation could be
and I don't know what's my role in there. And I'm exploring it
and, and Quantum prime was a part of it.
And it's still a fascination
with intelligent networks of the possibility of teleporting
data. I would hope that in my lifetime we will
teleport human consciousness. I'm super excited
about it and I'm following it and always
up for a conversation about technology, but also
what it would mean and ethically or capabilities.
What on the other hand, Quantum security, the
defense is this even
deeper need for me. And something
that always been part of me is fascination with people and how
different they are. I loved meeting people around the world. I loved
living places, hearing people and
building a global network to talk about
business and technology. So
the mission is to connect as many
people as possible together, to exchange knowledge,
to build businesses, to learn together.
I am not sure if there is an end point. It's more like
I want to build a vehicle for a journey
and then deliver value and facilitated
for as many people as possible that they can understand it and
be part of it just because it's cool
and just because they can build career while doing something
amazing. And you know, it's,
it can be contagious. And I think building communities
when people can get together and
exchange knowledge, I think it's precious. I always thought that
that was fun. You know, even as a child I always been in so many
different clubs. So I loved it.
So quantum computing and cybersecurity are
incredibly complex fields. How do you
explain quantum safe security to non technical
audiences?
When I have to tell my parents, I guess they are like the good,
good place to start. I actually just tell them that
it matters because of everything what they do
nowadays. My parents just recently had to get their
digital identities on their phone.
They were actually like, oh, yeah, we did it to protect
our data because there we can define what we want
to share and what we don't want to share. It gives us a bit of
control over our data. So
I always start with something that people can understand, their privacy,
you know, like, well, you want to have it protected.
If you send something, you want that only the recipient
have access to it, you know, no matter what it is. Even if you
send a cringy two cute photos to
your grandma, you know, because
you want to make her feel loved and whatever it's
meant only for her and
explaining it now that you know, there
is so many more tools that can
attack that privacy, that can take advantage of the information that
is taken over and that there is also
solutions to it and that it's worth exploring,
then I don't have to mention Quantum at any point to
have them with me. Because in the end,
it's not about technology.
It's back to this, like, you know, the science and the business.
It's not really about the technology. It's about that
really delivers the value that people care about. And I
think in this world, especially now when our
privacy, you know, got so attacked
and it creeped on us without even us
realizing, you know, that our photos can be snapped
and they can be used in so many ways, it all kind of creeped in
before we realized that our privacy is
so hard to keep. And,
and I think people relate to that very quickly. And
Quantum is just a new tool to,
well, attack, but also to protect
our data. Right. It's just the next level.
So you talk about Quantum being a tool and you talk about,
you know, explaining technology without even mentioning
Quantum, which I think is brilliant. Are there any other
strategies that you use when you're teaching or explaining these
ideas to students or business
folk? Well, it depends. Right?
It always depends on the person that is on the other side. Right. The, the,
the connection and communication always starts to whom you
talk to. You know, it's. You need to meet them
where they are and what they care about. And of course you can take
them on a journey, but you not always might know them that
well. Right. But if you can at least meet them
what they know, then you can make them care about
it. If you just throw at them a lot of science. I think people are
fascinated with Quantum. With Quantum, it's a little bit easier. I've been giving
talks to really broad audiences and
people were coming back and it's like, oh, it always
fascinated me, you know, this Quantum world
and that it's there, you know, so, so there
is curiosity is there so you can.
And then I typically listen what they curious about and they
come from so many different angles on it. Sometimes they remember
what they learned in a primary school and, and then
I start right there with them and we explore,
you know, the cat in a box or sometimes they already
fascinated, you know, with the beginning of the universe and
how magical and like mind blowing it is. And that's
where they, you know, or they have sometimes
some models already in their head. And I typically try
to see what, you know, where the curiosity seed is.
And those are very fascinating things. And quantum has a magic
to it that people heard it. You know,
people heard about teleportation, people heard about parallel
universes, but with business people it's
different. Right? So when you talk with people that you just want them
to come and like, hey, be curious about it because it's so much
fun. But there is, when you speak business, it's, it's
back again. It's less about what it is, it's really how
it solves the problems. It's back to this logical thinking
of this is your problems and this is the
things that could solve that problem for you.
Okay. And then you meet them where they, where
they are with the problems that they care about solving.
And you know, quantum is a problem.
I mean if we're gonna have a quantum computer out there, it's.
There's so many problems to solve and lots of people
should get engaged because we will need every brain
out there to solve access to it.
Such a powerful tool, how we should have access to
it. And that conversation needs
lots of thinking and lots of voices that are definitely non
technical because as humanity we develop also
other tools. You know, it's
laws, it's a governance, it's diplomacy, it's
the language. All of that will have to
define how we interact with those new
tools. And people should
care. The same as I think we did great with climate. My best
example is like, you know what, we did a good job to engage people
with climate change. We finally broke it where
people actually get it, where it meets them.
And I think we will be able to do it with tech. We just have
to keep on trying. Okay,
let me ask you this. What's one common misconception
about quantum computing that you think needs reframing?
You see, I'm doing it all the time, so I
talk with so many technical people, you know, so I sometimes
forget how it is to approach it as non technical person. Right.
It's like living In a bubble, you know, where people mostly speak. Yeah. And
then we are nitpicking on little details and we forget what's the
big picture. I think the biggest misconception
that would matter to a broader audience is that
quantum computer is not something that is an
isolated entity. It's
interconnected to all other technologies that we already
have to all other things that are developing. So if
we have AI development going on,
if we have blockchains, if we have social media and also
our lifestyle evolving quantum computer, when it
will arrive, it will not be just a quantum computer.
And the way it will impact us will be
intertwined into all of that
that is constantly evolving. And treating it
as just another tool is
undermining it. Just as we've undermined AI, you
know, we really did not expect
how AI will completely solve how we engaged with machines.
And then we will also get surprised by the quantum
computers and its capabilities that will be
under, you know, under everything. When you talk to your phone,
you don't talk. You, you keep forgetting that it's AI
driven. AI on so many different levels in so many different
applications. We just got used to it. And one
day there's going to be quantum computer making
engagement with every single machine even
more immersing, and we will get
surprised about it. And I think the misconception is that it's
just quantum computing. It's powerful, it's quantum computing,
but it's not, it's coming to this world, you know, it's,
it's, it's going to be so much more than we are at the moment
envisioning. Okay.
What essential skills or mindsets should students develop
to contribute meaningfully to quantum information
science today.
I think it's very important to engage.
So as the access
to a knowledge, you know, it's there. It's
because of AI, because of
access to information and the
skills that are important is the capability
of engaging with other people and
understanding how do they think. And
that will be very important. And it will not be
only important in business. It
will be important ever more how you teach.
Because it used to be that when you were teaching, right,
let's say you want to be a teacher of quantum.
It used to be that it was all about your knowledge that you know
something and you can deliver that, that it's not anymore.
Every child can just read it on and it will be probably
much nicer written than you could ever say.
So it's not about the
knowledge, but how you can actually engage with that
young person that in the first place. They want to read
it, listen to it or do. How do you. And it will be
the same in marketing, it will be the same, you know, in business
in, in all those aspects. It's going to be ever more important
to really uncover what do the other person
is saying, how do I talk with them, what do they like,
how do I build something or deliver something
that is tangible and that skill is non
technical. It doesn't matter what you will be doing.
The human aspect, like who we are as
humans would be so important in,
in our contribution because we will have so many other tools that
will be taking care of a lot of things. You know, it used to be
important to be a fast typewriter. You know,
it mattered. It was something. It's a course you would take when,
when I was back in school, you know, I remember it
was courses everywhere. You could take that to be very fast in typing
on a keyboard. It doesn't matter anymore that
type of skill, right? It matters that
once you get a text you can reflect on that text and think
how can I make it more appealing to other human person?
What would that be? What would be the little story that I can
make that little change? And this
we have to teach, we have to teach that. And I don't think we are
that good in it, I have to say. Okay,
so now as we kind of come into the final part of the interview, I
want you to know that I've really been enjoying this tremendously.
So I'd like to ask you if I could. As
quantum computing moves closer to real world deployment,
what ethical or societal considerations should
we be thinking about now?
This impact, this impact that
it will not only be on this high level,
on a geopolitical level, on a business level,
but quantum computing will impact
our lives, lifestyles. And
we need to really work hard on
knowing what we want so that we
are not ruled by the tech that becomes so
complex that we hardly
understand it. And it's, we have
AI and we should learn really fast
from AI how we implementing AI,
that it. We are getting it getting out of hand. You know,
we are, it's, you know, it talks to us and
we do what it wants basically. And,
and it makes us sometimes intimidated because it can write better
than we can. And you know, so it has huge impact
on us. And the same is with the quantum computing.
And we have to start thinking about
how to build next generations,
you know, that they can thrive.
Otherwise we're gonna have lost generations. The people that will
not be able because we can't prepare them for what's coming
and they will not be able to adapt fast enough to that.
And, and as a societies we can't afford that. We
need that potential to engage with
the real world. We don't want them to all disappear to the, you
know, the virtual worlds
and be there for the, for the better
of humanity. Whatever people are fascinated
with, we want them to bring it to the real world. And
that is a topic we should really, really think about
how AI, how quantum computing will be
impacting it and how we are not losing young
people because we are losing them at the moment. I see that all
over the place. We losing young people to the digital world
and if they do not see themselves
caring about the real world, it's the
worst that can happen. Because we need their talent, we need their
love. We need that because of the nature. We need that for
interacting with each other. You know, as, as hippie as it
is. We need it for the world, world peace. We need people to care for
one another and they can only do that if they actually are
engaging with the real world. We can't lose them. And I hope that we can
really brainstorm how to
teach them and how they should
interact with technology, that they can keep their integrity.
I'm very curious about it. I'm following the psychology
developments and I'm always curious what people
in those fields will bring, keep bringing in because we need that
knowledge very much urgently I would say.
Okay, so when all the titles fade away,
what do you hope people will remember about
how you showed up in the field and
not just about what you helped build?
I hope that people can feel that I care
and I really love what I do and
if they want to talk to me, they can. I'm always happy
to learn from other people and I hope that somehow I'm
projecting that.
So that would be your legacy that you would hope to probably leave in the
quantum community. That you want people to
know you care and that you, you're excited about the technology.
You're fascinated by teleportation,
which I think is so cool and you know,
you're interested in creating a really kind of welcoming
culture. And this would allow for an
opportunity for many non technicals
to be involved in quantum startups
because. Go ahead. Yeah, I would like
people to feel welcomed. I would like people
that have so many thoughts and they
have their contributions. I would like them to feel not
intimidated. I would like them to be able to come with
their contributions because we need
spaces where people can talk
and not only
the loudest ones, not Only, you know, the
most aggressive ones, but just as many people as
possible can exchange and contribute knowledge. And my hope
would be that my platforms will create that
places where we can, even when we compete in the business
or whatever, that in the end we are humans,
we are building something in this world and we can exchange
knowledge and, and we can, you know, we can grow
as a, as humans together and each
of us will have their own contributions. I truly
believe in that. I truly believe there's so much space for all of
us to thrive if we try. You
know, I'm, I'm a very hippie person apparently. I never thought about it that
way, but deep inside that's all I want. I
want people to learn to, and also to believe
that they it matters. What I find it the most sad
about the humanity is when we give up
about that caring. You know, when we think like, oh, it doesn't matter,
my voice is so little, it's just me, you know, it's
like, no, no, we need to every single
soul. And I hope also for women, you know,
and, and for men that we all will create this more caring
culture. And if, if I can contribute to that,
it would be just perfect. And that is all I want. I want people
to learn and know that they can, they are needed, that we
need them. That's a wonderful message. I'm,
I'm gonna, it's a wonderful message. I, I, I think it's fantastic.
I'm going to include everything that you would like us to include in the
everyone here now where should they find out more about,
about you, about what you're doing about the companies that you run?
I am all on LinkedIn so you can find me. I started
now Instagram, but it's not a big thing. But I'm
exploring that place to spread the world also to people
that are not yet in a maybe professional world, but would like to
also learn about technology. But yes, you can just
type in my long name and then follow. I write
About Tech on LinkedIn. I write about also
being entrepreneur and my journeys. I report from what I
do and share, you know, what I do on my journey also.
And sometimes I also share tough moments.
And then my company, Quantum Security Defense
and Quantum Prime Day both there and we have events every
week that are open. You can come and listen and
learn from the people in my network where they share their knowledge.
And yeah, I hope that
people want to come and be part of it. I'm always
excited about it. Well, I'm going to thank you
so much for Your generosity of your time and to
share your story, which I think is just really super important. It's really
aspirational and that's what we're looking for. And
thank you so very much. Thank you, Candice, for having
me and giving me the, this platform to just talk, you know, about human
stuff. Thank you. So
I'm going to end the podcast here and that was
great. You did a great. You were wonderful. Your story was wonderful.
It was really easy to talk to you. I really appreciated your
message. And then I'm going to go through editing and
then probably aiming to get this out
by mid February. I just want to get a couple more in the kitty
and then once I have a couple more in the kitty, then I want to
start releasing them like every other week. Oh, wow. That's my goal.
Hey, is that the project for this year or. Yeah, that's my new project that
I'm, that I'm doing this year. I just think it's super important. I, you know,
I spent all last year doing Impact Quantum with, with my co
host, which I'm still doing, but I just really felt
that it was essential to have something specific about women.
Women, because the various hats that I see
women wearing, I find it incredibly
inspirational. And I went to Columbia University
Barnard College, which is an all women's college. And I've always,
I've always been fascinated by women in
business, but then I've been in tech for so long and I
see that there's really just a disconnect between women
and tech. And so I want to show women, you know, we can
do all kinds of things. Right? Like, I don't know a lick
about physics, but I, but I went down the rabbit hole
of, you know, of quantum computing over a year ago and I still
haven't, I'm still falling. I love it. Every time I think I've
gotten something, I'm like, no, no, you could know more.
And that's great. That's really exciting. So, yeah.
Oh, you know what? You would love it. You should come to,
to Warsaw in June. There is quantum intact.
I've been there last year 13, 000 women.
I have not experienced something like I had goosebumps.
I would meet women that would be like, oh
my God, you know what I always really wanted to do?
Repair cars.
I loved it. It was, it was just such
a women power and this
talking about like, hey, we have all this curiosity
about those things. And I had women after women saying like, you
know, what I discovered is that I actually really like Math.
And I discovered it first being 30, when they just threw me
on the project. And I had no choice. I had to do it. I
had to do analyzing of data. And you know what? I'm really
good at it. And I dig it so much. You know, they would be.
And they would be surprised how much they loved it.
Right? Because that. It was difficult, but they were like,
oh my God. And you imagine all my life they were telling me that I
am bad in math, that I couldn't do math. And I thought I was bad
in math. And I couldn't say, and here I am, and I love it.
And. And you, you really like it. And it's plenty
of quantum. Like, there is a big quantum stage also, but
you walk around and there is just women, women, women,
women. And they just all like, okay, let's do
more. I loved it. It's one of the biggest women events around
the world. Like, if you have time, you should
totally go. I went last year and I didn't know what to expect because they
were saying they were advertising like more than 10,000 women. I was like,
I think they just say it like that, you know? Right, right. But then you
went. And then I. I went. That's where I got my
award. Okay, Okay. I only went
there because I got a word and I was remembering, like, going there. It's like,
I hope it's good, you know, Like, I don't know what to expect. 13,
000 women. That's fantastic. It's fantastic. And
the lady that is driving it, she is so
much into it. Wow. She is so. And
she's so, so lovely, you know,
and she's making this huge impact and.
And she's. And she's just so driven. She's like.
And she's like, I want to make the biggest. Even I want to educate women
in that. And she's doing it like year after year. It's bigger.
Like in Poland, basically on that two days,
women migrate to Warsaw to be there. Like, I love. Okay,
all right. I like it. I like it. I'm gonna look into that. Absolutely. That
looks fantastic. Fantastic. It is, it is so.
And as you said, like you, when you were in the college, you know, it
just gives that energy and this understanding that
we can do so much more if we just
meet and see. Hey, we are so many. Like, I thought
it was so inspirational. Like, oh, it's just not. Not me.
You know, it's because sometimes it feels so lonely.
Right? But then you realize, no, it's not like,
it's exciting. There are more women. I really. I mean, I can't prove the
numbers yet, but I still feel like there's a lot of women who are hitting
quantum and. And are just excited about it
and. Yeah, I'm like, love it. I'm like, tell
me what you do and how you do it, and let's talk about it. Like,
I think that's fantastic. So I love it. It is. Yeah. Yeah. I love it
too. Thank you for doing it. That's. That's a lot of work.
It's my pleasure. And I'm actually really excited about it. I'm really jazzed by it.
I'm like, woo. And it was great. So I'm all like, ready? Rock and roll
now. So this is great.