Is one of the quantum advantages that quantum networks have. And
security is an interesting point because in the Internet, in the evolution
of that network and the networks of networks,
security wasn't really front of mind and it was kind of tacked on
at the end. And there are plenty of vulnerabilities and security
on the Internet today. And so we do have an opportunity here to really build
these security first principles into
the quantum Internet as it evolves. Welcome to Impact
Quantum.
Hello and welcome back to Impact Quantum, the podcast where we
explore the emerging industry that is quantum computing. We don't
need to be a physicist. You just need to be curious about the technology.
And. And with me is the most quantum curious person I
know, Candice Giuli. How's it going, Candice? It's going great. Thank
you, Frank. It's going great. Today we are going to be speaking
with Michael Kubadoo, who is the co
founder at Alero Quantum Technologies.
How are you, Michael? I'm doing great. Thanks so much for having
me here today. I'm really excited to have this conversation. I'm
a big fan of the podcast and really honored to be here as a guest.
Thank you. Thank you very much. It's always good to
one find out we have fans and then two to meet one.
So Alero, I'm looking at kind of their just basic
talk. This looks really interesting. It's a quantum
networking company. So for those may not be in the know, what
exactly is a quantum networking company? So
quantum networks are new kinds of networks where
traditional networks send zeros and ones around.
And quantum networks, while they can send zeros and ones around, they can
actually send qubits or quantum states over these
channels. And those channels could be fiber, they could be over free space.
So it's really a way to communicate quantum data across
distance. And so to build a company around quantum
networking. There are many pieces of technology
that comprise a quantum network from different kinds of hardware, different
components, but then all of the software stack, the whole networking stack that really
drives what we can do with these kinds of networks. And that's what we focus
on at Alero. Interesting.
So what role? I'm thinking about networks and
so it just makes me think naturally of entanglement.
So what role does entanglement and quantum
repeaters play in making these long
distance quantum networks possible? That's a really
great question. And similar to the
evolution of the Internet, and there were different generations on
the way to the Internet that we, we know and love today.
You know, it really started as, you know, a network
for Science exchange and to share data across
distance between labs. No one really envisioned
the applications that we know and love today. And
we see the same kinds of trends in, in quantum networking.
And the key resource in the Internet is again, these zeros
and ones and how fast you can send them, where
those zeros and ones can. Can reach
over a certain distance. And those are the services that, that really
underpin all the great applications. And the same kind of
analog applies to quantum networking, where, as you said,
entanglement is one such resource, that different applications
can use entanglement in different ways. Now,
there's a lot more complexity with entanglement than zeros and ones. Right.
There are different kinds of entangled states. This notion of
fidelity, or the quality of entanglement, where there really isn't that
quality of a 0 or a 1 in classical networks. So it
is a different paradigm. But some analogies do apply. You can
view entanglement really as a resource that the network is providing, and
then you can build services and applications on top of that entanglement.
But there are different generations of quantum networks, too. Quantum
networks have been demonstrated now for decades. And the
first generations were really about just sending single qubits
or single quantum states and superposition across this network.
And what you mentioned as entanglement is really what we see as the next generation
of quantum networking, the kind of quantum 2.0 of
networks where now we can have not just single photons or single
qubits, but now entangled pairs or larger clusters
of qubits that are entangled with each other and have this special correlation
across distance. And that opens the door for all sorts of applications in
security and computing and sensing in others.
Interesting. So does that mean that
this would be impervious, or I'll
use that term with a little asterisk, because we don't know yet, really, does this
mean that snooping would automatically be detected because you're
sending the superposition so it's inherently secure?
Absolutely. That's really one of the big promises.
One of the quantum advantages that quantum networks have.
And security is an interesting point, because in the Internet,
in the evolution of that network and the networks
of networks, security wasn't really front of mind, and it was kind of tacked on
at the end. And there are plenty of vulnerabilities and security
on the Internet today. And so we do have an opportunity here to really build
these security first principles into
the quantum Internet as it evolves. But that's
absolutely right. These quantum
physics principles, like entanglement, superposition, the no
Cloning theorem, these core principles of quantum
physics really drive those security properties. So as you
said, spoofing or eavesdrop detection, where you can actually
detect when there are some adversaries or some funkiness going on on the network
that will produce patterns and measurement results from these nodes that
can really detect when those things are going on. It's interesting
where as you introduced this podcast focusing on
quantum computing, these sensitivities of
quantum states are actually a bug in quantum computing because they're very
hard to control and you want a computer to be reliable and
robust and isolated from the environment.
This kind of noise is a bug for computing, but it's actually a
feature for networking. You know, this fragility of quantum states, the
sensitivity to its environment is actually what unlocks these security
principles and this new kind of quantum advantage. So eavesdrop detection,
spoof detection, these things are really baked into the physics itself.
So theoretically it's impervious. But who knows what, who knows what
conversation we'll be having in 10 to 15 years about that?
Yeah, yeah, that's a great point. You know, security, they're all,
you know that theoretical security is one piece of the puzzle, right?
And at the end of the day, to build a quantum network, you know, it
sits in a box somewhere, there's some collection of hardware, there's the
software that runs it. So there are many other attack vectors to think about. But
at its core, you know, that's where we really derive a lot of the
security value is from that physics itself and using that
physics for security. Whereas, you know, security today in the
Internet, it's really based on math and assumptions about computational
complexity and all sorts of. Whereas this is really a physics
based approach. So for those listening and for Candace
and for Michael as well, if I sound a little grumpy about that, it's not
the concussion or the funky glasses. It's because I
remember sitting in a training class for Windows
NT, maybe 92, 93,
and the instructor, who might have been a
Microsoft employee, I don't remember, had basically boldly
proclaimed that because it was based on the new NT kernel and various security
features of that, that computer viruses would be impossible
to make in the future. So again,
I didn't really buy it at the time, sound a little far fetched, but
I kind of sort of believed it. I was kind of on the, I was
a bit in a state of superposition about it, but obviously as
time moved on, clearly, you know, the anti kernel and
you know, Windows XP and et cetera, et cetera have not been immune
to malware. So that's why it's
not that I don't trust it or I don't believe in the physics. It's just
like you said, at some point this has to sit in the physical thing and
what sort of software vulnerabilities will be covered. But it does give bad
actors a much
bigger hill to climb in order to mess with your network.
That's right. And I think this is where a healthy dialogue around
the security of these quantum networks. You
know, what applications it's being used for, for what kind of data,
what parts of the network are we talking about, what critical infrastructure
is it, you know, electric grid, is it securing financial
transactions, government communications? There are all sorts of security
requirements and compliance and different regulations around
what security means operationally to these stakeholders. So
that's a really healthy conversation and one that's worth having on the international
stage as we start to think about standards and
how to roll this out in the right way to make sure these networks can
talk to each other securely, even if they're using different approaches
to build quantum networks. So that's a really healthy conversation,
and that's what I think we can expect in the coming years as this technology
really matures. But, you know, we all really agree on this kind of,
you know, the driver, the core principles of using physics
and the laws of physics for security first. And,
you know, it's a lot harder to break the laws of physics than it may
be to find a side channel attack. Right. So, you know, but this
is the discussion we need to be having. It's like, what, what do these
attack vectors look like? You know, what do quantum adversaries look
like? What do we project our adversaries will be using as new tools?
Is it AI? Is it quantum? Is it some mixture of both to try
and attack these networks? Is it to read communications off the
wire, or is it easier to blackmail someone? Right. You know, but
these are. These are practical considerations that we have to think about,
you know, in the coming years as we start to really roll this out in
production. It's really exciting. Everything
that it's touching upon, it's quantum
networking. What advice would you give to
a researcher or an entrepreneur who's
passionate about entering the space?
That's a great question. One thing that's
important to know is that quantum computing
is coming. And even experts within the field
couldn't say that confidently even a few years ago.
It's no longer a matter of if, but a matter of when.
And I think all the great advances in error correction
have really made the case that quantum computing is really on a trajectory
to hit the stage in production sooner
than than we thought, which is great. But you know,
with any sort of emerging technology with this kind of power and potential,
you know, we understand that this, in the wrong hands or in adversarial
hands, can be used to, to attack, you know,
the digital security that we rely on today. So we need
to prepare for that. Now the question becomes how do we
prepare our networks to become quantum safe, to become
quantum resistant, to become quantum secure. And you hear these
words thrown around a lot, but that's extremely important for
governments, for critical infrastructure, our energy grids, our
banks, to really think about migrating to
a quantum safe, a quantum aware posture for their cybersecurity.
The attacks are ever changing and we're seeing this play out on many
different stages in military contexts and political
conflicts, in hacks, right? There are all
sorts of cyber attacks. And now with AI playing a
big role as well. It's not just quantum. Just have
more awareness that technology is moving very rapidly
at an increasing pace. And we need to prepare our networks and our
critical infrastructure, not take it for granted and be proactive about it
and don't be reactive. So that's the advice, I'd say, just
awareness around these attacks, preparing for that,
and doing research into what's out there
to protect these networks. Where does having this physics
layer make sense for your data, for your kind of network?
There are a lot of organizations figuring out right now, how much
of my stuff do I want in the cloud versus on prem, how
much do I trust these big hyperscalers and cloud
vendors? And so as they're going through this migration,
figuring out, okay, how much AI am I going to adopt, how much cloud am
I going to adopt? Where does my network security lie in
that? It's all a related problem. It's very hard to
decouple. So this is not a problem that's
decades out that it's fun to think about and a good
exercise. Now this is something that's very important and a complex
topic to start breaking down. So even just doing the inventory of
what's in place right now, what am I using for security? Who
wrote that code? Was it a decade ago and is
that engineer still on staff? Is it written in an old
programming language that I don't have an engineering team to support?
So those questions, just doing the surveying, the inventory can take a long
time and it's very complex. So getting started on that process
today is really critical. And that's the practical advice I would give.
Then it sounds like you're describing sbom or secure bill of materials
is going to be a part of a. And that makes sense, right? Like it
makes. So for those who don't know, we'll have to explain that because my wife
works in IT security. So I kind of, I kind of know some of the
goings on in terms. But one of the,
I think that, I think you're right. I think we have to have a, as
a society, you know, that is increasingly reliant on this
technology and to have very frank conversations, no
pun intended, about how
we secure infrastructure. Right. I mean, look at the chaos that
having us east one of us going down caused.
All the way from, you know, oh, you know, websites
go down all the way to, you know, some people had IoT devices that were
basically locked including. And I'll pick on them, I'll pick on them for many
years to come. Is the smart
bed. Apparently there was a smart bed that was collecting, you
know, measures how well you sleep and all that. But it would not do anything
unless it could talk to us east one. And you know, we're
recording this a day after a massive Verizon outage. Right.
Right. So it,
you know, we need to understand what our know,
vulnerability of it because, you know, for all we know, these are just
natural happenings. Right. Not a coordinated cyber attack,
for all we know. Right. We'll never, you know, what
will we ever really know the full truth? Maybe. But,
but Candace shaking her head no, like I probably not. But you
know, but I mean, what if this was, you know,
what if this was a coordinated attack?
Like how, you know, how vulnerable are we really?
Yeah. And another, you know, point to that, to that end is around,
you know, attacks that are happening now that, that we don't
even know about, that we can't see directly that aren't,
you know, taking user facing applications down and you know, making
a big fuss in the public eye.
You know, there are adversaries out there that are just harvesting data. They're,
you know, even if they can't crack it yet, they're harvesting it. And
some years down the road when they have access to these, you know, high scale
compute systems and quantum computers, they'll be able to,
you know, look back in time and crack that communication.
So this is especially important for, you know, the kinds of data that you want
to keep secret for a very long time, whether that's, you
know, sensitive financial records, if it's medical records, if it's Government
communications nation secrets. Right. These, there are certain classes of
data that you want to remain secure for
decades. Right. And so, but that's a
threat that's happening now, the harvesting,
you know, it opens you up to this kind of attack at some point in
the future. So a lot of what we do and we engage with these security
stakeholders is to just make them aware that this is happening
and you know, to drive the urgency to be proactive
today and making them understand that, you
know, these kinds of attacks that aren't visible are still
happening. And we do have a lot of dependencies on,
you know, certain cloud infrastructure, data centers, physical
infrastructure and these undersea cables. Right. You know, we
need to think hard and take a close look at what are our
dependencies, how do we mitigate them and what are the attacks that,
that take priority. Right. That's a good way to put it.
And I know Candice is itching to ask you questions and
I don't want to monopolize your time, but after Candace's, I
want to go through your because one, your website's awesome and two, I have some
questions about some of the use cases because those are things I never considered and
those look awesome. Sorry, Candice, go ahead. No, no, it's totally
fine. So let me ask you, so what
role do you see simulation in hybrid classic
classical quantum systems playing in building and testing
quantum networks before large
scale deployment? Yeah, it's a great
question and that's really why we've
spent many years building a very robust simulation
platform and a product,
as you said rightly so. This is a complex technology,
it's one that's evolving. As Frank mentioned, there are other use cases
beyond security that I'd love to get into. But
you know, we have, we have to coexist with what's
here today. Right. We can't lay down a whole new infrastructure
just for quantum. There's fiber in the ground. It's very
expensive to lay new fiber. There's technology we can leverage
today. Let's use it. There are lessons we can take from the Internet.
There's you know, classical security and math based security
that, that we use every day and
every time you see that lock icon and your URL, that's
encryption and we need to coexist with those mechanisms.
It's well baked and very prevalent throughout. That's really the
role simulation can play is to help figure out, okay,
as I start implementing a quantum friendly
or quantum enabled infrastructure, how does it coexist with what
I have today? What fiber am I Using in the ground.
What does it look like to introduce quantum devices onto my network?
How can I combine these new quantum security
applications with my existing security applications?
You mentioned smart beds. Am I going to get qubits to your smart
bed? Probably not. There's no quantum WI
fi. And so what that means is, you know,
when we talk about rolling out quantum networking and quantum
security, quantum encryption, it needs to be
deployed in the right places for the right use cases.
And over time that may grow. But we know
that not everything is going to be quantum. The quantum Internet is not going to
replace the classical Internet by any means. It is going to
augment it. It's going to add new capabilities for certain applications,
certain parts of the network. But classical networks will
absolutely play a role in
our future. And so we need to coexist with what's there.
Simulation is really critical to address those
questions, to figure out how to build these hybrid
networks where parts of your network are just classical, parts of them have
quantum communication on it. How can those nodes talk
to each other end to end in a secure way? So
it's the networking, the protocols, the security, but also the physics. Right.
We need to model how these networks work, what kind of
hardware you, you actually need to build a quantum network
for a certain scale, what kinds of rates and fidelities you need.
There are all sorts of trade offs when designing a quantum network.
And so simulation is really critical not just in planning and
designing a quantum network, but figuring out how to scale it, how to
introduce these new applications, simulating new kinds of protocols
beyond just symmetric keys and encryption keys.
So there's all sorts of use cases for quantum simulation
that is much cheaper than actually acquiring some of this quantum
specialized hardware, which could be quite pricey in some cases.
Okay, interesting. Go ahead, Frank. All right,
I'm chomping at the bit because one, one, your website's really well
designed. And two,
networking quantum computers, solving the scaling
problem. That is the one that blew my mind. If you're watching the video, you
can see when I really click through that, that is a, that is
an amazing concept where, you know, it reads like. And I don't know
how, you know, you know, is this happening
now where I could have, say, if I have a quantum computer, I can
network with that with another one and I can
have basically clusters of quantum computing, which is not something I heard
a lot of people talk about yet, you know, they always show like, here's our
chandelier, right, you know, and all that. But like the whole idea of
having like, basically an entire, you know, cluster of these
chandeliers. How real is that?
Yeah, that's a great question, and I'm glad we have an opportunity
to talk about how quantum networks really
enable quantum computing. So quantum
networks are not just good for security, and they're not good just for
long distance communication. What is a data
center? A data center is a network of clustered compute
resources, even GPU clusters. You know, there's the famous saying, the
network is the computer, right? The same principle applies here for
quantum computing. You know, the conversation, as you pointed out, used to be, my
qubit is better than yours. My, my material, my platform
has better fidelity, or it's faster, or it's this or that, or it
can run longer circuits. There are all sorts of metrics that the quantum
computing community would talk about. Now
we're entering a phase where, you know, we used to have small,
noisy, intermediate scale quantum computers, which could
have maybe a dozen qubits, and they're very unreliable and
noisy. But really, over the past years, since we
started Alero, we've seen the amazing advances
in quantum computing where now we're at the orders of hundreds or
thousands of qubits. We now have error correction, we have, you
know, some level of protecting against noise. And so the
conversation is starting to shift from here's why my qubit is better
than yours to here's why my path to scalability
is better than yours. And I think that's the critical
transition in the dialogue that we're seeing. It's all
about scalability. Now that I've achieved the error correction threshold, I
can build a logical qubit. How do I
scale to millions and millions of qubits? And the same
thing with classical computers and GPUs and CPUs, there's no
monolithic single chip that runs everything,
right? A data center is a network of small computers.
And the same thing applies to quantum computing. So
now that opens all sorts of fun questions around what
does that quantum data center look like? What does the quantum network look like to
actually communicate qubits across different quantum
computers? And that's some of the networking
problems that we solve with rstack as well. How to
manage quantum traffic between computers, how to manage
all the scheduling and the different timescales that these quantum
computers operate at? How to provide this reliable
entanglement as a service, as a resource to these different compute
clusters? There are all sorts of interesting questions from, you
know, not only a physics aspect, but the whole networking stack, the compute
stack, to support it and just to throw another
curveball in there we have GPUs to play with as well.
Nvidia has invested a lot of, you know, money and resources
into playing a big role in really pioneering
how quantum computers will interact with their GPUs.
Right. So you're going to have this hybrid quantum data center. You have
quantum computers, you have GPUs. You might have different kinds of quantum
computers playing a role. You have CPUs, you have networks that are quantum
networks that are classical. They all need to work together, they
all need to be orchestrated and play this
complex dance with each other so we can solve really
large scale and impactful problems.
Wow. I'm sorry, Candice. I'll
say. So from your perspective, what
are the most realistic near term use cases
for quantum networking beyond the
pure research? Yeah, great question.
There are all sorts of applications for a
quantum network. And you know, one
common misconception that we face is when folks hear the
word quantum, they either think about a Marvel
movie or something mythical and very far off into
the future. There's that camp, there's the other camp that's
quantum aware and they hear the word quantum and they think about quantum computing.
And that's really dominated the, the airwaves and, and the
discourse for quantum technology, and rightly so. It has, you know,
many huge potentials in,
in solving problems exponentially faster than, than other kinds of
computers. That's great. But one thing we face is
that to build a useful quantum network, you don't need a quantum
computer. There are other kinds of quantum devices, special quantum
lasers and detectors and other sorts of optics and
photonics that you don't need a full scale quantum computer
to do these security applications. For example, to generate secure
keys between nodes, to have a secure link. You know,
you don't need a quantum computer to do that. So those are the use cases
that are near term those ones where we don't rely
on error correction and fault tolerant quantum
computers. We just have security
and key generation and these
other sorts of applications. In the near term, I think in the medium
term, we'll see other kinds of security applications, not just for keys,
but to actually use the quantum channel to
encode our sensitive data. So using what's called
quantum secure direct communication, there's teleportation,
there's new kinds of authentication methods. So we
can actually use these quantum networks to verify location and
to verify the position of nodes on
a network. This is something you can't do classically.
So this is a way that quantum position verification has this non
spoofing property. To it, which is really nice. So we expect that
in the medium term as well. And then in the long term we can think
about distributed quantum computing where you're connecting
quantum computers over a long distance. There's
great applications not just in computing, but the security of
that computing as well. So who's going to own these quantum
computers? Is it the cloud titans? Right. If
so, how do I actually securely send my, my algorithm,
my computation to the cloud, to the US Quantum east one
and get those results back
securely? And doing so without showing
Amazon or showing the cloud vendor, what is my algorithm, what's my
proprietary data that I'm putting into that quantum computer? So quantum networks can
also help out with the security of those large scale quantum computing
use cases. But that's in the longer term. So to answer
your question, in the tldr, security
is near term and over time there are all these other sorts of
applications in computing and sensing, even some
far fetched ones as well, like quantum money.
There's the potential to have more trustworthy elections and leader
election kinds of applications, secret sharing, there's all
some really cool distributed protocols we can use entanglement
for and we're really excited about those. But you know, as a company
we have to be focused on what's here today, what's commercially viable, what are
folks interested in, what is the market telling us they need
and how can quantum networks serve those needs. So that's front of mind for us,
you know, on the day today. But you know, of course we spend some
time researching these long term applications.
Yeah, it's interesting you mentioned quantum money. Is that some kind of crypto thing?
Because I've never heard that before. Yeah, so it's interesting, quantum
money is actually one of the first
distributed quantum algorithms that was conceived of,
I think it was in the 60s.
I have to double check on that. But the first concepts of quantum money,
yeah, it's decentralized. It's basically using
essentially a quantum signature that can't be forged. So
with today's digital currencies there is, you know, there
are security vulnerabilities and forgery
blockchain is done, you know, designed to be decentralized, of course.
But with quantum money the idea is you can have these
quantum signatures where you can have, you know, let's
say a bank be the only ones to verify whether this piece of
currency is real. So they're fun exercises in
thinking about how these quantum
physics principles can be used for, for money and
to stop forgery. That actually inspired
some of the, the work for quantum key
distribution, which came later. So it's kind of an interesting evolution.
And I've heard Peter Shore talk about this where there's
quantum money that inspired quantum key distribution.
And the folks who invented quantum key distribution asked Peter
Shor to work on a security proof for it. That security proof led
Peter Shor to ultimately discover Shor's algorithm, which
really inspired all the quantum computing progress. So it's, it's kind of
a fun history lesson. But you know, quantum money, while it's very
far looking and very long term application, was one of the first
ideas of quantum networking that came out
in the middle of last century. Interesting, interesting.
So a lot of unpack, a lot to unpack.
But the short thing is, you know, when it comes
to conventional networking, we all understand what a
gigabit is. We all understand what, you know, megabit is like. Are there
similar, like what are the speeds that we're talking about with
quantum networking? Yeah, great question.
There are many factors that go into determining what is
the speed of a quantum network. And the biggest factor
being the distance of your channel. So
if we're doing this in fiber, fiber is quite
lossy and we lose a lot of our flying qubits.
So that really determines what is the maximum rate that
we can transmit quantum data. There's all other
sorts of factors, like how fast are your lasers and your entanglement
sources, how good are your detectors, you know, the quality of your
hardware will determine that, that rate. But
there are analogs, right? We and I touched on this in a recent
research paper I did with, with NIST on quantum
routing, entanglement routing. And in there we start to make some
analogs between, you know, metrics. What,
what are the metrics we know and love from the classical Internet. So things like
throughput bandwidth, you know, your typical
performance metrics. Do those apply to quantum networks? In some cases,
yes, it's a direct analog. In some cases, no, it's a
very different paradigm. In some cases, yes, but it's a
very different kind of unit. So you mentioned throughput
as an example. What are the rates in a quantum network that
could be, you know, qubits per second, it could be entangled pairs per
second. But again, with quantum networks you have this notion
of quality fidelity that you don't have in zeros and ones.
So which brings an interesting question about the
quality of service of these quantum networks. So some applications,
they really need a very high rate of entanglement. They really
need qubits as fast as possible, but they don't care that they need. You
know, if they're 99% fidelity. Other applications,
they don't care if it's, if it's that fast. They just need really
good quality of entanglement. So building a network stack, building
a network that can service these different kinds of applications.
And so you can have these, these knobs that you can tune,
whether that's rate, whether that's fidelity, whether it's the network
complexity and the switching capabilities. There are all sorts
of metrics to think about. But we started to address those questions a
little bit. And I know there are plenty of groups out there thinking about quantum
networking metrics and I think that's something we can work on as a, as a
community to have a common language. What metrics are important, what's going to drive
economic value? How do we start to understand
what these metrics actually mean for commercial use?
Right. I can imagine like at some point in the future you'll be like, in
the distant future, everyone, distant future, I'll be in the
store of a Best Buy or like Micro center and like, hey, this is the
10 gigabit, you know, and this is the
20 gigabit, you know, quantum router or something like that. Like, I mean,
you're right. Like, and does it even make sense? You're right. Like we need to
figure out like, you know, what numbers make sense. Right,
right, right. And is it, you know, you can buy
a box or a laser at a certain rate and you know, there are
those kinds of components available commercial off the shelf today. You can, you
know, buy a photon source that generates, you know, this many
pairs per second at say a gigahertz rate or a kilohertz rate.
It's tuned to this wavelength or that wavelength. Does that make sense for your
application? What kinds of distances could that actually cover point
to point? So there's, there's all other sorts of questions around it. But yeah,
I think, you know, we're starting to see that emerge
and especially over the, the past seven years or so that, that
we've been working at Olero, we've really seen that trend pick up and so
many amazing quantum hardware startups
focused on networking that are building these entanglement sources, these
photon sources, these photon detectors, the quantum switches, all the
components we need quantum memories as well, quantum repeaters that
are, that are being worked on. And we're seeing so much activity
in that space. And as Oliro, we're really focused on
kind of the networking stack and the software part of it.
And we partner with as Many of these companies as we can, in these groups
that have these components that we need to, to build a network and to
actually operate it. So that's been really encouraging to see and I'm
excited to continue that, that to watch that
space and to foster those relationships with, with those companies,
because it does take a village. No one company has all the right pieces, just
like the Internet. There's no, you know, single service provider.
There's no one company that can do it. All right? It takes components from all
sorts of vendors, takes contributions from standards
organizations, from software companies, from hardware companies to build a network
that we can actually use. You've
mentioned several different metrics. Is
there a single metric you trust most when
evaluating the maturity of a quantum system, or
does it always depend on the context?
It's a really great question and a timely one that,
you know, we're working on in some industry consortium, and I was
just at a conference last month talking about this exact thing. Like what,
what are the important metrics? What is the common language and the definition
of these metrics? I think it will be
some combination of these performance
metrics like rate, like fidelity, and like distance,
because those are the. Broadly the things we care about. Right. How,
how broad is this network? You know, what geographies does it cover
that tells us what kinds of applications we can think about.
The rates and the fidelities tell us what kind of, you know, service quality
can this quantum network provide? If it's too slow or if
it's not good enough, then, you know, we can't rely on the security of these
things. Or we. That that's not fast enough to connect quantum
computers over this distance. Right. So knowing that is really
critical, but I think it will be some combination of
speed, of quality, and of distance.
Interesting. Wow. I mean, there's a lot to consider here. Right. Like it's not just
about. And one of the other use cases.
I know we're running low on time, so I have to probably have you come
back. Quantum sensor networks, which, if I, if I were
to posit what quantum networking is for, is you want
to be able to sense the state of the particles and the entanglement
and then be able to send that state over a. What, over a wire?
Bear with me over something. Right.
And then it be preserved on the other side where it could be
read or whatever, done whatever with. Is that. Is that correct?
Yeah, there's. So quantum
sensors are arguably the most mature
subfield of quantum technologies. And quantum sensors have
been around and, you know, we're Talking about clocks, we're talking about
magnetic sensors, sensors for electric fields,
RF sensors, all sorts of sensors that have been worked on for decades and
deployed and used today in systems that we, we use every
day. You know, gps, Right. So quantum
sensors are very mature. But when you bring up
networking quantum sensors, that's, that's really an interesting intersection
point of these two fields where quantum sensors
are great at measuring, you know, something very locally
with great degrees of precision. But when we think
about networking these together and maybe entangling an
array of sensors over a network, that opens the door for some really
interesting applications, both for
geodesy, for mapping, for not relying on gps,
for sensing fluctuations in the magnetic field and the electric field.
Doing better astronomy, how we
collect light from stars and using entanglement to process that light in
better ways so we can have higher resolution for, say, black hole
imaging. There are all sorts of deep science questions
that can be answered with, with quantum sensors in a distributed setting, which
is a really, really exciting frontier that the community is thinking
about deeply. Oh, because the earth rotates, so you could have
a couple of these sensors. So that way you're always pointed at the same
thing in space. Right. And one, yeah,
one first example of this is ligo. So,
you know, basically we have these telescopes
collecting light from stars. And the way things are done today is that,
you know, this light is collected, that data is processed using
classical computers. And all those telescopes around
the world will share their data, they'll bring it together, they'll aggregate it and
they'll process it and try and generate an image or some kind
of data, you know, end result for science.
Now, how quantum changes the game there is, you
know, if these telescopes are actually entangled with each other,
you can process that light in a very different way. Instead of just post processing
it on a classical computer, you can use these, these
global entangled states to sense that light in a very different
way, to process it in a very different way. Ultimately, with the quantum computer,
they're all, you know, sorts of new features. You can think about sensing
and imaging for astronomy in that, in that application.
So yeah, it's a really, really interesting space.
Wow, that's
funny. Sorry, Candice, I'm just going to say. No,
I'm taking it all in. I'm taking it all in.
So what kinds of measurements become possible with quantum
sensor networks that simply can't be done with classical
sensing systems? Yeah,
it's a great question and I think the field is
thinking deeply about this question, you know, where,
so there's Kinds of evolutions of this whereby, you know, we
can have one sensor that's great for many applications. Say it's an
inertial sensor that's awesome for, you know, aircraft
and it has applications
on its own. Then the next generation is, okay, what if we have a
network of sensors but there's no quantum connections between them? They're just,
they're individual quantum sensors that are, that can exchange data with each other
classically. So that has, you know, some
advantages there just as, as an array.
And then the next generation is, oh, what if they are also
entangled with each other? And then you can get more advantage.
So the advantages come in precision and in accuracy.
And as you have these sensors working together, you
can actually enhance the precision that way. So
there's something called the standard quantum limit where there's a
square root performance benefit with the number of sensors you have.
So if you have K sensors working together, you can get that square
root K advantage in your precision and accuracy. So
there are, you know, there's a lot of great theory kind of backing this up.
I think the field writ large is thinking about, you know, what are those
killer applications, you know, in the near term, in the medium term,
you know, we have quantum networking on its own as a field, we have quantum
sensing on its own as a field. So how do we intersect these, these two
timelines and roadmaps and technology to actually work together
to solve certain problems in science and position, navigation,
timing and astronomy, all sorts of application areas.
Wow, that's cool. I mean, I just, it's just
mind blowing. Like what? Because you know, you hear about the hype
about quantum computers, you don't think about the networking. Right. Networking doesn't
always come up in the hype cycle. Right. However,
very clearly, like you said, like, you know, you don't need to have a quantum
computer to do quantum networking. Right. I would imagine that these
photon generators and things like that, they probably don't need to be super cooled.
Guessing. So you could have this
today with relatively modest
comparatively investment. Oh yeah, that's definitely right.
Yeah. Quantum computers probably cost on the order of tens of millions of
dollars and quantum networks orders of magnitude less than
that. And there are off the shelf components you can buy and start to piece
together these networks. There are all
sorts of quantum photon sources and entanglement
generators and photon detectors, all with different trade offs. Right.
Some are tuned to certain wavelengths.
Right. They want to operate in the telecom regime. Others are great for
visible light and free space. And that may lend itself better to say
A satellite link or an inter satellite link. Some
lasers might be better for fiber networks. Some lasers are
faster than others, but generate a different kind of entanglement.
So a lot of what we think about is like, okay, you have this landscape
out there of all sorts of components and different approaches to
generating quantum light. How do we stitch them together? How do
these components actually interoperate with each other, not just at the
physical level, but over a network? How can they communicate
with each other? What is a quantum network node? It's a collection of
dozens of these things, right? You're going to have switches and photon sources
and detectors. But it needs to be useful. There needs to be some
logic, some control, some timing and synchronization
infrastructure that actually supports all of these great
applications. So that's what we spend most of our time thinking about,
is building out these abstraction layers in the network stack to actually get these
components to talk to each other in a useful way.
Wow. So this seems to me like this could be a burgeoning career field. Really,
like a quantum network engineer? Absolutely,
yeah. And I think that's testament to how we've built our team
and grown the team over time. It takes a village.
And I think within all the subdomains of
quantum. I would say quantum networking is the most interdisciplinary.
We have folks on staff that are the PhD quantum physicists, but
we have folks that worked in classical networking and built
the products that power the Internet. They know what it takes to build a network
stack. They know what it takes to deploy a system in a data center
or for a telecommunications company. What does it take to have
five nines of service reliability? That's something in the classical
networking space is a must have. So taking those lessons learned
from the classical networking world, combining that with the quantum
expertise, and of course all of the amazing backgrounds
we need to actually build products and reliable
software products. So we have traditional software engineers, but out in the field,
we're going to need traditional fiber engineers as well.
So that's something that I'm excited to see over the coming years,
is a workforce development for quantum networking and having
upskilling programs to make this
less daunting, to lower the barrier to entry. There are
so many great engineers out there, and
they don't need a PhD level quantum education to be
to have a career in quantum networking. There are trade schools that
train fiber engineers today, and those folks can be
absolutely useful with minimal training, you know, to set
up this infrastructure, to monitor it, to, you know, go out and learn how
to, you know, fix some issues. That we might see in the network to do
updates, to do, you know, ads and changes, and to
scale the network. There are all sorts of field engineering that we're
going to need to really make this a reality. You know, we talk about the
quantum Internet. We're well, well away from that. But,
you know, right now we're, we're at the point where you do see these
metropolitan regions, these local area networks. There's dozens and
dozens of them around the world. What's the natural next step is to start
connecting them over longer distances. And you know, that
that's how we're going to get there. But it, it doesn't take only quantum
PhDs to do that. You know, we need practical engineering expertise, we
need classical engineering expertise to really make this a reality.
It's a good way to put it. As I like to say, someone has to
rack them and stack them. That's right, yeah.
So we always ask this of everybody. So what is the biggest
misconception that you hear out there about
quantum computing that you would like to reframe or just let them
know this is, this is wrong? What's one of the
biggest misconceptions out there?
You know, I think for many years
that I've been in this space, the misconception was that
there is going to be one single
winner of quantum computing. There's going to be a winning platform
and that's going to look like a huge chandelier
that has millions and millions of qubits on it.
That's not the case. The future of quantum computing is going to be
heterogeneous. I think different kinds of qubits will play different
roles. I think,
apart from, you know,
maybe certain modalities. I think broadly, most
of the quantum computing approaches will need to be networked. That's the only way
they're going to reach scale. The difference is how many
qubits can I get before I have to think about networking?
Some might be on the order of a couple thousand. Others think
they can scale on a single chip or a single atomic
system to say 50 or 100,000 qubits,
and then they need to network. So there's some difference there. But regardless,
to get to the utility scale of quantum computing, you're going to need to network
them. And that's something I'd like to shed some more light on. And I'm glad
the community has kind of woken up and
seen the need for networking these computers together
recently. And that wasn't always the case. So I still think
it's somewhat of a misconception. But for quantum computing
to realize that they need to network, I mean IBM just announced their
plans to network their computers just to few months ago.
Right. So you know, we're starting to see that shift. But
yeah, shining more light on that is really important. Interesting.
You had mentioned a couple times something called free space.
I think I know what that means, but I don't think I do like
totally. Is this kind of like white space spectrum
that's available or something else? Yeah, so free
space we use as a term to describe a
quantum channel that's not over fiber. So okay,
it's wireless now. There is a caveat there. So
you know the WI fi router I'm using now can those signals can
permeate through walls and things.
The quantum signals, at least for quite some time,
will need to be line of sight when you're talking about point
to point free space. But
there have been satellite deployments, we're working on some, some satellite deployments
as well for quantum networks with our partners in
the aerospace sector, which is really, really exciting. That's
a critical part of the quantum Internet. It's not just going to be fiber.
If you really want to generate entanglement cross continents,
cross oceans, we're going to need a satellite infrastructure to do that.
But you do need this line of sight. And so that's
what free space means for quantum networking. We
won't be able to have a quantity quantum WI fi unless there's some, you know,
huge advancements and physics breakthroughs in terms of like
microwave photons, but we can't depend on that. I
think it's safe to say that, you know, the quantum communication will be
line of sight. So you need to be able to see your end node.
Yeah. We had a previous guest, Dr. Catania
Kuntz, had mentioned that they basically has. It's
whatever she uses in her research is probably not limited to some flavor of
infrared light and things like that, but
okay, free space. I thought when you said free space I thought you meant like
spectrum that's available or whatever. The TV white
space is what people used to call it, but that means something completely different.
That's really cool and thank you for
explaining that. Any parting thoughts? Where can
folks find out more about you, more about what LERO is doing?
Yeah, sure. You know, I'm really, really
excited to get the chance to talk about quantum networking and its
importance not just in security and for,
you know, governments and companies today, but
also all the cool applications that that can be
derived from quantum networking. I think Security is
one that draws a lot of the attention. But you
know, we do play some of that fear motivation. Right. We need to prepare
our infrastructure for the quantum attacks. Absolutely. Like we need to drive
that urgency. But at the same time, this is an infrastructure play.
Right. This is, this quantum Internet that we talk about
has all sorts of amazing applications and I'm sure a lot that we
haven't even dreamt of. Just like the Internet, right as it was getting started, we
did not think about a Facebook or, you know, this,
all the Internet services that we TikTok, brain rot, all that stuff.
Yeah, probably not thought about. Yeah.
You know, there's a lot of room for innovation and it's a really, really exciting
field to be in. And so I really appreciate the
opportunity to talk about it today. Feel free to reach out.
We do also run a webinar series as well if you want to
learn more about what a quantum network is. How does it work,
what are the, you know, the trade offs, you know, everything from a
101 to what does it look like to deploy a quantum satellite?
We try and address all those topics in an educational way. So feel free
to check out our website, check out that webinar series if you want to learn
more about quantum networking. And as always, feel free to reach out to me as
well. Very cool. Any parting thoughts, Candice?
No. Thank you so much for this conversation. I think the
quantum networking is absolutely fascinating and we're
hearing more about it from the different perspectives. So I'm just really happy that we,
we got to hear about it from yours. So thank you again for your time.
Of course. It's an honor being here. Thanks so much. Thank you for coming. And
I really, I really learned quite a bit today.
I hope our listeners did too. And with that, we'll play the outro music.
And it's gold.
The multiverse is skanking Skanking in time Black holes
are wailing in a horn line so fine From Planck scales to planets they're
connecting the dots Candace and Frank they're the cosmic
Han shots.
Quantum podcast turn it up fast Candace and Frank
blowing my mind at last Quantum podcast They're breaking
the mold Science has got beats it's bold
and it's gold.