The other one that drives me crazy is people think that you need to have
a PhD in physics in order to do anything in the industry. I have a
business degree and I've done pretty well, and I'm sure there are lots of other
people who have— who don't have
PhDs in physics and, you know, they work in quantum.
Welcome to Women in Quantum.
Welcome back to Women in Quantum, the podcast where
curiosity meets the quantum frontier. I'm Candace
Gilhooley, and in each episode, we spotlight the
brilliant women shaping the future of quantum computing,
quantum sensing, quantum communications, and beyond.
From researchers and founders to ecosystem
builders and bold career switchers,
these are the voices expanding what is possible
in one of the world's most transformative technologies.
If you've ever wondered whether there's a place for you in quantum,
you are exactly in the right place. Let's
step into the quantum realm together.
Today we have the pleasure of speaking with Petra
Soderling. She is CEO,
advisor, EU and USA,
quantum, dual use, government.
Petra, tell us all, what is it that you do? You do so much.
Thanks so much. It's great to be here. When you were saying like this is
for quantum computing and sensing and communications and beyond, I felt like,
yeah, beyond. That's me. I'm beyond. What is
it that I do? That's a good question. So what I do
currently is I am the CEO of my consulting
company or advisory services. I haven't— I've been doing this for 4 years.
I still don't know what to call it. I help people to achieve
things. I do that with quantum. Mainly,
and with governments mainly. I do work with some companies, so
I help some U.S. companies to set up in Europe. I help
some European companies to set up in the U.S., but mainly I work with,
with governments and NGOs and large institutions,
banks and such. So take us back to the
beginning, okay? You're, you're a young girl, you're in grammar
school. What was the— what were the subjects that you had a proclivity for?
Arts, um, philosophy,
maybe public policy later, but first it was just arts
and humanities. I, I was not interested in science at all.
And where is it that you grew up? I grew up in Finland,
Helsinki. Okay. And that's where I went to school,
and that's where I started my very, very long and very windy
path towards where I am today in quantum and
governments. Well, tell us about your journey. Okay, so you
have time? This is a long story.
So I graduated in Finland in the middle of the
worst recession ever. There were no jobs at all. So I had to
find a job. I found a job selling forklift trucks.
As I was selling forklift trucks, I advanced in
the company and was also able to market them. So I became the
marketing manager of this forklift truck company. And the
company also sold Suzuki motorbikes and outboard engines.
And I was the person responsible for doing
the events, so the showcasing the Suzuki
motorcycle. So I did the motorcycle events and the
boat boating events. And then year
2000, Nokia was a big thing in Finland and they were
looking for an events manager and I got the job. Doing
events for products I had never heard of,
text messaging service centers and multimedia
messaging service centers in the telecommunications
infrastructure realm. And I'm like a forklift truck
person, I have no idea what's going on here. But as I was doing those
events, I also had to be responsible for the,
you know, the printed materials. And we were selling
these service centers to mobile operators, carriers,
and all of this material was written by the engineers, but the buyers were not
engineers, they were business people. So I realized I have to help the engineers
write their pitch, their, you know, their decks so that the buyers would understand
how to do this. And as I did
this, I got really interested in the technology. I really wanted to understand
how these products work and what they do. So I went into writing
white papers. So I left the events stage behind and I
started to write white papers for these products for
Nokia Networks. And then With that job,
these white papers were used in standardization. So I went into
standardization, helping Nokia standardize these new products,
which was the telecommunications infrastructure. But then later
also, I went to work for the device unit, which
was the mobile phones and the smartphones. So then I was in standardization,
standardizing user interfaces and
different layers in the stack for, for Nokia. Then I
jumped into research center and blah blah. I was at Nokia for 12
years in different roles. Um, then, um, at one
point, um, a new product came into the market, was called the iPhone, and
just killed all the phone business for everyone else. And
so I left the company and I left Finland. I started my own
startup company. I moved to New York City. Um, I spent,
um, how many years, maybe 10 years in the U.S. running two different
startup companies. I lived in New York, New Orleans, Colorado. And
then at some point, I think it was 2018, I was called to
represent Finland. So I lived in the U.S. and the Finnish government asked
me to do foreign direct investment for Finland, meaning find
American companies, science or technology companies,
who might be interested in setting up, you know, their operations in Finland.
And I'm taking this role very seriously, of course, so I kind of
start to think to myself How do I find something in
Finland that's so interesting that American companies would listen to
me? Like, why would they want to go to Finland to do something? And that's
how I discovered quantum, because in 2020, the
Finnish government was buying a quantum computer and it was an open call.
So I thought, hey, this is a good opportunity for me to go talk to
the American quantum companies and say, you should submit a
bid to this call. And, and that was 6 years ago.
And I just fell in love with quantum, and I've been all in, in
quantum ever since. And that's the story.
That's fantastic. That's honestly, that's a fantastic story.
I like, it's so incredibly singular. I
haven't heard anything else like that. That was great.
Did you have any early mentors or influencers that helped shape,
you know, your entrepreneurial direction, your desire for
startups, your inquisitive nature? Did you
have any mentors that helped you with that? I wish I had. I
wish I had. There was one role model early on.
She was the CEO of Nokia Networks business. Her name is Sari
Baldorf. And she is an
iconic woman because in the early days, so
those listeners who remember the times before the iPhone,
you had Motorola was number one in mobile phones back in
the 1990s and early 2000s. And then Nokia came, it was number 2.
And Sari, my role model, she was responsible for setting up the
telecommunications, the networks business, while all the men went to work with the
mobile phones, the sexier parts. So she was doing the boring part and the
guys were doing the sexy part. And lo and behold, the boring
part, the telecommunications run by her, ended up being
more successful and is still alive today. And it is what Nokia is today.
And all the sexy stuff that all the guys did is long gone. It's
gone. So she's still my, my icon and my role model.
She's no longer there, right? So when you look back, what
part of your path feels the most non-linear or
unexpected? All of it. All of it. I never had any plans.
I like— I just go where the wind blows. Not, not really where the wind
blows, but if there's a really interesting opportunity, I
just go there. I, I don't,
I don't have big plans ever. I do, um, sometimes my husband
and I, we make, um, these treasure maps for
like a year or two years, and then we're really excited about our
treasure maps and we kind of forget about it, but then it
stays in the back of our minds. And then a couple of years later, we
go back and look at the treasure map, if, uh, you know, if we follow
it. And usually pretty much, but not exactly So there is some
kind of planning and thinking, but not, not like
exactly. So for our listeners who
are new to your work, how would you describe your current focus in the
quantum space?
Well, I guess,
yeah, that's a really good question. I would say
what I would like to be is an expert on how
governments invest in deep tech, including quantum,
for economic growth. That was the subject of my book
that I wrote, actually. So when I went to work for the Finnish
government, I also realized that I have experience from working
in a big corporate environment, working as a startup
entrepreneur, and working for the government. And then during
COVID I was thinking like, this is a pretty unique point of view that I've
been working in all of these three different domains. So I wrote a
book about how how governments should look at
deep tech and innovation in general and how
to use that, how to grow that, how to create new industries like
quantum for long-term economic growth.
So my, my role broadly currently is to help
regions, governments with,
with their strategy. So I've been writing quite a few quantum
strategies for countries and regions.
So what problem in quantum are you personally most
excited to help solve right now? It's, it's
create, turning it into an industry, which we're kind of there already,
but we're still like,
we have it. We're very still very foundational, I think. Yes,
exactly. And if you benchmark the
learnings from other deep tech industries, it's always been
very government-driven. So you cannot create these new
industries without government. You think about nuclear energy,
for a long time it was publicly funded, and now
there's a private industry. Space, space was completely
publicly funded for a long time. Only recently, after decades,
has there been a private space industry.
So I want to help governments
realize their potential, invest in quantum, and
ensure that it's going to be turned into a private
industry that will then in turn help the governments by
offering jobs, paying taxes, creating infrastructure,
help with the national security concerns and, and so forth.
So you might have just answered this, but where do you see the biggest
technical bottleneck in your domain today?
To be honest, I'm not following the quantum technology that
closely because I feel that my role is
to take a step back and look at things more holistically.
If so, for example, every morning I open my LinkedIn and
there's a new quantum breakthrough. There's always a company saying,
oh, we've just, you know, completed this major milestone. This is
the big thing. Now this is going to solve everything. And then wait a week
or a couple of days, there's a new company or new technology, a new breakthrough.
So I see my role as being like the more long-term
projectory type of person that looks at things with
perspective of the history and, and a longer-term view,
and then looking at it from the whole society's point of
view, not just a company or a country even, but
globally, because this is a global international industry.
But what is one misconception people still have
about quantum that drives you a little crazy?
There's so many, Candace. Oh my gosh.
Well, I mean, one of the things that people ask is, when am I going
to have a quantum computer on my desk? So that's like, that's one. Like,
never. Well, maybe never. Okay, I don't want to be the IBM guy, but You
know, probably not ever. The other one that drives me
crazy is people think that you need to have a PhD in physics in order
to do anything in the industry. I have a business degree and I've done pretty
well, and I'm sure there are lots of other people who have,
who don't have PhDs in physics and, you know, they work in quantum.
And then there's this binary belief that quantum
will solve everything or quantum will solve nothing.
On, like, it drove me crazy when the CEO of NVIDIA said,
like, quantum is so far away, like, it's not going to solve anything.
And all the stock prices of the quantum companies crashed
overnight because of what he said. And then a week later, he's like,
no, actually, I think it does have potential. And then the stock prices come up
and it's not a binary thing. It's not something that
will be there one day or will not be there one day. It's, Like, people
don't realize the gradual adoption and
the hybrid architectures and so forth. And
one important thing, I've just spoke to some African
governments, is that people think that it's way too expensive.
So there is a possibility for even for developing
countries to get into the game without having
huge budgets. You have online access,
you have physics departments in universities. So you
already have all this stuff. Just get in the game and don't think about the
budget. So what skills
do you think are underrated but critical for success
in quantum today? People skills,
communication skills, human skills. It's
so many times people talk about the technology,
But they don't think that it's people doing all these
things. It's people in labs creating the science.
It's people in the business development talking to other people in other
business development departments. It's people in the government talking
to, you know, the government
relationships people in the quantum companies.
That's one. And then, oh
my gosh, I lost my train of thought. It'll
come back to me.
Should I go on with another? Yeah. What was the question? So it was
the, the skill, the skills, the skills that people need
today. And we talked about communication, people skills.
Those are more soft skills, interdisciplinary
skills. I think are incredibly vital
to this field. That's what we were talking about.
Okay, let's leave it at that. Okay. So you said that you take a
step back and you're kind of looking at the whole thing
holistically. So which regions or
ecosystems are you watching the most closely right
now? So
I'm Finnish American, so I have two passports. I
have one leg in the, in North America, in the United States. One leg in
Europe. So those are my two regions. I, I look at public policy,
technology policy from both perspectives, the US and
EU, what they're doing separately and what they're doing together, and hopefully more
rather than less. That's one thing. And then
the other thing is what governments can do. So there's a lot
that governments can do. There's the education, there's tariffs, there's
regulation, export controls.
Movement of talent. There is public funding, there's
public-private financing, there's a whole,
you know, there's a rich plethora of things that governments can do.
It's a long list, but my goal is to bring it all together
and kind of showcase to governments, you need to think of all of these different
things when you're advancing or kicking off
your quantum industry.
So what signals should investors,
policymakers, or industry leaders
be paying closer attention to?
Well, technology breakthroughs, obviously. So I'm not saying that it's not
important. It is important. But more
important is— I mean, I'm biased, of course,
but I would look at the government strategies. I think because these are so much
government-funded technologies, You should take a
look at what the government strategies say, which, which
countries or which regions are focused
more on the national security aspect of it, which
regions are more focused on enabling their, their
companies to grow, which, which sectors
are maybe focusing only on one modality rather than
all of the modalities and so forth.
It's a long-term investment. It's a risky investment. So
obviously, you know, investors are going to be looking at all of these
things. But I like, you know, my
spiel is the government angle. So I hope they're also looking at the
government strategies. Well, as you
said, you have one foot in the States, you've got one foot in Finland.
What has your experience been as a woman? Building a
career in quantum?
Yeah, that's, you know, when I knew that I would be
coming to this podcast and I knew you would be asking me that question,
I thought like, I don't really have a good answer for that. And
that really bothered me. I, you know, I have— I consider myself
a feminist. I've always worked to make sure that we lift all the
women. I'm lifting the women around me. Um,
but lately I've been thinking that it's not enough for me to just
lift the women close to me and around me. I need to
broaden the horizon and lift all of the women, even the ones that
I don't know and the ones that work with me. So actually,
last week, because I knew I would be coming here, I wrote my weekly
newsletter on women and technology for this very reason,
and This is not my personal experience, but just
I wanted to look at the generic role of women in
technology, and there are surprising things. OK, now I want to
pull up this chart. So there are a few things
that we don't really talk about
that much. So one of them is
the
role of
women in the early 1800s and 1900s. There is
a number of women who have invented amazing things.
Like, there's, uh, Ada Lovelace, said to be the inventor of
software. Hedy Lamarr invented the frequency-hopping radio.
Grace Hopper invented the COBOL programming language that we still
use in the government infrastructure today. There's
Marie Curie in radiation and so forth. So these women who
lived in an era when they were not able to own a bank account or
own any property, they weren't able to work, they weren't able
to go to a bar, these women managed to invent these
incredible groundbreaking technologies. So that's
like one aspect of it. But the other one
I want to show your viewers—
oh, by the way, is this going on an audio-only? No,
no, it's audio and video. Okay, so
what I'm sharing now on screen, can you see it? Yes. This is a
chart. This is the percentage of bachelor's degrees
conferred to women in the USA starting from 1970,
ending in 2010. So 1970,
excuse me, you can see that women entered
in all these fields. So you've got agriculture, social sciences,
business, math, architecture, physical sciences,
including computer science. So computer science is very
thin gray line, if you— that. So women
jumped into computer science just like they jumped into these
other fields. But something happened here in 1984,
and what happened was the launch of the personal computer. So
1984, those of us who were alive might remember,
um, uh, the Christmas present for
girls was the Cabbage Patch doll.
Christmas present for boys was a personal computer for
gaming, and that was groundbreaking
for this gray line. So women
felt that because the personal computer was
mainly marketed to boys and it was mainly
marketed to play games, you know, it created
this kind of bubble where games and
PCs and computers and computer science was seen as something for boys
only. And that really had a huge effect, and computer science
never, never recovered from that. So even
today we have, we have slightly more
people in computer science in than in 1970. Isn't that amazing?
That's, that's shocking, but completely like
remembering that's exactly what was going on. I mean,
exactly, exactly what's going on. Only field. That never
recovered. All these other fields, women are more than
half of biology, communications,
math is up there. So people, the women are almost 50%
of bachelors in math and statistics,
but not in computer science and engineering. So that's
kind of crazy. So those are kind of like the talking points or the
messages that I want to put out there when we talk about women
in technology. And of course there are all these other
things like you want diversity in your team, your product
development team or your management team. You
need diversity, diverse voices so you can create products for
diverse groups of people. And you want a
diverse management team so that you make decisions
that are looked at from different angles, from different
points of view. So women tend to have a lower
risk tolerance threshold than men. Sometimes it's good,
sometimes it's bad, but it's really good to look at things from,
from both perspectives. Right now, that was fascinating. That
was, that was really fascinating, that chart. So
have there been moments where you had to push past
doubt, either internally or externally,
and how did you manage that? As a woman?
Yes. Oh yeah, as a professional, as a woman.
Yeah, I have— oh my gosh, I have so many examples.
Um, I think I'm the type of person, even in my
private life, that I always want— I always want to
make things better. I always want to push for a better outcome,
and I've been that person in all of the
boardrooms or conference rooms or meeting rooms wherever I've
been. And I, I remember so many examples examples.
One of them was in a product development
meeting with Nokia. It was like 40 people in the room.
We were looking at the roadmaps and everyone in the room, there's
like 3 women and 40 guys. Everyone is like, yeah,
yeah, whoever is presenting, yeah, this looks good. And I'm the only person
who stands up and like, this is like, guys, this is not good
enough. You have to raise the bar. At least 20-30%.
This is not good enough. And everyone's just looking at me like,
shut up, Petra, sit down. They're like, we want to
go home and we want to go play tennis and do our things. Like, we
don't want to stay here over time because, you know, you
think that, you know, we should do better. Um,
there was, um, oh, I should tell this story. There
was, um, I was at the Nokia Research Center. I wasn't in
the management team. I was the head of marketing, but I wasn't in the management
team because marketing is not important enough. But I was very close to the management
team and they wanted to launch a fellowship program. And
all the people in the management team suggested their
people for the long list of fellows, like
the long list of people who, where they would pick the fellow from.
And I looked at the list, it was about 100 names, and
maybe 5% were women or something, 5-15, I can't remember exactly, it was
such a long time ago. And I went to the team like, what is this?
Like, guys, what's going on here? And
they're like, well, you know, we just named the best. Then I
was really pushing back. I said, no, you like, really, you named the
best? I'm gonna, I'm gonna give you a list of 100 women's
names. And I worked with HR and I did my own list, which was 100%
women. And, you know, I've
done things like this. I was a year ago in
a quantum conference in Europe, big
conference room. They were talking about standardization.
And I represent Finland in the ISO
IEC JTC3 group where they
standardize quantum. And all of the European
member states are there independently. They don't have an
EU-wide strategy on standards, whereas the
US has a huge delegation, China has a huge delegation. So I
stand up, I'm like, guys, we have to get together. We have to get a
European strategy for standards, not just the Finnish strategy
or German strategy. And the people on the
stage are saying, well, yeah, but it's not so simple. You know, Petra,
it's really difficult. I'm like, yeah, it's difficult. That's why we have to solve it.
Come on, guys, we're in quantum. It's difficult. It's a challenge, let's do it.
And everyone's just like, you know, she's such a troublemaker.
So I have had a lot of situations like
that. And looking back, I don't regret
being the person standing up. I don't regret being
the person raising the issue, raising the
awareness. But if I had to correct anything,
I would correct the way I presented myself. Because,
you know, especially I've been thinking about the guys
in the management team nominating the best people
they think to be the technology fellow of Nokia Research
Center. All of these men were thinking about people they
know, you know, from their, from their school or their friends,
people they trust, people they genuinely thought would be
the best person. And if they would nominate 5 people, it would be 4
men and 1 woman. Whereas the women in the
management team, they would usually nominate 50% men,
50% women. That's like, that is statistical
in voting patterns. Men tend to vote for men, women tend
to vote men and women. So none of
those people, none of those men had bad intentions. When
they nominated. So for me to go in and
hurt their feelings was bad. It was bad judgment. I was very young,
so I regret that. So it's just something that I've learned
to be better at communications and empathy. Empathy,
that's the key word. What's one piece of
advice— maybe you just answered it— what's one piece of advice you'd give your younger
self at the start of your quantum journey? Yeah, have more
empathy for sure. Yeah, and just,
um, I don't want to give advice to anyone, well, for myself, but,
um, one of the things that we often have to do,
especially for younger women in the industry, is to
do a lot of homework, make sure we have answers to all the
questions. We don't want to be caught in a technical
conversation, you know, without having all the answers.
Um, um,
also so many times people push back and say, well, you
don't have a tech technical background, you don't have a technology degree, so
you can't understand what we're talking about. So to
identify what your value is and communicate,
being able to communicate, and I'm still learning this, like in the
intro you said, what are you doing now? I was like, I'm not sure. So
to, to learn to identify your value and to communicate
your value in a very concise is, is important.
And yeah, always prepare for a plan, Plan B. That's
my advice. How do you stay motivated during
setbacks or complex research challenges?
I love to work with young people. I'm mentoring 2 young people.
It's fantastic. I, I just have
hope for the future. And, um, I also stay
motivated by logging off from the computer and from social
media. It's very— that is very healthy. I have— I
got chicken yesterday. I have 5 chickens now, and I have 3 dogs. So,
uh, just go for a walk with, with the dogs and play with the
chicken. That's one way of staying motivated,
um, especially with quantum. It's because it's a natural science,
so I I just love to think about not just
quantum as computers, which is, by the way, one of the things why I
got so fascinated about quantum in the first place is it's not computer
science, it's not plastic and metal and wire. Well, it has
some wires, but because it's a natural science, because it's
atoms, it's nature. So finally, we're like
really merging biology and
computers. And I think that's really fascinating.
What does success mean to you in the context of
a long and evolving career?
Um, success.
Um, I, uh,
someone told me a few weeks ago
they were moving on with their career, and they told me that, you know, Petra,
There are 3 stages in your career. One is,
um, first stage is you work for other people,
and then the second stage is you work with other people,
and then the third stage is other people work for you.
And that kind of stuck with me. I thought like, that doesn't feel
complete, and I was thinking about it, um, and I
would add a fourth stage is when you go back in the beginning
and work for other people again. So
the ability to make a difference, the ability
to help others and be the change. You know, when you
have a big movement like a political or I don't know,
any big movements and you track back in history, it always
starts with one person. There's whatever it is,
there's one person. Always in the very beginning. So
like, to me, a success— like, when
I die, and if there's anything in the world that
somebody tracks back and said she was the person, like, that would
be a total success for me. That, that would
make me happy. Was there a time when you were tempted to
give up, and what kept you going? Uh,
Never, never give up. No, I mean, there, there have been
times when I have reinvented myself over and over and
over. I, like the example
that I gave, I mentioned that I was the head of marketing at Nokia
Research Center. You know, in large corporations, they
do reorgs every year or every other year, and the
people who don't have a place, you know, they get
sacked basically. And I found after one reorg, I found
myself in the Nokia Research Center with scientists
having a business degree. And I had, I
think I had 2 months to create a new job for
myself and my team. I had a team
before we would be laid off. And I just figured like, hey, this
is research. Who gives the money to research? It's
investors. What do investors get in return? They get
long-term plants, they get long-term revenue. We should have a
marketing department that tells investors why they should invest
in long-term research and what they're getting in return. So I, you know,
I pitched my case and was able to
basically create this marketing department for the
research unit from scratch. And then,
you know, I've been moving to different countries, uh,
starting many, many companies.
So yeah, reinventing yourself is, is something that
keeps you going. How do you keep learning
and growing when technology moves so fast? Well,
I think the thing is to step back. That's like my safety
valve. I cannot, you know, focus on the
technical development because it's so fast, especially in
quantum. There are different modalities.
Different use cases,
if you look at the tools and the supply chains, it's just
so complicated. You have to take a step back and figure
out where, where your strength is. And
that's what I'm doing.
What book, idea, or person has
influenced your thinking most
outside or inside of quantum?
What book? Oh, I know what it is. It is—
ah, you should have warned me. Hold on.
Good thing I had it close by because I can't remember. It is Sparks
of Genius. Oh, you can't see it. The 13 Thinking Tools
of the World's Most Creative People. It's about polymaths.
It's a really good book, actually.
I met a person in the, the launch party of the
International Year of Quantum in Paris more than a year ago.
I was sitting in a dinner and there was a young man beside me and
he had this book. And, you know, I reached over and said, what is that
book? And he told me that he always carries this book with him.
So I went back home and I got the book, and then he approached me
and asked me to be his mentor. So I've been mentoring him for a year.
And we did a podcast episode on my podcast,
The Pockets, on this book. And I
think the polymath thinking is marrying
different fields into your experience
really helps be creative. For example, my husband makes
wine. So when I watch him design
new wines and go into the fields and doing the
whole agriculture thing, It helps me figure out,
you know, things for me in quantum or things for me in consulting or advisory
services, which is strange, but that's, that's how
the human mind works. I've asked you
about advice you'd give your younger self. What's the best
piece of advice someone has given you?
Oh, what is the piece of advice someone has given
me? Oh, I guess it's my dad. It's just,
be yourself, Petra. Just be yourself always.
Probably the most powerful piece of advice you could
ever give a woman would be that. To trust
yourself. Believe in yourself. Don't let
people make you think
you're less. Exactly,
right? Yeah, yeah. He always said like, I trust
you, and that was like the biggest push. Big. Like when
he said like he trusts me, I have to give it
all I have. I have to give my best to whatever I'm doing,
right? I remember, I think I must have been about 12,
and I said something and my mother turned to me and she said, okay, this
is the last moment that you doubt yourself ever. Yeah,
yeah, good advice. Like, what? And she's like, yeah, let's say
it again. And I'm like, yeah,
right. Yeah, it was really powerful. Looking
ahead, what future in quantum are you
personally most excited to help build?
It's something I don't know too much about, but what excites
me the most is the intersection of quantum and biology. So what
is going to happen? Because I— the reason why I love
quantum is because it's a natural science. So how do we
take the atoms and the physics and the biology and
marry those and what's going to happen from there? So I'm really looking
forward to seeing developments in that, that area.
Oh, me too. I know it's crazy.
So for young women or career switchers, who are
listening today, what's the single most important first
step they could take to
enter into the quantum ecosystem? Yeah, I, I think it's probably what I
mentioned already, is identify your value
and, um, practice how to communicate your value.
Because to me, you know, I have a business degree,
so to me everything is selling and buying. So whatever it is that— even
when you're a researcher, even if you don't realize it, you're
selling something every time you open your mouth or you send out an email.
So for young women, identify where you're really good
at, what it is that you can bring to the table, and, and
just be courageous and go out there and
give it all you got and do your homework. And also, something
that's not talked about very much is, as a young
woman or a woman or anybody, If you're in a team or in an
environment where you are trying to do your best
and you still feel that you're not appreciated, it's okay
to quit. Don't stick around forever if it's
not working. Someone else will appreciate you. Like,
it's not a failure to leave if things are not working out for you.
I think I've seen so many people push, push, push and be
miserable if like If they don't appreciate you,
someone else will. So
what role do partnerships between academia,
startups, and large enterprises play
in accelerating progress in this, in this sector? That is
such an important question. Like
I mentioned, I, the reason why I wrote my book is I have worked for
a big corporation. I've worked as a startup entrepreneur. Entrepreneur
and in the government. And they, all
these different entities, they really have a different language. They
have just different acronyms, but they speak a different language.
Um, they're all important and they all have a
part to play. Um, but I think we also
should be mindful that they need to work together better
than they are. And I'll give you examples. So when
When I worked in a big corporate, we would often get
emails or phone calls saying, hey, I have a really great idea for you,
a product idea. You should do this and this product. And, you know, we would
say, yeah, we just spent 6 months investigating this and
decided it's not worth it, but thanks so much for your idea. And they would
get offended every time, like, oh, you don't understand, this is the greatest idea ever.
And we're like, no, you don't understand, it doesn't have business value.
So, so So for people to understand that just because
you don't see a company put out a product that you think would be great,
it doesn't mean they never thought about it. They're not stupid.
People think that the corporates didn't come, they
just didn't think to do this thing. But yes, they did, and they
decided not to do it. So that's one thing.
The other example that I noticed very quickly when I went
from the corporate environment to the startup world is
that that corporate people tend to think that startup people are
just innovative guys hanging around with nothing to
do and are a free resource. So for example,
corporates, they organize hackathons and they think
that the startup company is going to spend weeks of their time coming up
with ideas or prototypes for this corporate. They're going to fly to
another country and with the whole management team and spend
days in your location for free. No, they have
investors. They have to, you know, do their own work. So they're not a
free resource for you, Mr. Corporate Guy.
That is something like I've over and over I had to explain to
corporates like, no, startups don't work that way.
And then another thing that still kind
of rubs me the wrong way is how
private sector people think that people in the government are
stupid. And so, for example,
I don't know if you remember if you saw when Mark Zuckerberg
went to Congress 2 years ago and
there was a senator like in his 80s who didn't understand the
business model. He asked like, how do you make money? And
Zuckerberg said, well, you know, we run ads and everyone in the
private tech industry were laughing like, oh, these senators are so stupid. They have no
idea what's going on. That's not true. There are, there are super smart
people in the government. Um, uh, the White
House Office of Science and Technology, for example,
the quantum person that was there, Charles Tahan, went to work for Microsoft.
Super smart scientist. Like, he didn't go from being
a stupid government person to being a brilliant
scientist at Microsoft overnight. No, he was always a brilliant scientist.
So we have We have all these super smart, brilliant people in
government, and the people in the private sector should not overlook
that talent. I forgot what you asked me, but
anyway, that was a long rant. It was good. It was good. I liked it.
What recent breakthrough in the field made you sit up and
say, oh, okay, this is moving faster than people think?
I, you know, I don't follow that. I don't follow that.
I'm— I will let the scientists do the science, and
whichever science wins, I will take it to the government and help the
government invest in it. Okay. Okay.
Are there any tools or communities or resources
that you would recommend to anyone who's curious
about quantum? Um, I, I'm probably
not the best person to ask that question at Impact Quantum, of
course. Um,
yeah, I mean, I'm a member in a lot of women in
quantum groups on LinkedIn. I think they're all great. I can't name one
over another. Has there been a moment
where you felt particularly supported and heard
by other women in in technology?
Oh my gosh, Candice, your questions.
Ah, sadly
I can't remember. That's so sad.
There must have been. There— was there like a, a tech conference that
you'd gone to and, you know, and then you, you know,
what someone else had said really resonated with you, and then you,
you know, it really turned into something. But no, not yet.
Well, let me answer this way. Um, when I wrote
my newsletter last week about women and technology, one of the things that I was
thinking about is, you know, whenever you go to a tech conference, there's
a track for women and whatever the technology is, and I
rarely attend those tracks. For two reasons.
One is the timing and the location of that track is
always the worst possible. They shove that track wherever there's like free
time. So it usually overlaps with something more interesting,
which is the actual subject or the topic of the conference. And the
other one is the reason why I rarely
go or attend is because it's just women. It's women on
stage and women in the audience. It's women talking to women and it's very
cozy and fuzzy and it's really nice. Um,
but like, what is happening now
in the world, in society, in
politics, in gender—
I don't know what to call it— what's happening has, um,
made me think that, like I mentioned earlier, I need to broaden
my sphere of influence. I need to talk to
wider audience, a wider audience of women, wider audience of men.
And I've revised my thinking. I actually think—
excuse me— I actually think that these tracks are
useful because women need safe spaces. Women
need that fuzzy and cozy environment once in a while because it's so
harsh out there. I think that's fair. I think that's fair to
say. And I think that the more that we get out there and show
you know, different faces. I think that really does
help younger women see themselves in
other people to say, wait a minute, you know, I like business, I
like this, I like that. She'd like business, she went here, she
did that. You know, it opens up, it opens up the
path for those that are coming up. And I just think it's so
vitally important that we show them. That there is a space.
Absolutely, absolutely. I think it's funny, I, I
never had an imposter syndrome in technology. So when I was
in those rooms with all the guys, I always felt like I belong
here. This is— I have a role here, I belong here. But I think I
might have had a little bit of imposter syndrome with, with the women.
Like, I felt that, who am I to tell any
woman what they should do or what they shouldn't do, or
I'm not successful enough to be a role model to anyone.
So I think I'm just discovering, like, I'm over 50 and
I'm discovering all these new aspects
of myself and my thinking. So I think I need to work on my
imposter syndrome with women. And I
am mentoring women, and women approach
me and ask me how how I, you know,
how I've done my career or how I ended up where I am. And,
and I hope I can help, help them. I hope I have
something to offer. If I do, that's great. I think you, I think you
do. I think the fact that you're trying to take such positive steps to make
it better for other women, again, lifting up those around us
and, and leading by example, putting ourselves out there.
And saying, you know, you too, you too can do this and you too
deserve it. And I— that's, that's really kind of
what Women in Quantum to me is all about. You know,
where can, where can people find out more about what you're doing and
who you are if they want to reach out? Petra
Soderling.com or LinkedIn. You heard
it here first. You heard it here first. There you go. So,
Petra, again, this has been fantastic. I thank you
so much for your time and doing this with us today,
and I hope that we get to speak again. Super. Thanks so much,
Candace.