I think success for me would be to, you know,
to live exciting adventures during the day and still, still
be home in time to share
dinner with my daughter and to put her to bed.
Success in quantum doesn't always look like headlines or hardware
breakthroughs. Sometimes it looks like balance. Welcome to
Women in Quantum.
Welcome back to Women in Quantum. Hi, I'm Candace
Gilhooley, and Women in Quantum is a podcast
where we spotlight the brilliant, bold, and
boundary-breaking women shaping the future of quantum
technology. The show is about more than science.
It's about curiosity, courage,
leadership, and the real journeys behind the breakthroughs.
Each week I sit down with founders, researchers,
engineers, and innovators to unpack how they got here
and what they're building and why their stories matter,
especially for the next generation. If you've ever
wondered whether you belong in deep tech, this is your
space. Let's dive in together. Good
morning, Sabine. How are you? Good morning. I'm fine. What about
you? I'm doing great. Today we are going to speak with
Sabine, and she is the Chief Quantum Project
Officer at Gensii. Hi,
Sabine. Hi. I'm very excited about
today. So I want want to, I to start at the very beginning. Okay. I
want to start with you in elementary school,
grammar school, in France, and what
was your most exciting
subject? What did you really want to know more about?
So I've been passionate about a lot of things over
the years, but I think what's really striking,
um, and some of you might be the same way, is when I
want to pursue a subject, I go all in.
So I've been into history, archaeology,
a lot of stuff. I've been into math
also a lot, biology also. I wanted to
be a doctor, then I wanted to be a lot of things.
Then I really, really got deep into math,
I'd say, in high school because I had
this teacher who was, well,
she was at first very hard to catch, I'd say,
because she also taught in prep
school for, you know, higher education, very
top-ranked engineering schools
in France. And she was also a teacher at my high school. So it
was a bit hard to follow. But
getting into the upper grades, I finally caught up
with the way that she taught math.
And then she pushed us to, you know,
take some exercises that were really next level.
And it was really nice because you could
see how far you could go even at this
high school level. So it was really a really nice, nice
adventure with with this, this teacher. And I, I
really kept in touch after, and she was really
pushing towards me taking
an engineering degree. But I had
some discussions with my parents, and as they knew that
I was also very much into
literature geopolitics. I was interested in, in
some other topics. So they
suggested that I start with a business and
administration degree,
which I did, and it it was, was super interesting,
to be honest. So I, I got into a Paris-based
business school that is called ESCP,
that is a very, very old and I took my first
economic lessons and, and also
history of the economy. So I was, I thought it was
super interesting. And I was also very
interested in marketing, international marketing.
And so that's also where I got to know a bit
more about technology.
Because these were, uh, very good topics for marketing courses, uh,
but I missed math and physics.
Okay, this specific business school had a partnership
with an engineering school, uh, that was called
Supélec at that time. So the, um,
engineering school of electricity, let's say. Uh, now
it's called Centrale Supélec. There's been some fusions and so
on, some mergers.
Um, and, uh, and I, I took some prep lessons, uh, during my
first year in business school to enter this
engineering school and have this kind of double, uh,
curriculum in both schools. And, uh,
this is where it gets interesting because,
well, I, I came from a business school which was
probably, yeah, you had an equal
number of women and men in that school. It was quite
balanced. Okay. But in this
electricity engineering school, it was all men.
I think we were about 16% of women
in, in the first year. But
to be honest, I I thought the atmosphere was still
great. It was a very warm atmosphere for women
because they were happy to see that some women had taken these
courses. Okay, okay. It was a nice
place to be, and actually my
friends, they helped me a lot because for the first
year in engineering school, it was quite hard because I had to catch up
with the two very intensive prep years that they had
had before the entrance exam. So some of them were like the,
the highest-ranked students in in the, the best
prep schools in France. And so I had to accept
that at first I wouldn't understand everything, that
I would be lost, that it would be more
difficult for me to understand the,
the lessons and to take the exams, so that I had
to work twice as hard or maybe three times as hard as
my fellow students. For that first year to just you
pass, know, the exams. But there was a really strong
solidarity because we didn't have the same background. So whenever
we had to take these oral exams, know,
you I was way better prepped than they were because I was
used to, you know, selling. When you are in a business school, these, these are
exercises that you do in class and also in prep school.
And so I was coaching them for these specific oral
exams, and they were correcting
my exercises and trying to prep me for the, the written
exam. So even though I think on the technical
stuff I was way behind them, but in
the, the way that you present things and that you make things clear
to an audience, I was also supporting them.
So trying to find the right balance between what you give and
what you take. Okay, so this was—
so, so you started in grammar school, you went to university, you went
on to business school. In business school, you got excited by
electrical engineering, um, and then you
transferred into that. And that was really the first time you're saying where you looked
around the room and you realized you were one of few women
that were in that discipline. So let me ask you, did that—
so when you navigate those moments when you might feel less
confident, especially when the stakes are high, You know,
how do you handle that? Well, my,
my father used to say to me, I think
that, I think is, is really essential. You don't play
with your life there. I mean, if you don't get the degree, it
doesn't determine everything that's going to happen next.
So at that stage, I mean, I'm not a
surgeon. I was not doing exercises on human
corpses. So in the end,
I just— well, it was all about having some bonus lessons,
learning something new, potentially having a double
degree. But if I didn't make it,
well, then I would still have this business and administration degree,
and it was already, already a good
academic background, so I would find a job
anyhow. Yeah. So was there a moment
when you started doing the electrical engineering that you—
you're moving back towards more math and more physics—
that you were like, this is what I really want to do? Like, when did
that happen for you?
I think it kind of happened every time it was—
it was tricky, every time it was tough.
Because in the end, when you actually
acquired, you know, the knowledge, you were so proud of yourself.
Okay. That's important. I like this feeling of
being challenged and, you know, giving it, giving it
all. I like that.
So what has surprised you the most about your
journey into quantum? How
multidisciplinary it is, I think.
But, you know, I didn't have much experience before I
got into quantum. I, I
worked as an apprentice on mission-critical systems,
so it was mostly about homeland security
and the military. So,
but the people, they mostly had the same background, or at least they
were from the Army. Formerly from the army. After that,
I moved to HPC where you had,
well, people with different
technical backgrounds, but not that
different. Like going into quantum, I discovered
the interest, very interest of having a PhD working for an
industrial player, which I had never thought
of before. How
you need to translate your physicist language
into the mathematician's language, into the
computer scientist's language, and that it
takes a lot of effort to, you know, trying to find
common grounds to actually go
somewhere together. But I— and, and
also Like moving
further as the industry developed, what I think was super
interesting is that I, I really run into brilliant
minds that were not directly involved
in developing the technology, but that were
involved in developing the business, developing the
structures, promoting the technology,
trying to you know, find the right networks
to connect these industrial players
to some user communities, some political
communities. And these, like, non-physicists,
non-mathematicians, masterminds, they're
probably as important as the people that
have their hands on the development of the technology.
Okay. And some of them are women. And
some of them are women. Yeah. So could you describe
a day in the life of what you do? Well,
so what we do is that Gen Z is—
well, most of our time is devoted to
animation around the platform that we provide
access to. So we try to reach out as much as
possible to the end users of our
supercomputers to make them aware that quantum is coming,
that it has some
potentialities for the work that they are
doing, that
if they want want to, if they to explore quantum computing, they can find the
right experts to help them with that, to train
them also. So we
are investing a lot in a kind of
public computing capabilities business development,
which is a very specific job actually.
So we are doing it for academic end users, but
also for industrial end users, because
the modalities to access our public platform
is to pursue open research. So it's free
because it's government funded, but it's for open
research mostly. And we're also very much
invested in public procurement of these
prototypes, of these
first systems that are produced by
mostly European quantum startups or quantum
providers. At the moment. So today we
have a Pascal neutral atom system that is up
and running in our HPC facility, in the
CA's HPC facility, and we have
a Quandela system that is owned by EuroHPC and that
will be up and running in a matter of weeks now.
And we are currently procuring a new
type of animal, I would
say, because we're procuring a cat qubit system. So that
would be an early FTQC platform.
So that's a lot of interesting things that you were just
discussing. So what skills beyond technical knowledge
have been essential in your journey to date?
Curiosity, like being, being open
to learning new things, um,
accepting that you can't understand everything, but that you need
to understand a certain amount of the topic, uh,
to pursue a specific goal. And that
accepting that the rest of the work sometimes must be
done by other people. So for it's, uh, me, um,
it's not that hard because I have a very very good relationship with
Felix that was in the podcast previously,
that is really our technical expert and with whom I
try to delegate, you know, the tasks. Okay.
And who explains a lot
to me, which is nice. But I think also,
and maybe that is specific to me, but I think I learn
mostly from discussions with people
rather than reading articles. So I, even though I
have this, this literature that is
accessible, I tend to go discuss
with the experts in, in the topics that I need to master
in order to make sure that I have the right ideas in place
to pursue the goal that that is, is set. So,
discussions and, you know, establishing your network,
finding the right experts. I
think that is essential. Yeah. Okay. So, let me ask
you, what challenges did you face early on in your career
that you might not have expected?
Trying to navigate in a new
in a new field, I'd say. Well, I think
going into this electrical engineering school, I had
an idea that I would like to work in an industry,
but the, the first internship that I
had was in the tire manufacturing industry, which is
completely different, super oriented towards
innovation still, but in a completely different field and,
and more established one.
When when I, I entered the quantum industry, I had no
idea that the structure that I work for now existed.
So, and I think they were not yet even yet investing
into quantum computing. So it's all taking
place now. It's, it's all structured now.
So you don't really have a very clear
outlook on what will be the next stage or
the next step in your career. So I think that's,
that's a super opportunity because my next job probably
doesn't exist, right? That's totally
true. But, but still, it's, um,
it's tricky uh, because, I, I've— well, I've been used
to, you know, discussing with people with very, very clear
career path, you know, uh, in the same, uh, in the same, uh,
company in the same field, more or less.
But since I got into quantum, I've, I've done
tasks in, in, in very, very different
fields. I started working as a product
marketing manager at Atos, which is now
no longer Evident but Bull since last week.
Then I moved to sales operations. To support their sales
force into selling quantum. Then I moved
to Quandela as a business developer, and
now I am product— I am project manager working on
large European procurements and
national public initiatives.
So yeah, it's, it's—.
You've moved around. I mean, you've moved around a lot of different
types of you positions, know, that kind of give you a perspective on the
whole system. You know what I mean? Which allows you to kind
of understand how all the moving parts work together, which
I think is important when breaking it down. So
has this influenced how you lead or you collaborate
and even how you mentor others? I
think so, yes, because what strikes me on,
I think, on a daily basis is
how, how you deal with the
customer-provider relationship. So
I've, I come from the industrial side, so I've been
in a position where I wanted to sell something
to some of my current partners, you know, HPC centers
in Europe. So I think I
kind of get what is at stake
when some startups, they come to us now trying to sell
their technology, trying to promote their technology,
asking us also to provide
some awareness to our HPC center network
on what they are doing. So I think it also
helps me understand a
bit better what what is, is going on
in in the, the mind that is facing me at the moment.
So have you ever doubted your place in this space?
And if you have had the doubt, how did you move through it?
I think I kind of frequently
doubt my place
in in this, this space, because I'm
not an administrative person.
But I am a bit in a way. Some
people, they come to me with technical questions.
Some of them I know how to answer to, some of them
I don't even understand the question. So
I— yeah, you know, the, the legitimacy that you
have is somehow fragile on this type
of, of emerging technologies.
So yeah, I think
in a way, in a way, working with someone like Felix has helped me
because it's very smooth. You know,
we we can, can share on— we are in the same office
on a daily basis, so we can share very easily
on the things that we are not sure about, the the
things that we'd like to explore more to, you know,
strengthen our position also as advocates,
for example.
But what really helps me go through these, these
phases, I think, is the discussion with
some of my colleagues, the reassurance from
my boss that he hired me for a lot of good
reasons that he has to repeat
Sometimes the connection, like the friendly connection that
I have with some members of our ecosystems.
I've made very, very deep friendships
amongst women, but also men
in this field. And sometimes it's you nice,
know, to have feedback on the impact that you have.
Okay, I think that's important to know that you—
that what you're doing has meaning and that
you're making progress. And so what
problem are you the most excited to help solve?
Um, well, I'd say the industrialization, the industrialization of
these systems. Like,
I, I, I'm faced with all of these
startups, these founders. They, they, they gave it all
in, you know, for their technology.
And more than money,
you know, more than public investment, public procurement, what
I think that we bring when we, when we have these projects
with them is the adventure of getting
these machines out of the lab and having them
working in an industrial environment,
in a wild environment where they don't master
everything. I think it has— where
I have these two examples of Pascal and
Kwandela, but the feeling is, and
the The impression that I got from these two projects is
that we have grown on both sides. We have
learned a lot from these, from these deliveries,
from these acceptances and
these integration projects. And I'm
also very excited that we're able to do that
also at a European level. As I mentioned
previously, Some of the HPC centers that I work with now,
I've sold devices to them.
So now it's funny because
we moved from a provider to
customer relationship to a partner to partner relationship.
And I still really much enjoy working with these people.
We have, by the way, some of these
HPC centers, they have women as project managers.
Well, to name a few, I really enjoyed working with Laura
Schultz, who is now working for Argonne National Lab in the US,
but formerly she was working at the Leibniz
Rechenzentrum in Germany, and she
was really a mentor to me. Even though we were
partners, I mean, she really supported me through
these projects. I worked with Sarah Martella. From,
from Ginecca in Italy, Alba
Severa Lierta in BSC in Spain,
with Arianna Torres in the Netherlands at SURF.
So these are just examples of, I'd say,
very important women in my field,
which they really do have a very strong
impact on how this field is
developing now in Europe because they are leading
major procurement and also integration
projects that are supporting the startups,
supporting the users, and, and the overall
development in this field. Okay, do you have any
choice as to the projects that you get to work on?
To a certain extent, obviously.
So The program that I am part of in
France stems from the national quantum strategy. So we—
it goes both ways because we
advise based on our understanding of the
market, our understanding of the needs of
the potential users on
the potentialities of these technology for solving
specific use cases. And so at a political
level, they— I think they listen to us so we can
suggest, and they validate or not
based on, you know, the bigger picture that they have
also by working with other European
members of your HPC, for example. So this
is a trial and error approach, I'd say,
with with our
stakeholders. Where do you
see the biggest bottleneck happening right now in the
quantum ecosystem?
Well, it's— I'd say it's not my opinion
directly, but it's, you know, something that I
hear quite often and that I've grown convinced
of is is that we've invested
massively on the development of the hardware, which I think
is essential. It's required,
but we are maybe lagging a bit behind
on the development of algorithms and the software
stacks. So this is something, and also
the support to the adoption by end users.
For example, we would like, and this is one of the goals of our
project, to foster the adoption of
quantum technologies and mostly quantum computing amongst the
HPC users. But this requires a
lot of not just awareness, but
also support, research to, to
guide them towards really digging a bit
into their codes and seeing what could be potentially
accelerated and to which extent, at what
horizon by these quantum
technologies. And so this is probably,
I'd say, the focus that we need to have in the, in the coming
years, not leaving behind the development of the platforms,
but we need to be able to use them when they're sophisticated enough
to reach these, these gains.
How do you stay adaptable when there's big
industry shifts? So we
have a I'd very, say, dynamic
community here in France, and we are very well connected to
our European and international
partners. So through discussions at
conferences, through
Yeah, I mean, being open-minded,
listening a lot to some experts.
So I think this is how we are trying to, you know,
keep up with, with most of the
important shifts, technological shifts.
I hope we're not missing too much, but
well, we have a very good
relationship with an expert in France that is called Olivier
Zrati, who produces and updates
a very, very thorough book, which is
free, by the way, that is called Understanding Quantum Technologies.
He's doing it, you know, as a hobby
and is very well— he's very well connected
to both academic and industrial communities.
In Europe and worldwide, and discussions with
Olivier are always very informative.
So in case we miss something, we might
find out through Olivier. Okay.
All right. What is some advice
that you would give your younger self at the beginning
of your journey into quantum?
I'd say don't, don't fear to, you know,
yeah, the fact that you don't know everything.
Don't be afraid to ask. Yeah, I think that's
a great, a great thing to learn, that it's okay to
ask and not to feel stupid. You're in fact stupid when you
don't ask. You know, you can't expect everyone except to know
everything, and you just have to be willing to accept that it's
a wonderful thing to learn. And, you know, and,
you know, in quantum and just figuring out
this field, I'm learning something new. I'm learning multiple things
every single day, right? And then as soon as I feel like I've got a
grasp, I'm like, not quite. You know, there's a little
bit more to it that you need to understand. So what practical
steps could students take right now if they wanted to enter
the quantum field?
Well, as always, I think
a a good, good thing to do is to get informed by reaching out
to people working in the quantum industry.
I, well, I'm not always responding as
quickly as I'd like to, but I try. We
get a lot you of, know, messages on LinkedIn from people
studying in math, physics, or even in business
schools or whatever, and who are
interested, curious about this field and want to know
more, or are looking for internships or
for thesis in in these, this field.
And I think this is a This is not an easy move, you know,
reaching out to someone that you have no connection with,
but this is— I mean, if you don't try, you will
never get it, so you should do it. You should try
reaching out to a person that you've heard of through
a podcast, or I don't know, if you look into
a presentation and you see a name, don't hesitate to reach
out to these people. Very often, that's my experience
in this, in this quantum field, they are quite open
to new connections, to discussing with people who
are curious about this field. And so I think
through these discussions you will understand a bit more how it's
structured, what is needed, what skills are
required, and you might be surprised they will need human
resources They will need secretaries. They will
need engineers. They will need in
a number of fields. They will need computer scientists.
They will need physicists with or without
PhD thesis. So, and that's,
yeah, so it's important to, you know,
see where you are going. And so to
just set this goal, you need to have more information and
by reaching out to people, you might get it.
So how do you manage intensity and burnout
in high-performance environments?
Communication is super important.
Communication. So I work in a multi-organization
environment, meaning that on all of the
projects that we're involved in, we don't work alone. I work in
a 20-people organization. So we rely heavily on
CEA, CNRS, other organizations,
other research organizations. So
there, there might always be room to
delegate something to someone. And if you don't
communicate on your workload, on something that
you're, I don't know, blocked on, then you will never
know if someone else might be able to help.
So the— probably the best, yeah, the best way to
deal with that is to communicate
and to, yeah, not to hesitate to say,
I am too loaded, there are too many things on my
plate at the moment, and I will need to find someone
else to do the rest. Yeah.
Because that, yeah, you can always just take on so many
projects. So what's one
misconception people have about working in quantum that you'd like
to reframe? I think there's
still this idea that you need to have
a PhD, and I have
so many examples of people like myself who don't.
I think one of the— I mean, the misconception is
this frequent that a
lot of people, they call me Dr. Mair when
I've never been ever in my life. I've never even considered
engaging in a PhD thesis. So
yeah, I think that might be one of the
misconceptions that is still very, very
pregnant at this moment. And it's a pity because
we've got very good masters people
who are doing the job.
Okay. Hmm. How do you think leaders could better
support women in deep tech?
Well, I, I think something that is
working well is the support amongst women.
But not the formal one, like the little things,
the little messages like, yeah, I saw your presentation, it was
really good. Uh, I mean, these
these are, are very tiny examples of how I felt, you
know, promoted by my peers,
uh, by the by the people, women I looked up to. Um,
and this is something that I've experienced in this field. That I think
is working very well. And this is also
something that I tend to replicate even mean, with, I with
women who are older than I am, just by saying,
I saw that you released this paper, or I saw
that you had this achievement, congrats.
This kind of feedback I think is important, or
Yeah, well, yeah, I don't know. I mean, last year there was
this woman from Bôle. She was doing
a programming workshop on a booth at a conference, and we had a minister
coming by the booth, and we rushed
to that woman who was doing something very hard. I mean, to
promote her to this politician who was
randomly stopping by, and it was a good opportunity for
her to, you know, to be shown.
So yeah, I think these are little actions,
not necessarily, you know, trying to push women at all
costs, but, you know, trying to support other women.
Okay, so let me— I didn't ask you about— I don't think I asked you
about mentors, if you had a mentor that really affected you, or have you
been a mentor to someone else? And how has that experience helped
you? Well, I think
that like two examples, very strong example, well,
maybe three, three examples. So the person who, who
identified me to take on this job at Gen-C,
so she, her name is Christelle Piuszczowski. She now works
for NVIDIA, but I met her when I was working
for Bull. At that time, and I actually took over this
product management task that she was having. And we
connected well. And when she
saw that I had left Bull for Kwandela, she told our
boss, because she knew she was leaving Gen-C,
that I would be a good fit. And she did not
just do that, like, she reached out to me and she
discussed with me about the potential position.
She encouraged me also because I thought it was a very
huge leap to take, and I,
I wasn't sure I would be the, the, the best fit for
it and that I would be able to take on the job. And then after,
she connected me to my current boss, Stefan, who I'd say would
be my second mentor. He is
supporting me every day He
tries to see all of my presentations,
tries to help me as much as possible whenever he can.
And he's a very, very busy guy, always very
kind, you know, trying to,
yeah, to make me look up to
myself. So he's a very inspiring person.
And I already mentioned her, but she she really, was
really an important important person on my path, Laura
Schultz, who used to work at LAC. she was, she Like, was,
she's the example. She was my customer when I was working for a bull.
She invited me to do this presentation at LAC in front of a bunch
of very high-profile scientists, and
she really encouraged me to do this
presentation. Later on, when we reconnected as
partners she was really, she
really promoted me amongst the community saying, I
know her from before, she's a really brilliant
woman. So she was really, and she, I
actually, I gave a talk to supercomputing in
November and it was a really hard task for me
because the room was super big and, and I
was talking not about quantum solely, but about a broader
scope. So I was really stressed out and we were in
St. Louis and actually the first person that I saw in that room
was Laura standing at the front row and she asked
questions and she was so supportive that it really
helped me. Even though we don't work together anymore,
she really kept on pushing me and
she was, for the
anecdote, she was one of the first people
that I told about my pregnancy and she was
really happy for me. I mean, so she,
she is actually now a really good friend.
So what responsibility do women like yourself, women who have experience
in the quantum ecosystem and are thriving in it, what kind of
responsibility do you have potentially to the next generation to come
up?
I think we have the responsibility to talk about
what we are doing now to the largest
possible number of people
in who are taking on you these, know, studies.
Um, a good example, for example, would be VivaTech.
This is a conference that we attend every year, and on the Saturday
you have this general public day where you have
children coming to the booth and saying, oh,
I just started studying physics and I'm really
into experiments and so on. And I think we
have the responsibility to make it as
simple as possible. You know, the basics of what
we do, we have to lower the barrier
for them to understand that this is a very exciting topic
and that know, the, the, the, you the physics field, it can
also lead to that. Math can also lead to that. A lot of
tracks can lead to that.
Um, so yeah, trying to, uh, uh, uh, tell little girls
that, uh, these scientific topics, yeah, of course they can
pursue them. And there are a lot of jobs, uh, in our industry
for them after that. I like that. I like
that a lot. So what excites you the most about what
we're going to see in the next 5 to 10 years in quantum?
The applications, the use cases. Definitely,
definitely. I want want to, I to see
actual impact of these platforms.
Ideally, I would like to see it on different technologies because
I think all of them are really interesting. I don't know if all of them
will survive, you know, to this, to
this path, like for the classical computing
track. But I really hope that
we that we will, will find some breakthroughs on different
technologies and on on
different, different fields that will really bring into the light
all of the hard work that is being done right now.
What message would you most want young women around the world
to hear from you about the
quantum ecosystem and the future of deep tech?
Well, for the quantum ecosystem, I think there are
a lot of inspiring women, a lot of inspiring
examples in this industry.
This is a very good place to work. I think most—
in most organizations that I know, academic,
public, private, industrial, you find
these very nice cultures.
And there there are, yeah, are a lot of organizations that are led by
women or where women play very important
roles. So, so I'd say this this is, is a
good field to work in, and you should invest
in a track that leads you to us. Yeah.
I didn't ask you this before, but how do you stay motivated during
setbacks or complex research challenges?
Um, we, we have a very festive culture, I'd say,
in our little program team.
So like up until
now, I think the major
downturns of what we've experienced, we've been
able to have always one of us keep
motivating the others. I have a
very optimistic boss, So, Stéphane is
a really nice asset in these times.
And I think Felix is also
quite nice to work with in
these times. And we also have a project coordinator who
is called Jacques-Charles Lafourrière, who works for CEA, who is
a very, very nice leader
and has, I think, also these
motivating spirit. OK, I
like that. OK, so now my last question
is going to be, how does— what does
success mean to you in the context
of a long and evolving career?
Well, I think this, this, this
has evolved recently for me because I've become
a mother. So my life has changed quite a bit.
Absolutely. I think success for
me would be to, you know, to live exciting
adventures during the day and still, still be home
in time to, to share dinner with my daughter
and to put her to bed. So, you
know, there you go. That's balancing, you know,
your home and your curiosity and your business
life and the exciting things that you do every So if people
want to know more about what you do and
what you're involved in, where, where should should we, where we send them?
OK, so we have on LinkedIn,
I'd say you can follow the HQI France
organization, which is the project page.
You can follow Gensi definitely, which is the organization that I work
for. I also urge you to go see what your
HPC joint undertaking is leading
as projects regarding HPC and quantum
because we have massive, massive
updates coming in. And yeah,
you can, you can go see the HQI website,
hqi.fr, Gency's website,
gency.fr, and also don't
hesitate to reach out directly on LinkedIn. I try to catch up.
Oh, that's wonderful. Thank you. Today has been fantastic. I really
appreciate, you know, the behind the scenes, under the
COVID you know, what's going on, how you got to where you are,
and why, you know, you're so inspiring to other, to other
women out there. And, and I really, really appreciate your time
today. Thank you very much. Thank you. I'm going to let the music
then take us out.