I don't have any kind of physics background. That's what I tell them. I tell
them I am an electrical engineer who likes to code,
right? And I like talking about science,
and I got a PhD in quantum without actually having a physics
background. I work with physicists, but I feel like right
now I think it's the best time for people who are curious
about quantum to get into quantum because right now it's actually
outside of the physics experimental
realm, let's put it like that, and more into application.
Welcome to Women in Quantum.
Hi, it's Candace Gilhooley. Welcome back. We're here today
to talk to Sarah Metwally, who is a
research associate, and we're very excited to talk about what
her perspective is in the quantum computing industry.
Sarah, how are you today? Doing very well.
Thank you for having me. How are you? I am great. Thank you so
much. In the green room, we were talking about how you had to run around
the university a little bit to find a quiet spot. It's very busy for you.
Yeah, it's crazy. It's the beginning of the semester,
kinda, you know. People are finally coming
back seriously after the New Year's. That's right. They're all
like, they're ready. They're roaring to go. No, I'm really
excited to talk to you today because I remember a lot about our pre-call,
and if I, if I do recall, and we're going to talk about it, you
are— is it true that you're originally from Egypt? I am originally
from Egypt. Okay. And I want to talk about that.
So I want to talk about when you were a little girl
and you were back in Egypt and you were figuring out what
excited you about the world.
What excited you? What can you remember is the first thing that really
kind of you wanted to know more about?
I, I think that honestly, science, right?
Science was very exciting. All
branches of science, like all of the science topics I took
in school, whether it be like biology, chemistry, physics, or
math. I did do best in math, so math was the
closest to my heart and it got me
interested in because it got me interested in learning more about
science, right? But the way math or like all of
the science topics are taught at school level, you don't actually get to
see how they are practical, especially math, right? Math is the
most abstract thing. They teach you a bunch of things. You do not know
how can you use them. Well, except like, you know, addition and multiplication. You do
not know like how is this going to be useful. So you feel like I'm
wasting time here. Which a lot of people feel about math
classes, right? Generally speaking. But for me, math got
me very interested in the universe.
I like to say math is the language of the universe, which is— it is,
right? It is. And then in high school, I took
my first programming class. Well, back, back in my time. Now I feel old.
Back in my time, programming was not as common. Also was not
as common for women to be like taking programming classes. And then there was this
one And I remember it was Visual Basic and it wasn't
really programming because Visual Basic was basic but on
like visual, like VS Code, right? So it wasn't that you're
actually writing code. It was mostly like very small writing
code that does something, but it wasn't actually writing a full code. But I was
like, oh, this is cool. I would like to learn more about that. So there
was programming and there was math and engineering kind of like
overlaps in the intersection of that. And I was like, okay, I want to be
a computer engineer because because those people do a lot of math and they
do coding, so they seem to be doing the two things I'm excited about.
Now, was that supported in the Egyptian culture that you were
raised in when you were in school? Was it, you know, were you—
were they— were they supportive of you wanting to pursue, you know, math
and science? Were they trying to shift you into something else that they might have
considered more appropriate? What was— what was the atmosphere like?
So that is actually a great question. I'll be like, okay, my
parents wanted me to be a doctor,
a medical doctor, that is, right? And I was like,
I can't. First of all, if I see blood, I will faint. So I don't
think I'll make a good doctor, right? I would say like, just based on that,
I don't think I'll be a good doctor. But I was also like, no,
medical school is so many years of study and I'm not doing that. Now, joke's
on me. I'm still at school now. But back then I was like, I'm not
staying in school for this long. To be a doctor also seems like a lot
of effort, and I do not know, different effort, like not the
effort that I wanted to put, right? So I wanted to, to be an
engineer because engineers know how things work, and my brain likes
understanding how things work, right? So it's like engineering is good. There
wasn't much pushback from my parents, but society-wise it's
always like looked upon as like girls in engineering school are like
manish, masculine, you know, because it's
a man's kind of a field. So there's like more
men than women in engineering school in Egypt, which is like
a cool— there are some disciplines actually in engineering school in
Egypt that literally it will be 99.999%
men, and then there is the poor 2 women that
kind of were curious about that and they were like, I want to study that,
especially mechanical engineering, right? That like the few women who
is like, I'm into cars, which is like not something, I guess,
feminine, right? So be like, and get into mechanical engineering.
I felt so bad for those women because though the
percentages was bad in like electronics and
electrical and computer engineering, they were still
better than mechanical engineering. There's still less women.
You were looked on as like, oh, you're manly. And
sometimes, I don't know, I had like male relatives,
like my male cousins who were kind of like closer to age to me. They
were so jealous because they could I did not get into engineering school because it's
a degree, it's a grades-based thing. Like, it's one—
like, in Egypt, the, the top school, it's different than the
US, maybe other countries, right? Like, the top school is medical school. So that's like,
if you have like the top grade, you're— you go to medical school or
dental school, right? Like, they're up there. Uh, and then
engineering. So engineering was like number 2, which is like
different than other countries, which is law school is the hardest. But for us, law
school was not even top 10. It actually was the choice for
people who did not do well in high school. Isn't that interesting?
Wow. Okay. Okay. So
society-wise, it's like, you know, I also had so many
ambitions, which was like, I want to go to grad school, I want to be
a professor, I want to change the world. I had all of these
ambitions, which not a lot of people did. So even within the
university, even the girls that were there, There was me who
was like, I want to travel the world, this country I want to go to,
and this country I want to study in, do an exchange
in. There isn't many exchange programs in the university in Egypt, but I just wanted
to do stuff. And then there was the other girls who were like, I
want to get married, like ideally I leave the university
engaged or married. And then there is me, I was like, I want to
travel. So it was even harder to connect, right? Because
Even within the university, even with women who you would think are
similar-minded because they're studying similar things to you, they
would still, hey, like, I'm getting it because
of— okay, it's— this is a weird thing to say, but like there are
a hierarchy of like how good a
woman is, uh, vis-à-vis when it comes to marriage,
right? And if the woman is, say, in the medical school or engineering school,
that means she's smart, so she will make a good wife and have smart
kids. So like, the— some objective— I'm not saying all
of the women who did that, but a lot of women who went into these
schools was their marriage is like, yes, I'm gonna be looked on as
like I'm an engineer woman or a woman who's a doctor, right?
So I will have better suitors. Oh my God, I can't believe
I'm talking like this, like it's the 1900s, the 1800s.
There's a lot of women— it's called the MRS degree, right?
Yeah, the one— the women that go to school because they want to find their
husbands. I mean, I hate to say it, but You know, when I, when I
went to my 5-year high school graduation,
okay, I could not tell you how many girls,
women were going to law school. Okay.
Like, I swear it was 30% of the class was often was going
off into law school. And then the question was, well, did
they actually all become lawyers or did they end up— and I
hate to say that the predominance of them who actually did get
their law degree that just kind of ratcheted
up to them to being the most, you know, the best kind of mate to
have in marriage. And they all got married. And again, nothing wrong with
marriage. I got married young. Yeah, but you know, if you're going to
school and you're learning, you know, to, to be kind of
a member of society, you want to add something more. Um, that's why you get
all the schooling. So, okay, so women were kind of
judged and, and kind of ranked, let's say, according to what
they're achieving in school. Okay, okay. And you're like, I want to
travel. Of course, wanted me to get married, like,
very desperately, needless to say. And because it's a
thing, right? And, uh, I am— perhaps
was not the most feminine woman, but I
liked— because I dressed practically for school. We had school
from like 8. We had lectures, and then you have to go to labs, and
you have to carry a lot of stuff. We carried so many stuff,
whether it's books or like tools, right? And I was like, why?
I get it. And I super respect for the women who do
both makeup and everything when they go to the university. But for me, I was
like, I need to be comfortable because I will be sitting
for a very extended long time and I need to be comfortable, right?
Even now in the lab. And I was like, I get it. When I go
out, when there's a conference, it's different. But like, if I know that I'm going
to be sitting in the lab for 8 hours, my number one priority is like,
am I wearing comfortable pants? Am I wearing comfortable shoes, right?
However, again, I had a lot of comments like, oh, why don't you wear
more dresses? And I was like, I'm going to the university and going to the
labs. First of all, a dress is dangerous. Some of these labs were like, you
know, you take a little bit of labs like, you know,
civil engineering labs. You had to take like selective, and I like to
take courses from different disciplines of engineering just
because I was curious, still am, curiosity is still a thing. So it's like, or
like chemical lab, like chemical engineering labs, it's like you're not going to be there
with a lot of skin showing, or even not skin because, well, I used to
wear the scarf because it's a religious country in Egypt, right? And my parents are
very religious. So it's like I had to so
many things, right? And I was like, I just, all I wanted to
do honestly was to leave Egypt and to actually be
able to explore who I am and do what I want without the
pressure from society and from my family, which
again, I would say my parents are not the most
pressuring, but they're there and they be like, they would, you
know, guilt trip you as most parents do. It's like, oh, I can't
wait, I just wanna see grandkids, this kind of things, right? Like they will not
be like, hey, go get married. But they would say these things, which for me,
I feel like worse. Just say what you want. Right. I know what
you're trying to say. Just saying,
right? So when, when I finished undergrad, funny enough,
in Egypt, before I did my, my
post— well, my, my postgraduate studies in Japan, but before
Japan even was an option, I was like, cool, I want to
go to grad school anyway. So I did apply for grad school in Egypt,
and I remember when I went to the university, I was like,
hey, I want to do a master's degree. They were like, oh, you're not
smart enough to do a master's degree because you did not score perfect scores in
all of the topics. Some topics you did not get perfect scores, hence
you cannot do a master's or
a PhD. You have to have perfect scores in everything to be able to go
to grad school. I was like, but the topics that I didn't get perfect
scores was not topics I was interested in, nor is it the topics I want
to do the master's in, so it does not make sense. But in Egypt they
were like, oh, just, you know, just go get married or something. Really, the
women, the staff in the universities in Egypt were
savages. I was like, just no. However, I
did kind of start outside of the university, kind of like a private
university. It's not really private, but like more like, hey, can I
pay? So I did kind of have like a job after graduation. I was,
I was an Android developer, so I was writing code for
Android apps. Feels like forever ago because it was
like 12 years ago. So that was in 2014,
right? So I did work there for 6 months. I had very
little savings because you're not— I was not getting paid good at all
because I was like newly grad. Like no one pays well when
you're no experience. And I was like, cool, I'm
going to do a master's. And I started a master's in
biomedical engineering actually, which was very interesting. It was kind of like
between medical, like doing medical tools,
but like from the engineering side, not from the medical side. But I was like,
oh, that's cool. I always like the intersection between fields. Like I like
interdisciplinary fields. That's why I like quantum where you can do a lot
in different ways and you just need like the core knowledge and some other people
who have different core knowledge and you work together, right?
But I only did that for like 2 months. While I was applying.
Then I got to know— I was attending so many,
how to say, workshops. And back then,
the webinars did not exist, but there are—
there was a group in Egypt called Egyptian Scientists, and
they would do online calls. Back then, it was like on Google
Meets, the old Google Meets. Again, it feels like I'm talking about ancient history,
but yes, back then there was no Zoom, right? So like,
and they would do these calls, which were mostly just audio about
some Egyptians who managed to travel and do science. And they mostly
were men, but like, like 90% of the time it was a man
telling a story about how he managed to travel.
And his only, his only obstacle was financial,
right? Which is, it was like valid, but as a woman, there's so
many other obstacles. Finance is one of them, but then there's culture that you're a
woman, you have to tell your parents, hey, I'm traveling. And your religious
parents would be like, oh, but you're a woman, you should not be traveling alone.
Like, there was like a whole thing that you had to overcome, plus the
finances, right? That was like a lot. But one of them
was in Japan, and he talked about how Japan was a
good choice because not a lot of Egyptians travel to
Japan for post— for like, you know, doing master's and PhD.
So there isn't as large of numbers like Egyptian want to
go to Europe or the US. So the chances of you actually
traveling will be higher because there isn't as many people
applying from abroad. And if you have like, hey, I'm doing— you can prove your
knowledge more or less, you— it's, uh, it's doable to go to Japan.
Also, it's like cheaper than to study
in the US, or in— I mean, then the US for sure. I
mean, you have scholars— you have to have a scholarship to go to the US.
It's very expensive if you don't. For Europe, there are some countries that
have free-ish university, but mostly for Europeans,
not for people coming from outside, right? So, and there's— we're talking about
currencies here. You have euros, you have dollars, and you have yen.
And the yen is like the cheapest. So it's like financially,
logistically, Japan made sense. I was always curious about
Tokyo because it's a gorgeous city. It was one of the cities I
always wanted to try living in. I had like a list. It was
Tokyo, New York, and London. And so far I lived only in Tokyo.
Maybe in the future I will live in London. Since I'm in the UK
and maybe somewhere in the future I will live in New York. I lived
in Chicago, close enough. Love Chicago very much, my favorite city
in the US. So I was like, okay. And then I
applied for grad school in Japan and I got in and I was super happy.
Like, I remember I had to convince my parents. That was, that was the
challenge. I was like, look,
Japan is safe, everything. It did help that I
was always the good child. That
makes sense. I was never the rebel. I'm the firstborn, right?
I had two younger siblings. I have my sister who's
2 years younger than me and my brother who is 10 years younger than me.
So my brother was— me and him, there is a whole 10 years
between us. It's hard to talk to him sometimes because different generations,
but you know, and my sister was the rebel, so she had a
lot of attention and I was always like just following the
path. Kind of thing, you know. So when I said, hey, I want to go
for school, my parents was like, did not have to
say, I didn't have to put a lot of fighting because they were like, cool,
like she's a good person, she's not like gonna go crazy or anything,
and she's a nerd, she's always studying and such. So it's like,
makes sense, I guess, that you want to go. But they were like, oh, but
you're coming back just after the master's, right? I
did say right, I did make a promise that I broke there. But I was
like, yes, I shall be back and I will be married and whatnot.
I will do whatever you want if you let me travel.
And I did not do what they want. I lied to them.
Not intentionally though. I had to say what I had to say to pursue
my dreams. You gotta do what you gotta do.
You ended up in Tokyo and you were pursuing your PhD.
Was there a mentor
at that time who really, you know, got
you and, you know, was excited about what you wanted to be excited about
and was working with you in your PhD? Was there anyone
like that in Tokyo that just kind of continued
to keep you going? So yes,
when I first moved to Japan, I mean, it was hard, but I was
very excited. I mean, it's a whole different language. It's a whole different
universe than Egypt, Japan. It's like it's their whole
thing. And then I go and there's like I have to learn some Japanese
and I have to kind of like adapt to the Japanese society,
right? And in my master's degree, at first I didn't have
anyone there, which was also like, you know, difficult. I didn't know
anyone. I didn't know the language. I didn't know the country. There was so many
unknowns, but I still was excited because I could be anything I want to
be. It's like a new start, right? Like no one knows me here, so
technically I can be anyone. I can be me. With no pressure
from society or religion or whatever, right? And that was great.
And I, when I went to Japan, I did not have a
scholarship, right? So I had to kind of pay
for school. However, I would say that the school where I did my master's
was a very nice school. They, if you can tell them,
if you can show them your finances, you can get exempt from paying the
tuition fee. If you have like a high school record,, and you
can prove like, hey, I'm a good student, I'm doing so much, but like, I
do not have the money, you know, but you have to prove that, and
your supervisor has to like be like, yes, she is doing great work,
look, like she has, she's going to conferences and such, right, and
doing publications. So, and then they can give you exemption from the
tuition fee, which is great, and they did all of my master's. I did not
have to pay for it, but I have to do a lot of classwork, right,
like you have to kind of balance it out. Yeah, and but you have of
course to get money somehow to live. That's like different thing, but I did not
have to pay for school and to live. I worked as so many things in
the school and I remember I was a TA for like 2
different classes. I was a transcriber for
like some research that was just interviewing people and I would listen to interviews and
type them down. That was one part-time job I did. I did a lot of
tutoring. It was fun because then I got to introduce to
the person who is still this moment is my mentor, and he was
not my supervisor at any point. He was just a
physics professor who I worked with as a TA
after like the moment I went to my— started
my master's. And he is actually an American guy
from Texas, so he was a Texan and he would walk around in
his cowboy boots, but he was one of the nicest people I've met. I mean,
he still is. I do not know why I said was. He is one of
the nicest people I met, and he was such an
encouraging man. He was like, yes, you can do this. I know it's
hard. And I literally worked as his TA the entire time
I was in that university. And he's the one who introduced me
to quantum and to my PhD supervisor.
So he had a huge effect on my life and how I
got here. I don't think I would have gotten here without him, so I'm very
grateful for him. So let me ask you, how do
you navigate moments when you feel less
confident, especially when the stakes are so high with what you're working
on? Ah, that's a very good question because I feel like
that all of the time. Imposter syndrome is strong in
research. Academia is a very fast, you know,
very aggressive, I would say, community environment,
right? Like you always feel like, oh my God, I'm working with those people who
are smarter and they work harder. I don't think I belong. There's always this
moment of self-doubt, maybe again because I've been told I'm not
smart explicitly to my face, right? So it's not like, hey, I'm
thinking crazy thoughts. But one of the things I do is
like, I like to take a pause and look at what
I accomplished. Where did I start and where I am
now? And remind myself that I wouldn't be here now. If
I didn't have what it takes to be here. Sure, I can be
like, people are kind, people gave me chances, people supported me, but in the same
time, it was like, the people wouldn't have supported me,
especially career-wise, right? Like, people wouldn't invest money in me if
I did not have what it takes, right? If they did not believe that I
can help them move their whatever
research forward, right? Their business forward, as for
like, no one gives people jobs if they're not qualified for,
right? So I was like, I have to remember that. I was like in this
moment of self-doubts and I can be like, oh, my boss is like super nice
to me. They're just nice. That's why they hired me. No, especially
in quantum, especially in stuff where they need outcome, right? It's not like
you're doing— they need outcome, they need work. So it's always—
I always stop and remember, hey, remember where I have
been in Egypt being told I'm not smart enough, but here I am now with
a PhD. Publications, worked with IBM,
worked with National Labs in the US, working now in one
of the top 50 universities in the world. It's like,
stop doubting yourself and like, be like, no, no, no,
I did that. I worked so hard and I deserve
everything I got. It's, it's, it's important, but it's something of course
that we forget every now and then when things get hard,
right? But It's— I always had very supportive friends
as well. Like, I appreciate them so much. I had amazing friends who were
always there. So in the moments where I couldn't stop and see
where I've— that all of the things I've gone
through, they were there. Be like, hey, in case you forgot how amazing you are,
we're here to remind you. So I had such supportive and amazing friends.
My friends are my family. I think of them as more family than my actual
relatives. Because they have been there for me in a lot of ways.
Like, they are my emotional painkillers, as I like
to describe them. I like that. I like that. So
they're fantastic. So let me ask you, when
you're facing doubt internally, what's your process
for deciding whether you should speak up or step
back? That's a good thing. And it's something I did actually think about a lot
because I feel sometimes it's good to know when to give up on something. Like,
it's like, this is not for me, it's taking too much energy and power and
I can't, I need to stop
back. I also do a lot of reflection and we're going to talk about
like purely career-wise, you know, I do a lot of reflection where I've
been, what is— so the moment where I decide to step back,
if it's, if I'm doing something I did not want to do but I did
because I've been told that it looks good, right? So
I don't like it, I've been told it looks good, but so I don't have
any passion towards it. And I'm neurodivergent,
so actually to do something I'm not passionate about requires a lot of
mental energy because every part of me does not want to do it. So I'm
pushing myself so hard to just do this thing because
it looks good. And I always step back,
and maybe more so now after my PhD than before I got it, and
be like, okay, Can I do something
that both interests me and is good for my career instead of
this thing that is taking too much energy for me to just get myself to
do it? Not even to do it, the thing itself, right? To get myself to
do it. And can I, can I find the thing that
intersects between what I like to do and can be good for my
career? And I always went for that, with the second option, because
then things become easier even if the problem I'm
working on, again, you know, quantum problem
or programming problem or even teaching problem, then be like,
cool, it's a challenge because it's something I like and I want to get better
at instead of me having to do something I don't like, even if it
pays more, even if it looks good. Both
these things never been motivations for me. It's like I have to be passionate
about what I do and then I give up. Honestly, it's not give up.
I change direction. That's how I like to think about it. I'm
changing direction and taking a different route to the same
destination, right? Instead of this route that maybe is
shorter, but let's say has a lot more obstacles, I can take the scenic route
to the same destination. Sure, might have to take longer. Maybe I will
do a little bit more work, but I will be happy doing it.
That's always like been my mindset when I choose what to do or what
the next step should be. Okay, so what
advice would you give someone who's curious about quantum but
doesn't have any kind of physics background? Oh,
I don't have any kind of physics background. That's what I tell them. I tell
them I am an electrical engineer who likes to code,
right? And I like talking about science, and I got
a PhD in quantum without actually having a physics background. I
work with physicists, But I feel like right now, I think
it's the best time for people who are curious about quantum to
get into quantum because right now it's actually outside
of the physics experimental realm. Let's put it like
that and more into application. So it
is as important to know how to use quantum as it is
to build it. And the physicists are taking care of the building
it. We need now people to focus on how can
I use it, which is still very under-researched, right?
Like we have all of these potential
for quantum to solve these amazing problems.
However, we don't actually know the extent of it, you know, right?
Like how far can I take quantum? It's kind of like when AI and
machine learning first started, like we did not know how far can we take
these tools. They were just in research labs being used by
just scientists, not by the normal people. But when people, the
public use them, then we got to learn more about them and
got to know new ways that we can utilize them, right? Same
with quantum. Like right now, I do more application
stuff in quantum. So it's like, what can we use quantum
for now? It's not like how we build it, or sure, I
can learn a little bit about how it works enough to know how to use
it. But like not enough to be like, I have to be like, go deep
into the physics. You can like, there's a middle
ground, right? Like the application is high and the physics is this
here. You can like learn a little bit physics to know how to
use quantum without actually knowing quantum.
Also, most of the quantum communities now are
very diverse because I feel like quantum is more of a tool because you
can use it to do different things. Sure, if you're really excited
about building an actual quantum computer, that's a different thing, right? Sure, you will need
to know physics, you will need to know a lot of
electronics, right? Because the hardware, but if you just want to use it and
be in quantum, like there is a lot of
need, right? The quantum field now is
very young and I feel it's still, it
has not matured yet. Even the startups, which is so
many of them, right, in quantum, they do not know
where they're going yet, right? Because the field is still new, so
they do not know who to hire yet. It's like a very weird
position, right, that is for quantum now. And most of the time
they're like, yeah, we want someone who has a PhD in physics, which I
know frustrates a lot of people, and I get it because it frustrates
me too because I don't have a PhD in physics. What are you talking
about? But I still can bridge
the, because the skills can be bridged into quantum, right? You do not need to
know quantum. I know a lot of people who were computer scientists that really
like software, and now they work in IBM Quantum doing quantum software,
right? Which is just building software for quantum, and they're
learning quantum as they go because they already have like the core skill, which is
they're very good coders. So they're building their quantum knowledge as they
go. And actually knowing quantum was not a criteria to actually write
code. For quantum, you just know how to write code and be curious about
learning the quantum side of things. So I feel like there's so
many quantum jobs that people can do and they
do not have to know physics unless they want to do research in quantum physics,
then they need to know physics. But if they want to just do stuff in
quantum computing, physics is, you know, preferable
but not needed. Okay. So what's
one piece of advice you'd give your younger self? At the start
of your quantum journey? Oh,
you are smart enough to do
quantum. That— do not give up. You're smart
enough to do quantum, especially quantum, because it's always— people be
like— people now, when they ask me for advice, they be like, I don't think
I'm smart enough to do quantum. It's like hard, right? And I
was like, sure. I mean, but I wouldn't say it's harder
than machine learning or AI. It's kind of like the same level of
difficulty, but people won't be like, I'm not smart enough to do machine learning, they
still do it. They learn programming and do it. It's just that
there's misconception about quantum. The word quantum somehow triggers
fear into people's hearts for some
reason. Yeah, I was like, no, no, it's not as bad as it sounds. It's
actually very fun. So how can
the quantum field become more welcoming to people from
historically underrepresented
backgrounds? That's a great topic. That's a topic I actually did some work on personally.
Well, some activities
towards, uh, I think because quantum is a new technology, so it's an emerging
technology, and unfortunately in the world that we live
in, the people who have access to emerging technology are often
the people with the most privilege. By the time those
people like become familiar with it, then the underprivileged
people, underrepresented in science, whether financially or
gender or sexuality, whatever aspect they're
underrepresented because of, by the time it gets to them, like, the other people who
have it easier have learned from it
and maybe progressed in it, right? So then you feel like
I'm getting there late, and I feel
it's— I don't know whose job it is. I want to say it's the
individual researcher jobs, the university's jobs, company companies,
jobs. I would say it's all, it's the ecosystem, the entirety of
it has a role to get the people involved,
right? Because a lot of companies
and universities will be like, we need more people in
quantum, but then they don't do anything about it. Now, sure,
they can be like, yes, we have like
IBM, for example, right? One of the things that they did that I
like, and they did a lot of things I don't like, but one of the
things they did that I like is that they do have free
access to the quantum hardware. It's not
like all unlimited free access. They give you like, I think, 10 minutes
a month, which is more than enough for you if you're
curious to learn how to use it. There is a
lot of companies are taking like, they're
doing educational content on YouTube and people can
watch it, watch it and like implement it, right? But
not any, I don't know of any other company who gives free access to
the hardware except IBM to the general public. Now,
if you're privileged enough to be in an institute that is, I
don't know, big and pays those companies to have access to their
hardware, it's different. But like, if, if I'm just curious, then what
do we do? I worked
with Argonne when I was in the US after my PhD for like
6 months. I did like a postdoc internship. I mean, I was
an intern, right? And I had a PhD and I remember
the manager, she was like, you're the most qualified intern I've ever had in my
life. And I was like, she always introduced me as this is
Dr. Sarah. She's an intern on title, but she has a
PhD in quantum. So she is not by any means an
intern. We, we were in Chicago, right? And we did intentionally go
to like the underrepresented, the
poor districts of Chicago. And we did give webinars and
talks about quantum and about science in general, right?
Because again, kids who grew
up in societies or communities where they're not given
the the options, right? Like they do not know that they can do quantum
because they do not know that quantum is an option, right? Not because they're
not smart enough. They don't even know that there exists a
quantum computer and that the field got this far ahead and you can
actually do it if you want to. So
there's that kind of like outreach that I like to do. I like
to, whenever I'm, someone reach out to me to give webinars
online for people, for students, in the Middle East,
right, particularly. And I was like, yes, for women, right?
Now I'm writing a funding proposal with two other postdocs who are also
women about getting more women into quantum, right? Okay, I like
that. So how do we go from even the middle and
high school girls? That's the level that I want to target,
right? Like from when they're younger and then the society still,
it's still pushing starts pushing self-doubts on them and tell
them that, hey, you know, stay out of the sciences because it happens everywhere in
the world. I lived in so many countries and it happens
everywhere in different degrees, but it happens everywhere. So
it's like, how do we get more women interested in science? How do we
make it more welcoming? And again, as I said, it's
hard because it's very still male dominant. I mean, I, in
my office now, all of the visitors are men. It's
still, still the numbers are still very skewed. So which means
there's so more work still need from us to do it.
And I, I hope that sometime that in the future I get
to a point where I have more influence and more
decision-making capabilities to, to make a change and
be like, yes, let's, let's do more
outreach. Let's, let's, let's tell people that it's an option.
So getting there step by step. I, I, and that's
another, another reason why, you know, I wanted
to start the Women in Quantum podcast. I want to
show who is out there, what they are doing, why it's
exciting, so that younger women can see
themselves in other women that are out in the field already and say, wait
a minute, I could do this, I could do that. I'm just like her. I
can, you know, and then feel less of a barrier to
entry. Yes, because they're hearing it from other women themselves, and I think that's a
way more powerful message to convey
from woman to woman. So let me ask you a little bit
about your, your current, the current research that you're working on.
So what is the focus of at the
Quantum Software Lab that you're working on? Okay,
so, oh, the Quantum Software Lab, oh, they do so much stuff. We do a
lot of stuff, not just software. But currently I'm working
on two projects. One of them
is, so I'm in the University of Edinburgh, so technically it's the
UK. And right now there are a lot
of hardware companies
that have hardware different kind of qubits. So qubits can be made
in different ways, physically speaking, right? And
each type of qubit have different
characteristics. So if I choose to make qubits, for example, let's see, IBM
and Google have something called superconducting qubits. There are ion
trap qubits. So there is companies that works on that. There is neutral
atom qubits. There's some, and there's new ones that people are getting, that's the
researcher coming up with. There's photonics, right? There's different kinds., and each one
of those qubits have different characteristics. So the way we
want to implement stuff on them, right? Because that's what I'm interested in,
right? Like say I have an application, a code that
does something, is it, it's gonna perform the same on all of these machines? The
answer is no, because the qubits have an effect, although
they're all quantum, but they all have different error rates.
They have different way they interact with each other. Some of
them has, they cannot hold their state for long.
Qubits are very sensitive, right? They're very finicky. You know, you have
to baby them. So it's like, okay, how they
don't hold it. So some of them can hold their
state longer. Some of them interact with each other faster. So it's like,
okay, how do I choose the right application to the
right hardware is kind of like one of the projects, but also
how do I benchmark the performance
of the hardware. So cool, I have this bunch of hardware.
I actually do not know, even if I choose the right application for
them, how do I know if it's good, good, right, or bad.
I'm not going to say bad, I mean the performance, like what can get better,
right? Like not like bad as in don't use it bad, but like
what is the— how do I evaluate the performance
of it. So one of it is like we're working with a group of people,
so we take their code. So people who already wrote application
and we test it on different hardware and see how can we optimize it
for specific hardware. We're working about if that process
can be streamlined, if it can be something— can,
can we write code that does that for us instead of
the researchers spending a lot of times doing that? Maybe the researchers
are not coders, maybe they're physicists or chemists or I
don't know, doing any of the life sciences, right? Maybe they work in
finance because quantum has application in finance and they do not know how to
do this optimization thing for the hardware. Can
we find a way to make this streamlined? It's like, hey, it's a set
process or a code that does it for you. Uh, the answer is still
unknown because it's research, but that's
one project. The other project is actually
an application which is about using quantum machine
learning for life sciences.
So like biochemistry or
biology, like detecting diseases like cancer based
on like a bunch of like cell imagery. Like you get a bunch
of cell imagery, can we use quantum machine learning to detect
it faster? How hybrid can we have like a
quantum classical machine learning algorithm? 'Cause quantum machine learning can mean so many things, it's
such a big term, but it's Mostly like have some quantum stuff,
some classical stuff working together to make something hopefully better
than just purely classical, right? Hopefully. And that's what we're testing. So you have to
try a couple of things and be like, is the performance better or should we
just stick to classical? Because it can be like, just
stick to classical 'cause it's doing better, at least for now,
because the quantum machines now cannot do much. They're still,
again, very faulty. So we're in a,
we're quantum computers now vis-à-vis hardware. It's called like
the noisy intermediate quantum, so NISQ, which is something that
a lot of people throw, which is because the size is intermediate and it's
very noisy. All of the hardware companies are trying to get to
a fault-tolerant quantum computer, which is like something
that is not, I don't wanna say not affected by error, but we have some
error correction and error mitigation technique enough that we can
eliminate the error and then we can fully utilize the qubits, right?
So until we get to that point, which we're not there yet, some companies
are super optimistic about it and they think they'll get there in like, you
know, by 2030, fingers crossed for them. I don't think they
will, but I'm gonna remain optimistic. Some people do
not think that we'll ever get a full-tolerant quantum. So we have the very optimist
and the very pessimist in that science field. And I try to stay
in the middle. It's like, we'll get there, But I think it will take more
than 4 years to get
there. So that's kind of like what I'm working on. I'm again, I'm writing
a funding about public engagement, which I'm planning
again with my colleagues about quantum and
young girls, young girls and women in quantum. How do we encourage people or just
the general public? We even going to go
give quantum talks in a pub because that's what people do here so
they can drink. While we yap about quantum in the background, they will learn a
thing or two, even if they're not paying attention. So,
and then, yay, mission successful, right? That's the whole point. We
want some people to know a thing or two about quantum so
they can be able to distinguish between the hype, which is there's so
much about quantum, and what actually quantum can do. That's
the goal. So what do you see as the most
promising near-term application for quantum
computing? Oh, that's a tough one. If you were going to just
say quantum and stop, and I was like, oh, quantum sensing, great. There's
so many applications for it right now. Quantum sensing
is the most of the quantums, right?
Because there's computing, there's sensing. Quantum sensing is the one
that actually have applications now, whether it's in like detecting diseases because
it's like little sensors. And I think
that Last year, there was a company— oh my God, I forgot the
name— an aviation company that used
only quantum sensing as navigation for the entire flight, and it succeeded, which
was great. So quantum sensing is one of the things that is super
overlooked because there's so much hype about quantum computing. There's also quantum
annealers, which also have great applications. Quantum computer is still there,
it's still young, but I feel
I would say like the, the, the one I'm
excited about the most is chemistry because drug discovery would be such
a great application if we get it to work. Oh my God, the amount of
lives that can be saved. But also finance.
So there's a lot of financial application to quantum,
like portfolio optimization maybe is one of
the things. So I feel like maybe those will be
the The two, I don't know, hopefully
near-ish terms for quantum computing once
we overcome all of the errors, which is kind of like the main
area of research. So many people are doing quantum error correction
and mitigation because we need to overcome the error so we can actually see
how far we can take the devices once the error is a little bit
more manageable. But yes, but quantum sensing, exciting stuff. I think people should read
more about it. It's such, overlooked again because there's so much
hype about quantum computing breaking the
internet and whatnot. So people are like, ooh, breaking the internet, oh
my God, scary. So it's not going to break the internet
anytime soon. I'd like to ensure everyone who's listening, not going
to break the internet anytime
soon. So, okay, so aside from that, it's not going to break the internet, but
let me ask you, so what's one misconception about quantum
computing you wish more people understood? That
quantum computers will never replace the computers we have
today. They will not. Quantum computers are good in
solving only one specific kind of problems. They
are not gonna completely replace it. And I know I might
break some hearts by saying that you will not have a quantum laptop to
play Minecraft on. I'm sorry, okay? I'm sorry to break it to you, but they
are good in solving One specific kind of problem which we
call the multivariable problems, which is a problem that you have
so many variables that affect the output and you want to
consider them all. The computers we have now
can do that, but it just takes forever to do them
because they're classical and they have to go one by one. But quantum,
because of the quantum magic, which is superposition and entanglement, can
do them faster. And I remember
When people was like, like, give me an example, right, about these kind
of problems. Uh, one of the fun examples that I've heard through years was called
the chicken in the grocery store problem, which is if I have
a grocery store and I need to decide how many chickens do
I need in a set day in the grocery store for people to
buy, right? How do I decide an optimal number where I don't end up
short or like having way too many chicken that goes bad? And there's
so many factors, more than people think, about how
grocery stores decide. And it's an optimization problem,
right? Basically, in computer science, what they're called, this category of problems. You
have to decide what day it is of the week matters. Is there
a holiday coming up? Is there a chicken
farm nearby? How many chicken farms nearby? How many trucks do
we have available? How long does the trip take?
From the chicken farm to whatever, the grocery
store? How many fridge spaces do we have in the grocery
store? There is multiple factors, right? And all of them
affect the number that I need to choose, right? So there are so many things
to consider. So you need to simulate for so many things to be
like, okay, maybe, I don't know, 500 chickens will be good for
a Tuesday. Like, to get to that number, right, you need to consider so
many factors.. And there are so many problems in life where we have like
so many factors, like the weather, predicting the weather.
There's so many factors and we're like, okay, we need to
consider them all. And quantum computers will be good in that type of
problems. That's why they're good in financial problems because there's so many
factors to consider when you're choosing a portfolio. So
many, too many, one may say. When you want to try to find a
drug, so many combinations between the chemicals that you need to discover. So
they all have the same background that we need to consider so many
things to do some math and then get the results. And those are the kind
of problems that quantum is going to be good in. So quantum will
never replace classical computers, they will always work side
by side. But I do not know, again, not to be a pessimist, but I
don't know if quantum will ever be a standalone thing,
which is like just without classical,
at least post-processing. I'm not sure. Hopefully, but maybe not
in my lifetime. We'll see. We'll
see. So beyond tech, what personal values drive
your work in science
and community building? Oh,
that's great. I would like— no, the reason I do all of the community
and outreach is because I don't think that tech or science should be for
specific people, which are the people doing it.
Because especially tech, especially tech, we are building products
for the people. How is the people not involved? How is just a
room of 6 people making decisions for the billions of people that
are going to use this product? So we need the
input from people. And I know that again, there
is the academia, there is the elitism, right? You're, if
you have a PhD or you're a professor, smarter than everyone.
There is the whole, uh, my beef
with scientific publication that is intentionally
difficult to read, intentionally hard to access for someone who is
not in the scientific field, just so science can
be this elite community that you need to suffer to get
into, which I hate with passion. I think science should be
for everyone because it is how we make society
better. For everyone. And tech and science, for me, they
overlap a lot. You need the science to build the tech, so you can't have
one without the other, really. So it's like, and you need tech to
advance science, right? Like, the relationship goes both ways. So it's
like, and we do that because of the advancement of
humanity. So how is all humanity should be involved to some degree?
I think people should know how their phone works to an abstract level. It's
like, how does this work, this thing that is a very crucial
part of our life. How can you not know how it works? And again,
a lot of tech companies and the tech world intentionally
want people to be left outside
of this knowledge circle, which I do not know because I think knowledge
is to be shared, not to be kept. And that's why I
like to share it as much as I can
to whoever listens. So, so, so what does success mean to you in the
context of a long
and evolving career? If I manage to
get people to, I don't know, overcome their fears and doubts about
joining quantum or STEM or tech, then that's success
for me, especially if those people are women
or young girls. I am,
whenever I volunteer to tutor or teach young girls how to
code and they then without me knowing, tell people that I am
a role model, or why they want to learn more about tech or
programming or computer science. For me, that's success. That's why I do this.
This and advancing science may be my measure of success.
It's not having a lot of money or having a lot of publications, which are
the measures of success in academia or industry, but the matter is like,
is what I'm doing— is what I do matter to the world, to the, to
the people? How can I make something
that benefits others? For me, that is the
definition of success. Okay. And as we're coming to a close, I have 2 more
questions I want to ask you. So what question do you wish
more people would ask you? And if you can think
of that question, how would you answer it? Oh my God. Okay. That's
a difficult question. I need to think about that one. What do I
want to be
asked? I want to be asked, how does
what you do matter, right, to the, to the
people, right? Like, not just for me to write a paper and keep my
job, but like, how does it benefit or
connect to the public, the people? That, that will be a great
question to ask. Or what do researchers actually do and
how does that benefit the people? That would be a great question because I feel
like a lot of misconception goes there. And then
I can start yapping about how we're building,
hopefully, the future of science,
or hopefully we're building the fundamentals, the foundation of how
do we build better tools that we use to save lives,
hopefully by finding out, again, faster drugs,
faster vaccines that can help people with quantum
chemistry or better materials. Because again, quantum can be used with
material science too. Build better machines that people can use to advance
their lives. So that will be a very interesting question. It will be hard
to answer because some research are very harder to connect to the public, but
it will be a challenge, a mental challenge. She was like, okay, I can answer
that. So that would be a very interesting question. Let me
ask you this then. What is the best piece of advice someone
has
ever given you? Does it have to be career-wise? No. The best piece of
advice that I've ever gotten is, uh, don't take
advice from people you wouldn't want to
live their lives, which I loved deeply because some people think that just because
they are in a specific state in society that everyone
want to do what they did to get there. So it's— and often their
advice does not apply to so many people. So I was like, do
I want where they're at? Do I want to be where they're at?
If the answer is no, then I will take their advice into
consideration, right? But it will not have to be the advice that I
actually take actions based on. Well, I
have to say thank you. This has
been very exciting, very educational. I have so many
more questions, so I'm, I'm absolutely going to want to have you back on. Um,
but I Really enjoyed kind of, you know, getting a sneak peek
into, into what you're working, how you're working, how you think about it,
how you think about the whole quantum computing industry
and the importance of having women recognized
and be interested in the field. That's just
so exciting. If people want to find out more about you, where would you
suggest that we send them to? I would say the most reliable
one would be my LinkedIn. So I'm on LinkedIn. I respond to my
LinkedIn messages. Because, you know, when you change jobs, emails change. So
LinkedIn is where you'll always find me. So I am on
LinkedIn. People can find me. It's Sarah A. Metwally, right?
A is my middle name initials. And I
try to answer as many questions as I can for the
people who ask. Thank you so much, Sarah. I really appreciate
this. I'm very excited. And I'm going to let— I'm going
to let our music take us out.