But one phrase they used to tell each other is like, I'm not going to
jail for you. Oh,
welcome to Women in Quantum.
Welcome to Women in Quantum, the series where we spotlight the
brilliant women shaping the future of deep tech.
I'm Candace Gilhooley, and in each episode we go beyond the
headlines. To explore the real stories,
career pivots, and bold ideas driving the
quantum ecosystem forward. Whether you're quantum
curious or already building in the space,
you're in the right place. Let's dive in.
Today we're speaking with Sierra Claus,
and she is a managing partner
at Barlow Ventures Studios. Hi, Sierra, how are
you today? Hi, Candice, I'm doing well. Thanks for having
me. How are you? I'm good. I'm really excited because I remember
quite a bit about our pre-call and I was
like, oh, this is going to be interesting, exciting episode. I really
want to talk about your journey. So let's
start at the very beginning. Can you tell me where you were born and
raised? Yeah, so I was born in Cleveland,
Ohio, but I ended up growing up in Denver,
just, just outside of Denver in Aurora, Colorado. It's interesting
to, to be an adult and have a family, have kids,
and make decisions about relocating and all that around career, especially because
that's how I ended up growing up in Denver. My parents had
at one point both worked for United Airlines. My dad actually ended up
retiring from there after 40 years, but they were
closing the office in Denver. In Cleveland and they gave him the option
to go to Chicago, Charlotte, Honolulu,
or Denver, with the added bonus that if he did
decide to go to Denver, he could help wind down Stapleton Airport
and be part of the brand new build of what would be Denver International
Airport as part of customer service. And so
he thought that that sounded like a great opportunity and there was so many people
moving to the area at the time. So I, I guess I kind of just
came from a background of people who would be willing to
take a chance, see about bettering, you know, things for themselves,
their families, and be open to those sorts of career pivots and those kind of
projects that could define the rest of your career.
OK, so as a young lady all the way back
in grammar school, what was your favorite subject?
Oh man, I think it was a tie between
English or language arts because I loved to read. Yeah,
but one of the things I really love to read was, I guess, more so
in the— it would, it would split between like history and geography,
that sort of thing, because I've just always been so fascinated with how
people have lived in different times and in different places.
Okay, so when did you stumble into science?
You know, it's interesting, it's less that I stumbled into science and more that
I developed an acute awareness that Everything comes from
something, you know? OK. And,
and when you look out into the world and you give yourself a pause to
think about how do things work, like when I was
growing up, we didn't have a computer in our house. There were only
computers at school. So I grew up in the '90s and our family
wasn't in a position to afford a computer, so we would use the computer at
school or we'd go to the library. And I remember thinking to myself like, man,
what makes these things so expensive? Like
they're not like a bike or like something else you could put on your, your
wish list and your parents would be like, yeah, that's, that's not like something you,
you're allowed to circle in the JCPenney catalog quite yet. It was
that time. And so as I grew up and I had more of that awareness,
I've just always been very curious. You start to realize that so many
of the kind of modern amenities or things that you think are really cool even
as a kid, there is like. This basis of
engineering and production and shipping and like all of
these components that go into the things that you like and use every
day. And for me, I kept finding that at the basis of the
things that I really liked was a bunch of science and engineering
and a lot, a lot of different systems that, that made all of that possible.
So where did you go to university and what did you major in?
So I did my undergrad at Ohio State. So I grew up in Colorado, came
back to Ohio to go to Ohio State. I studied in the business
school on a track specialized around supply chain and logistics.
Going back to the whole, like, everything comes from something, it's from
somewhere with a whole lot of someones behind it. So
I had an internship through the InRoads internship program, so I'm an alumni
of that. Incredible opportunity, and what it
does is it allows college students to
be sponsored by a corporation in a specific mentor
department. They focus primarily on women and
underrepresented groups at the time in engineering, business, and nursing.
So I was selected to be a part of the internship track
at what's now called L Brands, but at the time it was the
Limited and Limited Logistics Services. So that was
Victoria's Secret, Bath and Body Works, Abercrombie, Zombie Express, all of those
were under one roof at that time. But I was an intern
during a lot of that kind of retail consolidation, a lot of
things going to private equity, a lot of things spinning out.
And really having, you know, that was part of the experience was that
you'd be able to take on these different roles, do these different reports, and if
you were invited back every summer to be mentored and continue
your internships, you could be presented with a full-time offer.
And so I did that every summer. Through my undergrad,
and I was even invited to do a part-time HR operations gig
at the distribution center during a couple of the years I was at Ohio State.
And so it was a very hands-on contact sport,
a kind of, kind of way to see how things worked across. I had been
in regulatory and compliance, distribution center
operations, HR for that, upgrades of
systems where they're using sensors and conveyor belts and all of that to
really upgrade the accuracy of reading shipping labels.
And making them on like a streamlined optimized path between
inbound and outbound, and then all the different sort of operations and
things in tech that would support that. So technology at
that point was just embedded in everything that we did, and I didn't
realize at the time, because this was the early 2000s, I didn't realize at the
time how quickly the industry I was a part of
was moving into these sort of optimization models, and they were—
we were using simulators and we were using all these things around like
logistics and routes because the competition and the cost and everything. When you
looked at like UPS having the no left turn rule
or Walmart vendors and suppliers having to comply with very
specific like specs for the product shelves space that they were even
allowed. And then you look at inventory management, palletizers. There was
all these different things that had all these underlying technologies and
analytics. What people will call later that and
What was really fascinating to me, like looking back on it, was that you had
to have dashboards, you had to have numbers, you had to have
estimates, you had to have risk management. These are all things that were just part
of how you do like that, that whole domain of supply chain and
logistics and very applied in specific ways. It
wasn't until later that I understood that outside of
like logistics and supply chain, like marketing would then be
introduced to this concept of dashboard. As like a standard
practice. Some people call it the metrics, the
metricization of American business. So there was like manufacturing,
supply chain, logistics, finance. There was like a handful of industries in America where it's
like, well, of course you want the biggest, best, smartest
calculators and systems and data and all of that to
do that. And then that started finding its way into like almost
everything in the business world.
So, so I, I think about that a lot as we do
what we're doing with our venture studio and commercialization. Like how things actually
get out of these very niche spaces and
find their footing and their value and their application
in ways that are specific and tailored to, to other people who might find it
useful. OK, OK, so now you're
in logistics and business and business process
administration organization. So OK, and this is
undergrad, so Now what did you do for your
master's? Well, we do have a blip between the master's and
undergrad because, you know, the best laid plans of getting that full-time offer.
I graduated in 2008-2009. Oh,
OK, in recession. OK, that's right. So
yeah, so they had— so the company had already been consolidating and kind of spinning
off different things, and it wasn't that logistics and supply chain was going away, it
was just that roles outside the distribution center and some of that
seasonality wasn't, wasn't going to be as available. And so I took a break and
had my kids and stayed home with them for a
bit. And I spent a lot of time reading
because when I had 3 little ones at home, there would be times where the
only adult I would see was their dad and the
ladies I'd see at church on Sunday. And that, that would basically be it.
Make you go crazy. It really— that's right. Love, love, love children.
I have them. But yes, you need adult
interaction and adult conversations about all kinds of things
to stay sane, for sure. Yes, it's true. And I love Elmo. I
do. I still love Elmo. But there's a time and a place. There's a time
and a place, right? You know, and it's nice to wrap your mind around, you
know, real world, you know, real world problems and, you know,
adult situations. So I completely understand that. OK, so you
had the blip. Now you went— so, OK, so then you went to get your
master's. That, yes, so I, so I had, so in the
time that I was at home and I had a lot of time on my
hands and needed to do a lot of reading, I kept, I kept finding
myself really once again drawn to how,
like, yes, people promise technologies will be disruptive. But
then this is also a time where, like, the recession and lots of other things
like across housing, construction, supply chain, like all the knockdown
effects, retail. I mentioned my dad had— was at United Air
Travel. So my dad was
at United Airlines and serving in the best capacity he could. He actually got recognition
for supporting his coworkers and crew and a lot of people
after 9/11. And then from— in very short order, you go from that to what
happened in 2008, 2009. And it— and so when I
have this blip and I have this pause, I think about like what happened with
my dad's career. I thought about what was happening in all the careers around me.
I was, I was still living in Ohio at the time. There was a lot
of like offshoring impacts that were
happening like in parallel to all of this. So I, I really thought
long and hard about like what do I want to do when I go back
to the workforce? And if I do get something that would
help me advance like in terms of my education or career,
you know what, what, what would I want that to be? And
I ended up like in the course of thinking about this, I knew I wanted
to do something within technology because I wanted to
understand and maybe be like a more mindful part
of like how, how we implement these sorts of technologies and how
can we try to minimize some of this like job disruption and how can
we be smarter about like talent and skills? All of those things
were top of mind for me and a friend of mine at church had
offered to introduce me to some folks who had a managed service boutique IT
firm and she said like if you're, if you're interested, like she goes, I'm
new to IT as well and I got some great mentorship and. It would be
like in the recruiting area. And I was like, you know what, that,
that does interest me because I had that stint in HR operations at the
distribution center. I had done like hiring events, like all those
sorts of things as part of that experience. And I also wanted to understand like
what does it actually take to do these jobs? Like what are people hiring for?
Like what do they pay people for? What are their skills? And so I had
that opportunity. I was like, it was definitely, it was so
challenging. It was, it was a great learning experience. It was, it
was highly competitive because we were at a small boutique firm and you had these
like big, like sort of like consultancies
and talent recruiting firms like your Tech Systems and your Experis type, type
sort of organizations. And so like the, the kind of
speed and, and learning why you lost a deal, or even just
learning about like how do you even get into these vendor management systems to work
with these enterprises. All of those things, it was great
experience. They had some hard times as well there on their team,
so I ended up transitioning to a role where briefly I was working in financial
services. So I was at New York Life. I was getting my
series licenses, so I was working my way through it. I just had
got the one around mutual funds, and then somebody from the, the
IT recruiting team called me and said, hey, you know how we
used to recruit for those like project management roles and all of that with, with
our clients? I said yeah. They're like, they're actually looking for somebody who could be
new to tech. They want them to have a financial background because you're going to
need to own budget and scope and schedule. Risk and
contingency funds, like that sort of thing, and they can teach you the rest. They
have a pretty rigorous system. What do you say? So that's how I got my
first proper, proper IT role, was working in healthcare
supply chain logistics company. And
from there, that's actually when I decided to pursue my
master's, and I ended up being in a program for
what's called Master's of Science in Information and Knowledge Strategy.
Oh, OK, OK, so that's in one of the grad schools at
Columbia, the School of Professional Studies. So, and I, and
I chose that because, as the name indicates, right, there's a, there's a
science to how you take all this information
and knowledge that we are flooded with and how do you go,
how do you use that science and, and learn your own sort of art around
going from strategy to execution to operations.
So I had that kind of operations, bottoms up, middle out view.
But that strategic piece and having frameworks and knowing how to like
know up from down when you analyze a product or a new technology
and think about its downstream and upstream implications. So
that, that really appealed to me and I was able to get into the program.
And so I was, I was working as a— eventually got promoted to,
to a project manager. And so I was doing that and
going to school. OK, at the same time
and raising little ones. Yes, yes, it takes a
village. It was very much a team effort. I, I was fortunate enough to get
a fellowship from the American Association of University Women
as part of being in that program those couple years,
and I'm still friends to this day. I'm in the wedding party of
one of my buddies from, from that program coming up here pretty soon,
and that was over 10 years ago. So it's, it's true what they say. If
you find the right sort of program and the right sort of fit for those
things, you really can make lifelong friends. You can have these opportunities
that like not just change your life, but change the way you see the world
so that you can, you can just be more mindful, intentional
about where you want to go. You know, with, with a lot of turmoil.
I'm definitely one of those like millennial career women who like
turmoil has just been the order of the day. Right, and all
things work and it's just like what, which kind is it? You know, like I,
you know, I mentioned I grew up in Colorado. When I was 12, I was
45 minutes away from Columbine. And so we grew up under like that
zero tolerance thing at a time when kind of the rest of America was hoping
that was like a bit of a one-off. But, you know, so, but the schools
and the rules and everything that changed after that for us in Colorado was very
distinct. I would learn later, but I mean, it was Columbine and then it was
9/11 and then there was the financial crisis. And then, you know, we're
still kind of like kind of finding our footing after all of that. And so
I actually thought I had a bit of a break until 2020.
Right. And then I got a kind of break. Yeah, so, but, but, you know,
here we go again. So, but I, I only share that to say that
the, the thing about technology and just the way that the world was
working was it's just like you have to be adaptable. You can't not
be adaptable. I knew that there were a lot of people like
culturally, generationally, etc. And just honestly, like the hope
of like my dad where like you get to retire after 40 years with one
company, like And people like that, like people
have a lot of respect for and desire for like the discipline and
consistency and stability that comes with growing in a handful of roles
that you stay in for years and letting that define your career.
But from the time I was an IT recruiter, and I, I think even
more so now, there is always this risk of not just disruption, but
like obsolescence. Yes, yes,
and it happened so many times in so many ways, in so many,
like, things I've observed in the world and in my life, that I, I
just couldn't— I couldn't really, like, I guess,
accept that we were gonna ever go back to that, or that
that was like a thing that you as, like, a woman, a working
mother, can expect if you really want the job to even cover
the cost of your child care.
So anyway, I'm like, I'm just like, I'm like, I'm like,
I'm all about what you're talking about. I completely understand what you're talking
about, right? You know, like when I was in uni, like the
first positions I had, like didn't even exist.
Like everything kind of was made up. And then it was
recession after recession, you know, '07 and
9/11 and then, and then 2007 and then again.
And then you had pandemic and it made it very hard to get your footing
and be able to kind of nurture and build,
you know, a singular career path.
Right? Yeah. You know, like my father was an
IBMer. He worked there for over 35 years, right?
I grew up with the same kind of mentality, like my parents worked somewhere and
you thought, okay, I find somewhere and I work somewhere and then I
develop myself and I'm not leaving, but that's just not
the way it's done anymore. So, OK, so now, now do
you— so when did quantum enter
your world? Yeah, so yeah, this, this is the
fun part. So I, I graduate, I'm
from Columbia, I get an opportunity to join EY
as a consulting gig. They were one of the capstone sponsors, not, not my group
sponsor, but one of them. It's, it's, you know, it's why you go to these
programs. You hope you can get that aligned next step
up in terms of your experience and career. And then I
found myself very, like, very quickly working with some of like
the Microsoft track folks and all of that. And I ended up relocating
in 2019 to Seattle from Ohio. So, so
that big move, that's, that's the big move that kind of catalyzed— big move, big
move. And I, and, and I had always kind of— I had been in emerging
tech without knowing it. 'cause as I had said, like the whole like, oh,
like we're going to do big data and analytics and I'm like, oh, I recognize
this stuff from logistics, but the rest of the world is just like, hey,
like what is this IBM Watson? Like what is this Hadoop thing? Like how do
we use it? And now that stuff just like runs in the
background. You can have all these APIs. You know, so it's
so, so, so I, I hadn't known that, but by the time I moved to
Seattle and I'm working at Microsoft, I'm working in the field with
enterprise customers. And then I get an opportunity to move to a
global strategy team doing playbooks around, once
again, a new technology, a new feature in Microsoft 365 security.
So I'm right back onto here's a new thing that somebody built, it does cool
stuff. How do we get people to know it, use it, like it, buy it
kind of thing? And then I had an incredible opportunity to go to Xbox.
Which was— I mean, all the things we're talking about were at
like at play there, no pun intended, but it was just so fun.
I— it was the first time I had worked at a technology, like,
based company that is not only not perceived as
technology, it's gaming, right? It's not the tech, it's what you do with it. And
what you do with it is game, and there are communities. And it's one of
those things where you're working on something that is so loved,
like, so loved. I, I've only had the chance to work on
enterprise tools that were on their best day, like, tolerated, you know,
right? And people cannot wait to log off, take their PTO, put that out of
office on, they're done. And this was a place where people would want to
log off at work so they can log in and play. And I, I loved
that. And it was, it was during this time that, um, I had been approached
with an opportunity to, uh, to join
a blockchain startup that was spinning out of Meta. And
this is where it gets interesting because I was starting to be very
interested in, um, security. I'm starting to, 'cause it
was modern work and security and, and so much
of the rightful customer questions and enterprise rigor.
It was, it was a lot. It was less of like the sales team having
to get budget and all of that, and it was more the security folks wanting
to be like, hey, do we have the right like granular controls
for this subscription tier that we're looking at? And
then, and then within gaming there was obviously their security around like
credentials and people's money and like all of that. And you know how they payment
methods in Game Pass, but there was also Xbox player safety.
My kids love Minecraft. We got a chance to like tour the Minecraft studio. They
take that stuff very seriously, and so there's all these technical security
components to that as well. And so by the time I'm looking at this blockchain
startup, I'm thinking about security. There's a big focus on like decentralization
and privacy. There's definitely a gaming use case, and then
there's cryptography. Because
blockchain. Exactly. And so, you know, I, I guess
I put that out there as a plug to some of my, my, like, the
blockchain friends or some of the Web3, etc. people. It's like, you know, please
remember that blockchain is not just crypto. Blockchain as an applied
technology has cryptography, and this, this era
that we're going into is going to make cryptographic proficiencies of all
kinds very important as
we, as we think about how we're going to navigate a lot of of these
like, these threat cases is what I call them, right? So you have your use
case, but there are threat cases. So whatever, when we think about
something that's a tool, there are ways that you do need to think like a
bad actor in ways that it could be weaponized.
So anyway, that's kind of how like my curiosity, I
didn't know that I was on that quantum track looking at
security and cryptography until it like clicked. Because
it's like you said, like the words and the terminology and the language for it,
it didn't really exist, or like it at least
hadn't like reached my bubble or like any sort of mainstream or
like kind of critical mass for people to know like, oh, that's what that is,
right? Like that's, that's what we're talking about here. And so, um,
it was during that time with the blockchain startup that I met my current co-founder.
Um, so he was, he was working, um, and not just working, he was, he
was managing and had founded a really amazing, uh, marketing agency
that was doing all kinds of like just— it was really like a creative studio
that was doing amazing things around branding, in-person event activations. So they were
doing a lot of this ecosystem work where things were just a lot
easier, cooler, and more fun the way that they
would introduce people to these different products and
experiences. And so I really love that about what
he, what he was able to do and what he was working on. And we
just, we had just stayed in touch over the years. I always give him kudos
at this part of the story when people ask about how we met or know
each other, because he was literally one of the guys, one of the few guys
that I met that like, he liked, he loved
his wife, his wife loves him, he loves
his kids, his kids love him, and it's, that's still the case
to this day. And it was honestly just so refreshing to be around something like
that, particularly like at that time within like very tech
bro like that, that sort of like kind of heavy crypto
culture. Okay, okay, that's fair. There is a very
tech bro culture in crypto. You're right,
you're right. So that probably was very refreshing.
Yeah, yeah, he stood out for all the right reasons, as well as like the
guys that he, that he hung out with. So, so,
um, so that was, uh, that, that's one of those things when
people talk about the intangibles you know, like, how do you know you can work
with a person? How, you know, that kind of thing. And for me, I,
I, I get very uncomfortable when we kind of have this abstract idea of—
I don't know, I don't know, Candace, I feel like you and I might be—
we could do a whole separate other episode around how, you know, how we remember
how back in the day we talked about business ethics.
When's the last time you heard— see, you see
it like— so this— so, you know, Especially, well, think about what's going
on with AI. I mean, think about what, you know, like, like,
you know, Musk's new, you know, AI engine that, you know, will
create nudes. Like, why? Like,
there's— why? Like, you know, there's, there's no—
like, where are the brakes? Where is the
governance? There are— there needs to be rules
because there are bad actors who will who will do things and we
need to protect people. I, it's just, it's the
technology is moving so quickly, right? Yeah. And yeah,
and, and that was it. Like, that was, I mean, and it's interesting too, right?
Because within like the blockchain space, etc., I
mean, this has actually been in the news. This is actually somewhat contemporary where
part of the reason I was so interested in blockchain as a,
for a tool to democratize, like getting people access to finance,
right? So, so even now, um, I've advised on and like talked to some folks,
it's like, we're like, oh, like stablecoins, crypto is a Ponzi scheme in America.
And it's like, well, if you're in Bolivia or if you're in Argentina, um, if
you're— there's places where having a stablecoin and it has like backing and
liquidity and stuff and it keeps its price and you can transact in it
better and more reliably than what you have going on, uh, that's a big deal.
Like, that can be life-changing for you, right? That's why I spent a lot of
time when I was in blockchain abroad. And there's nothing illegal
about like getting people access to like the financial sort of things that they
can afford. That's why it was called decentralized finance, right?
Exactly. But, but what's in the news now is like people like myself
and my co-founder and others who are working in the space around those sorts of
applications. We always had— we were always constantly up against this whole thing
of like, well, you know, that's the Silk Road currency, right? That's black market,
gray market stuff. Like what's happening, this whole like tragic situation
with, uh, the kidnapping of Savannah Guthrie's mother, right?
They asked for the compensation in Bitcoin and people are like, oh yeah,
like all that stuff is criminal. It's like, well, that's, you know, that's how
you're socialized, right? Like, if that's how— and I mean, because that's the thing, you
could say that about honestly any form of money. I, I don't know a form
of currency that isn't used and implicated in criminality anywhere.
But when people don't know, or you can have use cases and
then you can have something that's useful to them. And so that what I just
shared with you about people who don't have access to a credit union or Chase,
you know, people don't have the FDIC. That's an American institution, right?
Right. You know, like, we— like, they don't have it. Lots of countries, they don't
have something like a Federal Reserve. They don't have, like, like, these. And even
if they did, they just now got, like, access to, like,
internet sometimes, and they're dealing with rolling blackouts.
How do you create a financial sort of access point
and system for folks in those austere environments?
You know, and so, so anyway, so I think about this stuff because it's like
going back to like this idea of ethics and like what you can do with
technology. And to me, like the green flags, I mean, I
think all of us can name our yellow and red flags about what we're comfortable
with and who we do and do not want to hang out with. But I
bring up the thing around like ethics and like, you know, how I was confident
when my, my now co-founder approached me about the venture
studio. I don't think I don't really like this whole thing
where we don't even talk about ethics, we just talk about compliance. Okay,
right, right. It's like we don't, we don't do things like on principle, we do
things based off of what we can and can't get away with. It's kind of
what that implies, basically, right? Right.
So I'm not a fan of that. And maybe it's because like I have kids
or whatever, but to me it's like I don't think I should be in business
with people like in close proximity that way that I would not want
like my kids around. I think that's totally fair.
I think that that's a hard line to draw, but I
think that if you want to raise your family in a certain way and you
want to live by a certain set of ethics, then it should spill over,
you know, what you do in your personal life and in your business life. That,
you know, you've gotta, you've gotta feel like you're doing the right thing on both
sides. And if you're not, then you're doing— obviously you're doing something wrong.
Right? I mean, well, yeah, and it's, you know, it's, um, I,
I did advise a company briefly, or organization,
I should say, where, um, you know, sometimes when they call you in as a
consultant, you are accidentally like a family
counselor, right? Like you're, you're just thrown into all the dysfunction. Like that's part of
why you're there. It's like you're supposed to be a part of a team that
helps people navigate all this dysfunction, a lot of hurt feelings, sometimes a
lot of bad blood. That kind of thing, and
try to reset, find a path forward for whatever, you know, you've been assigned to.
And I remember there was this one, this one organization was really rough like that,
but one phrase they used to tell each other is like, I'm not going to
jail for you. Oh.
And while on the one hand it's like, yikes, like I wish
that was like not in like the chat on a regular basis, but like.
But like going back to what we talked about, like turmoil and
desperation has many outlets, you know, and, and
the risk. Like I think we used to talk about some of this thing we're
talking about, like personal ethics and all this and who we work with, especially with
new technology and like money and hype cycles. When
those things kick up, there are people who do overreach.
There are people who do. It's called a Greed and Fear
Index for a reason. Right? So when that greed and
fear index thing kicks up around the thing that you're working on, and I promise
this is going to get to quantum and why this stuff is important to have
many people, is that we know time and time again
that that greed-fear dynamic, it leads people to make some pretty risky
choices that other people around them may or may not know
about, that other people around them may be forced to aid in a bit.
And you know, some of the turmoil you and I have been talking about in
our careers, you see the collateral damage, and it
is a lot of like women's careers, early career folks,
you know, that kind of thing. Older, older workers who are closer to retirement.
There's a certain kind of worker who is most at
risk for the shakeout of those sort of greed and fear
and desperation responses. And And so
I, I do think it's good and healthy as we talk about
innovation and we talk about security and we talk about bad actors.
You know, one of the things that we all the time in cybersecurity is the
insider threat, right? And so it's like,
you know, the more promising and high potential something is, the
more it draws in that kind of attention and those
sorts of elements. And I, I only wish that, um,
maybe, maybe somebody like you, Candace, had a podcast like this, and I, and I
was maybe a little younger, but maybe you'll reach somebody now. And somebody
would tell me like, hey, sometimes you are going to have to have standards. Like,
if I don't want this person around my kid, I only want them this far
into my circle, right? If, um,
if I have to ever be tempted to say the phrase, I'm not going to
jail for you, it's already gone too far.
100%. Uh, uh, 100%. I,
I totally understand what you're saying, and
it kind of blows my mind that you, you actually saw that on a
chat internally. That just would give me
pause to say, what's going on? Like,
what's, what's really going on here, right?
Yeah, I mean, and, and that's the thing, right? Because when— as soon as that
happens, As soon as that happens, it's like, oh man,
do I even want to know what's really going on, right? I'm like, I don't
know, I think I want to even know, right? I just know that I want
to see my way out of this, right? Yeah. And you know, this,
this, so, so when, so this does get into
like, you know, how I find myself fully like bought into like what I want
to work on within quantum technology and emerging technology because
as I'm at that blockchain startup and I'm traveling and we're looking at like all
these things around, ecosystem. There's these different Builder House events
we would do around like more specific education
hackathons. I was on the ecosystem program that
worked very closely with developer relations, and then we also had a grants
program as well, both academic and for our
ecosystem tools. And also just like high
potential projects. And so I'm working on that, and then I'm also working on a
cybersecurity engagement. So I'm starting to do some freelancing. And so
the, the, that conversation we just had about like that human side of ethics,
human side of risk, this is where the cybersecurity,
privacy, all of that really starts to become very important to me
because I'm starting to see the whole thing of you have shadow IT.
For those of you who don't know, shadow IT is the thing where you work
somewhere, uh, your identity management,
CISO, security people are like, sorry, you can't download that
on your work computer, or you can't, you know, you need admin permission
to add this feature, do this thing. And you say
Aba, and you go and get, you go and get it and use work
stuff, credentials, content, documents, whatever you want to do, just
outside of the digital estate, the ring fence of the systems
that your admin hard stop said you couldn't, couldn't have it. So
there's a whole kind of, so that's one kind of concrete example of shadow IT.
But by the time I'm working on the cybersecurity stuff, we have full-blown shadow AI.
Oh, absolutely right. 'cause people are not just like,
you know, getting like free freemium kind of like AI subscriptions to
work on things, but they're also like they got open source stuff.
Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. So, so we're,
so I'm, I'm looking at that and I'm, I'm still like
somewhat connected to Johnny and when he reaches out to me and we, we were
working on primarily like state, state, federal,
like the state, local government kind of and, and Occasionally we try to pitch to
federal sort of contracts in terms of like moonlighting and who you'd want
to like talk to. But this was, this was
2024 and the writing was on the wall that maybe even cybersecurity wasn't going to
be safe from a lot of US government budget turmoil, right?
Right. I knew people at the time who felt differently, and I think maybe if
they— less that they felt differently and more that they hoped
differently, that they were like, you know, if there's one thing that's going to like
stick it out through like this transition period with the new administration, it's going to
be cybersecurity. And then it
wasn't necessarily the case.
And so I saw that coming.
Johnny had approached me and said, hey, I think there's some real there there what's
happening in quantum technology around specifically what's
available to be commercialized. And
I'm exploring doing like this venture studio model. I'm talking to somebody
who has worked in these funds and like all that sort of thing before. Would
this be something like you'd be interested in? Because you're the first person I thought
of in terms of like if we're going to do this thing like end to
end and like figure out who and what it takes.
Like, I'd like— I'd love your, your help with that. And so I took the
holiday break to think about it. And so I did. I decided to like wind
down my role, like doing like the moonlight contracting in cybersecurity with that particular
group. And then we launched Barklow about a year ago now,
and that has been Absolutely fascinating because when you
come into quantum technology from the perspective of like, hey, like
these are like these papers that are looking good, like I'm seeing like these different
like companies of various sizes, you have different funds, and
then if you're like me, you're like, great, what can I log into?
And folks are like, ah yes, about that. Yeah, not quite, not
quite. And so I'm like, great, that's why we're here.
So, so yeah, so that's, so that's how
we found our way into, into what we've been building. And then it's really
kind of taken on a life of its own as we use our
methodology. Our big focus when people say like, what does commercialization
mean to you? That's a big word. Means kind of like an inkblot test, right?
Like it means different things to different people when you hold it up.
To us, particularly for like what Barclo focuses on with Quantum and
critical tech research, roadmap, revenue.
That's what commercialization means to us. So research
comes from the basis of science. Science is never through because we are
mortals, currently constrained by space and time. So
there's always going to be more to learn about the world around us
and the world within us and the materials we're made of. So that's science.
But then when you get to the roadmap, that's when you can start engineering from
science. Into specific technologies. And
that's that, that part right there, right? It's like
when you go to look at foundational science
and you go to apply it, that's when you can start that
kind of engineering, like that roadmap sort of lens on it. And then from
there it's like, well, I, I think people here want to get this out into
the world and get adequately compensated for it. So then that's, that's what we can
get to to that revenue part. But that is the supply
value chain and lifecycle like unto itself
in terms of just even using that, that kind of framework for, for how we,
how we assess things and pursue them.
So let me ask you, so every deep tech career hits
bottlenecks. You know, what is, what has been your most
frustrating stuck moment and how did you work your way
through it? Man,
it's, you know, the thing is, is that what,
what could have been perceived as a bottleneck when we started this
work, and it definitely created a lot of friction for sure,
is really just that as soon as we started the Venture Studio and we
just even soft launched that we were like looking at doing this, there
was excitement. Like, like in terms of like our community and all of
that, because we're right now the only venture studio like in our region and in
the Pacific Northwest that even focuses on quantum tech and like critical
tech applications specifically. And we were, you know, of course, like we're new
people, you know, they're rooting for you. They hope you make it like, you know,
they're like, I'm not really sure what a venture studio is. So there's like excitement,
there's hope, there's good vibes. But then there was also like
the realization that like, hey, like, You guys, you guys want to do this now
when Washington State still doesn't have a quantum hub?
You know, and many people have tried, right? Like, people have
like worked very, very closely with, with who they could,
when they could, how they could. And you know, they made
organizations and they've made pitches and proposals and all of that.
And so, you know, it's one of those things where, and I think this happens
like honestly with all sorts of things in innovation, right? Where it's like, like, how
are you going to make it and how are you going to hang in there
when, like, it feels like everybody else is kind of, like, striking out,
like, despite, like, their best efforts? And, you know, we
didn't— we couldn't really, like, answer that question per se,
right? Because it's like, first of all, we're just getting started and we're
still, like, learning and discovering, like, how we want to do this. But, but
second, you know, on the one hand, you could look at it like we're
making this regional play and that isn't here yet in our backyard. But the
flip side of it was by the time we were looking at Barclo, like there
was like a dozen states that did have
programs and hubs, right? Maryland, Colorado,
like what's going on in Chicago and Illinois, New York, New
Mexico. So like there were things.
So, so I think that, that was the one thing where it was like,
you know, I, I was excited
to show people that we don't have to like wander in the dark.
You know, success leaves clues and you know, there was just such a low awareness
that, you know, there were those sorts of hubs that you could be learning from.
So that, that's kind of how I took it. It's like, yeah, like, is that
a bottleneck? For sure, in terms of like scale and traction and
what's like kind of in the advantage of these other states and their initiatives.
But we now have like several years, like a couple years I should say, of
data from multiple deep tech hubs
that we could learn from. And I actually, I actually credit like that sort
of like body of work with how we were able to make heads or
tails of like directionally, like how do we assess like where
we fit and what we want to work on and really like make that roadmap
ourselves. Because I would like to use like Colorado, you know, I grew up
there, but for you, like, you know, their translational funding,
the way that they are so intentional and structured, I mean, CU Boulder, I think,
is up to like 10 unicorn spinouts alone.
That's across deep tech areas, right? And then I gotta give a shout out to
my buddy Jason Yeager and everybody out in Montana, the Montana Photonics Hub.
Amazing work going on in Montana. And so it's one of those
things where, once again, you know, if you wanna, if you wanna go fast, go
alone. If you wanna go far, go together. And so, so
it's like, hey, you might not have that in your backyard, or maybe your company
doesn't have like a quantum initiative, your state,
your or whatever doesn't. But man, this is a big world and there's a lot
of countries, over 40, that do. And there's a bunch of states that do,
and you can learn from those folks. And they're actually really cool and really helpful,
by the way. And they're excited to hear more and more people want to learn
from them and, and especially learn from their mistakes and their frustrations.
So from your vantage point, what separates deep tech venture
building from traditional startup building?
I, I say in the US it will all building in like
many things in life, everything has to do with context. OK, and I
think in this case in the US the context of
regular venture, regular, regular venture, like
venture in the US that has had
like an established kind of like track record model,
etc. Has been very software-oriented in
tech. Okay. And
so when you have an industry that looks to de-risk and
analyze and kind of pick winners based off of
historical lagging indicators,
and particularly lagging indicators around things more like software,
or like in some cases like consumer packaged goods, like that sort of thing. As
soon as you call it, I know some people call it deep tech. I kind
of have started referring to it as more built world.
OK, and the reason I use that turn of phrase is because like, well, first
of all, like kind of like Internet of Things used to be Internet of Things
and now that's just Alexa. I think that deep tech is going to take
that same track where we used to call it deep tech and now
it's just like, like, well, like, well, of course, like we need that for
satellites in space. Like, like, you know, of course I need that for like
my internet, like my modular energy kind of thing, right? So
yeah, I think, I think that that's part of it. There's this, the software piece
that detects like just what we consider is going to
change, but also like the economics, the cycle time, the
implications, the talent needed for software,
fundamentally different than things you need for the physical world or things that
have a huge dependency on a physical world hardware component.
And I, I know some people are like, well, just call it hardware. I'm like,
well, Well, I, we've tried that and what happens is you say hardware and people
are like, oh, so you mean like chips, right? You mean like, well,
what do you mean when you say hardware, right? Right. It's like I try to
use something more inclusive like physical and built world because like
you're like these like headphones, right? Some like people are
like, oh, like that's auxiliary equipment hardware, right?
But there's also these like, like really cool like
sort of like the way that you have like the VR immersive reality AR like
headsets, they have versions of those and kind of like the Google Glass sort of
thing for mechanics working on engines.
Okay, right. So that's an application of all these
different types of technology, and people still don't think of that as like hardware per
se. But the cycle time to have a quality product like that,
figure out who's gonna make it, who's gonna buy it, how much is it gonna
cost, like once again that commercialization side like for software,
the friction points, the cost, like that physical, the physical world
constraints just aren't
there the way that they are in deep tech. And so I think that
that sort of thing where you're talking about like everything from
timelines to like the ramp-up cost, that's the thing everybody always talks about is like
the upfront capital to even get started with this stuff
is a big barrier to entry as well. And so yeah, I think, I think
it's those sorts of like functional, financial,
operational, etc. differentiators. And then with it is
the risk, right? So some people don't, don't really want to stomach the
risk of like a failed, like these failed prototypes,
etc., because like that, that's kind of like one of those sort of sunk cost
things. And this is also why, you know, governments and like the
US, you know, we have these like grants and everything really starting to kick up.
Nondilutive funding to help underwrite some of those risks,
because our grants programs like that have known
for a very long time that what the market will bear
doesn't necessarily align with what we probably
can and should be working on. But businesses and
budgets and all of that don't necessarily want to take that
risk, or necessarily should, right? Because they're accountable to investors, shareholders,
etc. That, you know, that's not necessarily in thesis
or what they signed up for. Let me ask you
this. What misconceptions about quantum investing do you
encounter the most often? That everything's a computer.
And until we have the big, the big one, nothing,
nothing works. Nothing's ready. Okay. Very, very all or
nothing. And also very like only computer.
So like I ask people about like, well, what do you think about like quantum
sensors? And they're like, What are those? And
I'm like, awesome. Like, here, let me show you a couple
examples. So, so I think that's one is
that the, the, I think the primary kind of
like education or awareness for a lot of investors, even like an emerging
tech around quantum, is the news cycle, is the US news cycle,
at least like where we're at. And so if you're only looking at the US
news cycle and you kind of train your algorithm to give you those sort of
updates or whatever about it, you're seeing like stock news about D-Wave and
IonQ. You're seeing stuff about like IBM and
HSBC and their latest thing. You're seeing like, that's what you're seeing,
right? And so some of the stuff like
that really lives like behind the curtain, even if it is useful,
successful, etc. Like you're not going to necessarily see it until it's like
newsworthy that way. And it can create this perception
that if it's not in the news cycle, Or if like my, you know, my
timeline and people are like still debating about it, there must not be,
be anything out there to use or buy. Okay,
so I'm going to ask you my last question is there's a lot of quantum
corridors that are, that are populating
around the world. Do you,
where do you see the most, the next unexpected quantum hub
emerging? Ooh, like around the world
or like within the domain? Let's say
around the world. Hmm, you know what, I, I,
I can't answer that question yet. But
I will say this, I will, I think I will have a bet. I will
have some, some contenders in mind very shortly
because I'm actually leaving for Japan tomorrow. Oh my gosh,
Japan, there's so much. In Japan.
I'm like, I want to talk to you after you come back. Yes, I was
going to say, I was like, so I'm going to— I haven't been there yet,
but like, I haven't. So I've been there for leisure. I love it
in Japan. I'm leaving for a trade delegation, Quantum Ecosystem
trade delegation trip. Awesome. That Barclay was selected for. We were
so excited. We were one of 15 organizations, companies like
enterprises, that kind of thing between US and Canada that were selected to go to
this one. So, so I'm heading to Japan tomorrow and then I'm also
part of Quantum Tech World Boston and
there's a whole bunch of amazing folks from national labs and quantum
corridors who are planning to be there. And I'm serving on the
startup advisory board. So we're preparing— excuse me,
we're preparing to do some like VIP events. We're excited
to meet so many people. If you just Google Quantum Tech
Boston 2026, you'll see it. Peter Shore is the
keynote. I know, like,
come on. So anyway, what I'm saying is I'm going to have a much more
informed answer here in the next few months, but I think
more than like what's unexpected, like surprise, like, I mean,
one of the things I tell people, it's like, yeah, they're like, oh, you're going
to Japan for quantum stuff. I'm like, yeah, like they built their own quantum computer,
like in-country, vertically integrated. And you know me, like, I like supply chain
logistics, the Toyota way. They do it, they lean it out. That's where we
get Six Sigma, you know, the land of kaizen. So
I'm geeked for lots of reasons. And so, um,
so I think that that surprises people even here, uh, that, that, you know,
that they built out that capability and now they're thinking about talent, they're thinking
about materials, they're thinking about like all those things. And they're thinking about, hey, we
built the computer, what do we run on it? Uh, which is where we come
in and love that stuff. And so that's why I asked if you want to
like surprise and be domain, because I think that that's going to be where the
surprise is going to come from. It's going to be on like this data
layer and like people realizing like, oh, like if you build a
MacBook and you don't have like a suite or like an internet connection, like
what, like what are you gonna do with the computer, right? So like it's a
really pretty paperweight, you know. Yeah, yeah. And so I think like that, and
particularly I think that we are going to see some like
application algorithms, that sort of thing. And what's really gonna surprise people
is they didn't even have to know it was quantum to like it and to
know it was really cool. Oh, that's fantastic. That's, that's my
prediction. This has been such a great conversation.
Where can people find out more about what you're doing
currently? Where can I send them to? Yeah, so
definitely you can send them to our website. It's barclow.ventures.
You can find me on LinkedIn. I'm posting on there pretty much all the time.
I'm doing the building out loud sort of thing. And yeah,
I'm happy to follow up with you as well, Candace,
if your listeners have any specific questions. That's
excellent. I think you and I are going to be chatting, I hope anyway.
Absolutely, because I want to hear about how the trip goes and what happened. I
just, I want to be involved. So we will be speaking again for
sure. I— you were a fantastic interview. I really
enjoyed— I really enjoyed our conversation. I really— Candace, this was a
lot of fun. I hope it was helpful, and I hope to see you guys
around. Excellent. Well, thank you so much. I'm gonna let the music
take us out. Oh yeah, thank you again. I
really, really appreciate your time today. It was wonderful, and
enjoy your trip, and I want to hear all about it. Oh, thank you so
much. So this was a lot of fun, and yeah, I hope— I hope that
the audience likes that we just got— we had like a little Quantum Ladies talk.
Honestly, we did. It was wonderful. It went like that. It flowed.
It was beautiful. I really, really enjoyed it. And I really like your perspective. And
that's what I think is so important, is just to show the different perspectives that
there are. And people, younger ladies, can find the data
points that match with them, that they're like, they can relate better. So this
was exactly what I was going for.